<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Biomarkers &#8211; SiPhox Health</title>
	<atom:link href="/hub/category/guides/biomarkers/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/hub/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 14:47:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Carbon Dioxide</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/carbon-dioxide/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 19:11:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3839</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is CO2? CO2 (carbon dioxide) is a blood biomarker that measures the amount of carbon dioxide in your blood, primarily in the form of bicarbonate. It helps assess your body&#8217;s acid-base balance and can indicate respiratory, metabolic, or kidney issues. Understanding CO2 as a Blood Biomarker CO2, or carbon dioxide, is a waste product&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/guides/biomarkers/carbon-dioxide/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Carbon Dioxide</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is CO2?</h2>
<p>CO2 (carbon dioxide) is a blood biomarker that measures the amount of carbon dioxide in your blood, primarily in the form of bicarbonate. It helps assess your body&#8217;s acid-base balance and can indicate respiratory, metabolic, or kidney issues.</p>
<h2>Understanding CO2 as a Blood Biomarker</h2>
<p>CO2, or carbon dioxide, is a waste product produced by your cells during normal metabolism. When measured as a blood biomarker, CO2 primarily exists in the form of bicarbonate (HCO3-), which plays a crucial role in maintaining your body&#8217;s pH balance. This measurement is typically included in basic metabolic panels and comprehensive metabolic panels, providing valuable insights into your respiratory function, kidney health, and overall metabolic status.</p>
<p>The CO2 blood test doesn&#8217;t actually measure carbon dioxide gas directly. Instead, it measures the total amount of carbon dioxide that exists in various forms in your blood, with about 90% being bicarbonate, 5% dissolved CO2, and 5% carbonic acid. This measurement helps healthcare providers understand how well your lungs and kidneys are working together to maintain proper acid-base balance.</p>
<h2>Why CO2 Levels Matter for Your Health</h2>
<p>Your body maintains a delicate balance between acids and bases, and CO2 plays a central role in this equilibrium. When you breathe, your lungs remove excess CO2 from your blood. Meanwhile, your kidneys regulate bicarbonate levels to help neutralize acids in your body. This intricate system keeps your blood pH within the narrow range of 7.35 to 7.45, which is essential for proper cellular function.</p>
<p>Abnormal CO2 levels can indicate various health conditions. High levels might suggest respiratory problems where your lungs aren&#8217;t effectively removing CO2, metabolic alkalosis, or certain kidney conditions. Low levels could indicate metabolic acidosis, kidney disease, or conditions causing hyperventilation. Understanding your CO2 levels helps identify these issues early, allowing for timely intervention and treatment.</p>
<h2>Normal CO2 Ranges and What They Mean</h2>
<p>The normal range for CO2 in blood typically falls between:</p>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
23–29 mEq/L (milliequivalents per liter) for adults
</div>
<p>These ranges may vary slightly between laboratories and can be influenced by factors such as altitude, age, and certain medications. It&#8217;s important to interpret your results in context with other blood tests and your overall health picture.</p>
<h2>High CO2 Levels (Hypercapnia)</h2>
<p>CO2 levels above 29 mEq/L may indicate:</p>
<ul>
<li>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</li>
<li>Metabolic alkalosis from prolonged vomiting or excessive antacid use</li>
<li>Cushing&#8217;s syndrome</li>
<li>Conn&#8217;s syndrome (primary hyperaldosteronism)</li>
<li>Severe dehydration</li>
</ul>
<h2>Low CO2 Levels (Hypocapnia)</h2>
<p>CO2 levels below 23 mEq/L may suggest:</p>
<ul>
<li>Metabolic acidosis from diabetes, kidney disease, or severe diarrhea</li>
<li>Respiratory alkalosis from hyperventilation or anxiety</li>
<li>Addison&#8217;s disease</li>
<li>Ethylene glycol or methanol poisoning</li>
<li>Salicylate (aspirin) overdose</li>
</ul>
<h2>Factors That Influence CO2 Levels</h2>
<p>Several lifestyle and environmental factors can affect your CO2 levels:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Exercise:</strong> Temporarily increases CO2 production as your muscles work harder and produce more metabolic waste; respiratory rate increases to maintain balance.</li>
<li><strong>High altitude:</strong> Can lead to slightly lower CO2 levels as your body adapts to lower oxygen by breathing more rapidly.</li>
<li><strong>Medications:</strong> Diuretics and corticosteroids can raise CO2 levels by causing metabolic alkalosis, while medications like metformin can lower CO2 if they cause lactic acidosis.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Optimizing Your CO2 Levels</h2>
<p>Maintaining healthy CO2 levels involves supporting respiratory and kidney function:</p>
<ul>
<li>Engage in regular cardiovascular exercise to strengthen respiratory function.</li>
<li>Stay well-hydrated to support kidney health and acid-base regulation.</li>
<li>Address underlying respiratory issues with breathing exercises, pulmonary rehabilitation, or appropriate medications.</li>
<li>Manage metabolic causes by treating root conditions such as kidney disease or diabetes, and following appropriate dietary plans.</li>
<li>Maintain a balanced diet that avoids excessive protein or antacid overuse to prevent acid-base imbalances.</li>
</ul>
<p>Regular monitoring of your CO2 levels, especially if you have conditions affecting your lungs or kidneys, helps track your health status and treatment effectiveness. Understanding your CO2 levels as part of your complete metabolic panel provides valuable insights into your overall health.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: IF YOU ARE CONCERNED WITH ANY OF YOUR RESULTS, PLEASE CONSULT WITH YOUR PHYSICIAN.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Day 3 Hormone Testing: Understanding the Baseline for Fertility</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/day-3-hormone-testing-understanding-the-baseline-for-fertility/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 14:56:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3754</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Day 3 hormone testing is a common practice in reproductive health, providing a standardized baseline to evaluate your hormonal balance and fertility.]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When your doctor asks you to schedule bloodwork on the third day of your menstrual cycle, there&#8217;s a reason behind the specificity. Day 3 hormone testing has become the gold standard in reproductive health—not by accident, but because it captures your hormones at their most revealing moment.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" /><b data-stringify-type="bold">Why Day 3 matters</b><br aria-hidden="true" />Day 3 represents a unique window in your cycle: the early follicular phase, when both estrogen and progesterone are at their lowest and most stable levels. Think of it as your hormonal baseline—before the cascade of ovulation begins to shift everything.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" />During this window, we can see the conversation happening between your brain and your ovaries. Your pituitary gland releases FSH (follicle-stimulating hormone) and LH (luteinizing hormone) to signal your ovaries, which respond by producing estradiol, AMH, and SHBG. Testing at Day 3 captures this signal-and-response system in its clearest form, giving us insight into your reproductive hormone balance before the cycle&#8217;s next phase kicks in.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" />Because the early follicular phase is relatively consistent across most cycles, Day 3 results can be reliably compared to established reference ranges—making it easier to spot patterns or potential concerns.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" /><b data-stringify-type="bold">A note on timing:</b> If your cycle runs slightly shorter or longer than average, testing on Day 2 or Day 4 works just as well. What matters most is catching that stable, early-follicular window.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" /><b data-stringify-type="bold">What if you&#8217;re on birth control—or don&#8217;t have regular periods?</b><br aria-hidden="true" />Here&#8217;s where things get more nuanced. If you&#8217;re using hormonal contraception, your body isn&#8217;t going through natural ovulatory cycles. Hormonal birth control suppresses ovulation and keeps hormone levels relatively stable, which means a &#8220;Day 3&#8221; doesn&#8217;t technically exist in the traditional sense.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" /><b data-stringify-type="bold">If you&#8217;re on hormonal birth control:</b> You can test at any time during the active hormone phase. While you might experience regular withdrawal bleeds, these are artificial—triggered by the drop in synthetic hormones, not by natural ovulation. Since your hormone levels remain suppressed throughout, there&#8217;s no meaningful difference between testing on &#8220;Day 3&#8221; of a withdrawal bleed versus any other day. What matters is understanding that your results will reflect the influence of synthetic hormones rather than your natural baseline.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" /><b data-stringify-type="bold">If your cycles are irregular or absent:</b> Whether due to perimenopause, PCOS, postpartum recovery, stress, or other factors, you can test at any time. The key is working with a provider or testing service that offers condition-specific reference ranges designed to account for different hormonal patterns, ensuring your results remain meaningful and actionable even without a defined cycle day.</p>
<p><b data-stringify-type="bold">Planning to stop birth control?</b><br aria-hidden="true" />If you&#8217;re coming off hormonal contraception and want to understand your natural fertility baseline, timing matters. Hormone levels don&#8217;t bounce back overnight—they may take anywhere from several weeks to several months to return to their natural rhythm, depending on the type of contraception you used.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" />Three months is a common guideline for waiting before testing, but individual recovery varies. For the most reliable snapshot of your natural hormones, it&#8217;s best to wait until your cycles have resumed and stabilized.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" /><b data-stringify-type="bold">The bottom line</b><br aria-hidden="true" />Day 3 hormone testing offers valuable insight into reproductive health and fertility—especially if you have natural menstrual cycles. But it&#8217;s not the only window that matters.<br aria-hidden="true" />If you&#8217;re on hormonal contraception, in perimenopause, or managing irregular cycles, you can still gain meaningful information by testing at other times. The key is understanding what your results represent within your body&#8217;s current context—whether that&#8217;s a natural cycle, hormone therapy, or a transitional phase.</p>
<p><br aria-hidden="true" />Hormone testing can be informative at any stage of life. What matters most is knowing how to interpret your results based on where you are right now.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Understanding Your Lab Results: Beyond Standard Ranges</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/understanding-your-lab-results-beyond-standard-ranges/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 19:47:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3743</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When you receive your lab results, you'll notice two different types of grading systems: the “lab reference range” and our clinical optimization grades “SiPhox Grades”. Understanding the difference between these approaches can help you make better decisions about your health.]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When you receive your lab results, you&#8217;ll notice two different types of grading systems: the “lab reference range” and our clinical optimization grades “SiPhox Grades”. Understanding the difference between these approaches can help you make better decisions about your health.</p>
<h2>Laboratory Reference Ranges: How They&#8217;re Determined</h2>
<p>Laboratory reference ranges are typically established through a standardized process:</p>
<ul>
<li>Testing a large sample of the local population</li>
<li>Including people who aren&#8217;t necessarily in optimal health</li>
<li>Using statistical analysis to include approximately 95% of results</li>
<li>Creating a bell curve of results and setting ranges based on standard deviations</li>
<li>Focusing primarily on identifying disease states rather than optimal health</li>
</ul>
<p>This means these ranges are designed to identify clearly abnormal results rather than guide you toward optimal health. They reflect what&#8217;s common in the general population, not what&#8217;s ideal for your wellbeing.</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4.png"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-3747" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4.png" alt="" width="1999" height="1387" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4.png 1999w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-300x208.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1024x710.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-768x533.png 768w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1536x1066.png 1536w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1568x1088.png 1568w" sizes="(max-width: 1999px) 100vw, 1999px" /></a></p>
<h2>Our SiPhox Grades: A Research-Based Approach</h2>
<p>Our grading system is fundamentally different. We determine our ranges through:</p>
<ul>
<li>Comprehensive review of peer-reviewed clinical studies</li>
<li>Analysis of research linking specific biomarker levels to health outcomes</li>
<li>Evaluation of data from longevity and wellness research</li>
<li>Integration of findings from multiple populations and health contexts</li>
<li>Focus on identifying truly optimal ranges for health and performance</li>
</ul>
<p>This evidence-based approach allows us to provide more refined and meaningful grades for those looking to improve their health beyond “average”:</p>
<h3>Pay Attention (Red)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Results requiring proactive attention and intervention</li>
<li>Often still falls within standard laboratory &#8220;normal&#8221; ranges</li>
<li>Our more stringent criteria serve as early warning signals</li>
<li>Allows for preventive action before markers become out of range</li>
<li>Based on clinical evidence of potential health impacts</li>
<li>May indicate need for lifestyle changes or medical consultation</li>
<li>Represents an opportunity for early intervention</li>
</ul>
<h3>Fair (Yellow)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Results that fall short of evidence-based optimal ranges</li>
<li>Based on studies showing room for health improvement</li>
<li>May be &#8220;normal&#8221; by standard ranges but below optimal</li>
<li>Indicates opportunity for targeted optimization</li>
</ul>
<h3>Good (Blue)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Results aligned with positive health outcomes in research</li>
<li>Better than population averages</li>
<li>Supported by studies showing good health markers</li>
<li>Represents solid foundation for wellness</li>
</ul>
<h3>Optimal (Green)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Results matching levels seen in research on exceptional health</li>
<li>Based on studies of longevity and peak performance</li>
<li>Aligned with best documented health outcomes</li>
<li>Represents evidence-based ideal targets</li>
</ul>
<h2>Why Our Approach Makes a Difference: A Practical Example</h2>
<p>Let&#8217;s take Vitamin D as an example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Standard laboratory range: 25-100 ng/mL</li>
<li>Our evidence-based optimization grades:
<ul>
<li>Pay Attention: &lt; 30 ng/mL or &gt; 100 mg/mL</li>
<li>Fair: 30-35 ng/mL</li>
<li>Good: 35-40 ng/mL</li>
<li>Optimal: 40-70 ng/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>While a result of 32 ng/mL would be &#8220;within range&#8221; on a standard report, research shows better health outcomes at higher levels. Our grades reflect this scientific evidence rather than just population averages.</p>
<h2>The Power of Evidence-Based Optimization</h2>
<p>Our approach offers several advantages:</p>
<ol>
<li>More nuanced understanding of your health markers</li>
<li>Grades based on actual health outcomes rather than population statistics</li>
<li>Targets derived from scientific research rather than averages</li>
<li>Focus on optimization rather than just avoiding disease</li>
</ol>
<p>Remember: Standard ranges tell you if you&#8217;re similar to the general population. Our grades tell you how close you are to optimal health based on clinical evidence. This difference empowers you to make more informed decisions about your health journey.</p>
<p><!-- notionvc: 0b8ab9cd-56a6-4518-a6b4-0ea2891ea544 --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Decoding ApoB: The Key to Cardiovascular Health</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/decoding-apob-the-key-to-cardiovascular-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 17:27:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ApoB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiovascular]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cholesterol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lipids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Learn how to manage your cholesterol effectively by understanding ApoB, a critical indicator of cardiovascular health.]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Key Takeaways:</p>
<ul>
<li>Apolipoprotein B (ApoB) is a protein found in atherogenic (artery-clogging) lipoproteins, such as LDL, VLDL, and IDL, and plays a critical role in lipid transport and metabolism.</li>
<li>Apolipoproteins, including ApoB, are essential for transporting lipids in the body, but high levels of ApoB are associated with an increased risk of cardiovascular diseases.</li>
<li>Regular monitoring and managing ApoB levels through diet, exercise, and possibly medication, are important for cardiovascular health.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- notionvc: 1452707f-e3bd-4dfb-82e9-d6fa5ae66b6f --></p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Heart disease is the leading cause of death for men, women, and people of most racial and ethnic groups in the United States. One person dies every 33 seconds in the United States from cardiovascular disease. <strong><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="1">About 695,000 people in the United States died from heart disease in 2021</span></strong>—that&#8217;s 1 in every 5 deaths. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span><!-- notionvc: 1b03393c-5628-45bf-9eee-00a569bcd68a --><!-- notionvc: 3eac429a-cfb2-4e94-86f7-61e588c4388f --></p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>Heart disease is the leading cause of death for men, women, and people of most racial and ethnic groups in the United States. One person dies every 33 seconds in the United States from cardiovascular disease. <strong><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="1">About 695,000 people in the United States died from heart disease in 2021</span></strong>—that&#8217;s 1 in every 5 deaths. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span><!-- notionvc: 1b03393c-5628-45bf-9eee-00a569bcd68a --><!-- notionvc: 3eac429a-cfb2-4e94-86f7-61e588c4388f --></p>

</div><h2>What is ApoB?</h2>
<p>Lipoproteins serve as intricate transport vehicles for lipids (fat) in the body, featuring a lipid core (consisting of fats such as cholesterol and triglycerides) enveloped by proteins, phospholipids, and free cholesterol.</p>
<p>There are different types of lipoproteins each with distinct compositions and functions. Examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>High-density lipoprotein (HDL)</li>
<li>Low-density lipoprotein (LDL)</li>
<li>Intermediate-density lipoprotein (IDL)</li>
<li>Very low-density lipoprotein (VLDL)</li>
</ul>
<p>Their role is to navigate the circulatory and lymphatic systems. HDL, renowned as &#8220;good&#8221; cholesterol, prevents arterial plaque buildup, while elevated levels of others, particularly LDLs, pose cardiovascular risks.</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23229-lipoprotein-illustration.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2810" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23229-lipoprotein-illustration.jpg" alt="" width="800" height="715" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23229-lipoprotein-illustration.jpg 800w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23229-lipoprotein-illustration-300x268.jpg 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/23229-lipoprotein-illustration-768x686.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></a></p>
<p><em>“Lipoproteins: What They Are, Function &amp; Importance.” Cleveland Clinic, 22 May 2022, <a href="http://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/23229-lipoprotein">my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/23229-lipoprotein</a>.</em></p>
<p>Apolipoproteins (Apo), synthesized primarily in the liver, are integral components of lipoproteins, usually attached to their surface (as depicted in the image above). ApoB is generally associated with our “bad” lipoproteins such as VLDLs, IDLs, and LDL, whereas HDLs “good cholesterol” are associated with a different type of apolipoprotein, “ApoA1”.</p>
<p>Where apolipoproteins become useful is in indicating the abundance of all lipoprotein particles in the bloodstream. For example, ApoB is attached to the “bad” lipoproteins in a 1:1 ratio. They also play a key role in the movement of our lipoproteins around the circulatory system. By interacting with various enzymes and receptors involved in lipid metabolism APOB facilitates the uptake of cholesterol and other lipids by peripheral tissues.</p>
<h2>What exactly is cholesterol?</h2>
<p>Cholesterol is a waxy, fat-like substance that&#8217;s found in all the cells in your body. It is both produced by the body (primarily in the liver) and obtained from dietary sources, especially animal products like meat, dairy, and eggs. Cholesterol is an essential component for the body, necessary for cell membranes, bile production, and hormone synthesis.</p>
<p>The nomenclature surrounding lipoproteins and cholesterol can be confusing. Cholesterol is a type of lipid (fat) found in the blood and cells of the body. Lipoproteins, as explained above, are particles that transport cholesterol and other lipids through the bloodstream. HDLs (high density lipoproteins) are often called &#8220;good cholesterol&#8221; because they help remove excess cholesterol from the bloodstream, while LDLs are known as &#8220;bad cholesterol&#8221; because high levels can lead to plaque buildup in the arteries. Therefore, when we talk about HDL or LDL cholesterol, we&#8217;re actually referring to the cholesterol carried by the LDL lipoproteins.</p>
<p>Imbalanced cholesterol levels, especially elevated LDL cholesterol, heighten the risk of cardiovascular disease. Dietary choices, notably consumption of saturated and trans fats, are key influencers of cholesterol levels. Regular screening is advised to monitor cholesterol levels, with interventions typically encompassing lifestyle adjustments such as diet and exercise, complemented by medical treatments like statins when needed.</p>
<p>The nomenclature surrounding lipoproteins and cholesterol can be confusing. Cholesterol is a type of lipid (fat) found in the blood and cells of the body. Lipoproteins, as explained above, are particles that transport cholesterol and other lipids through the bloodstream. HDLs (high density lipoproteins) are often called &#8220;good cholesterol&#8221; because they help remove excess cholesterol from the bloodstream, while LDLs are known as &#8220;bad cholesterol&#8221; because high levels can lead to plaque buildup in the arteries. Therefore, when we talk about HDL or LDL cholesterol, we&#8217;re actually referring to the cholesterol carried by the LDL lipoproteins. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>Why is lipid transport by apolipoproteins important?</h2>
<p>Lipids, including cholesterol and triglycerides, are vital for many bodily functions. However, lipids are not soluble in blood. Without apolipoproteins, lipids would remain insoluble in the bloodstream, leading to their accumulation and potential blockages in blood vessels. By forming complexes with lipids to create lipoproteins, apolipoproteins ensure efficient transport of lipids to various tissues and organs. Proper functioning and balance of apolipoproteins and lipoproteins are essential in preventing diseases. Dysregulation can lead to lipid disorders, such as hyperlipidemia (high levels of lipids in the blood), which is a major risk factor for cardiovascular diseases. Problems arise when there is an imbalance between the different types of cholesterol. High levels of LDL cholesterol, often referred to as &#8220;bad&#8221; cholesterol, can lead to atherosclerosis. Atherosclerosis is the buildup of plaques in the arteries, which can restrict blood flow and lead to heart attacks, strokes, and other cardiovascular issues. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> It&#8217;s the balance between LDL and HDL, along with the overall level of cholesterol, that determines the risk of cholesterol-related health issues.</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Atherosclerosis-diagram.gif"><img decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2812" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Atherosclerosis-diagram.gif" alt="" width="450" height="451" /></a></p>
<p><em>&#8220;What Is Atherosclerosis?” National Heart Lung and Blood Institute, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 24 Mar. 2022, <a href="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/atherosclerosis">www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/atherosclerosis</a>.</em></p>
<h2>Why is ApoB considered “bad”?</h2>
<p>ApoB is a primary component of LDL, the so-called &#8220;bad&#8221; cholesterol. High levels of LDL in the blood are a well-established risk factor for the development of atherosclerosis. ApoB is not only present in LDL but also in other atherogenic particles like VLDL and IDL. These lipoproteins are involved in transporting triglycerides and cholesterol in the blood and also contribute to atherosclerosis. Importantly, ApoB-containing lipoproteins have the ability to penetrate the arterial wall, where they deposit cholesterol and initiate the formation of plaques. This process, known as atherosclerosis, is a major contributor to the development of cardiovascular diseases. Hence, monitoring ApoB levels is crucial for assessing cardiovascular risk and implementing preventive measures. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>Numerous studies have shown that ApoB is a strong predictor of cardiovascular risk. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> In some cases, ApoB has been found to be a better indicator than traditional lipid measures like total cholesterol or LDL cholesterol because it reflects the total particle number rather than just the cholesterol content. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>It&#8217;s important to note that while ApoB is associated with &#8220;bad&#8221; cholesterol, it is a necessary component of normal lipid metabolism. The &#8220;bad&#8221; designation primarily relates to its role in the context of atherogenic lipoproteins and their contribution to cardiovascular disease risk. Managing ApoB levels, typically through diet, lifestyle changes, and sometimes medication, can be an important part of reducing cardiovascular risk.</p>
<h2>Interpretation and management of ApoB</h2>
<p>To interpret your results, here are a few values that can be used to gauge your cardiovascular health. It is important to consult with your physician if you are concerned with any of your results.</p>
<ul>
<li>Low: &lt; 50 mg/dL <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Optimal: &lt; 65 mg/dL <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_11');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_11');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_11" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[11]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_11" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Normal: &lt; 100 mg/dL <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_12');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_12');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_12" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[12]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_12" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>High risk of vascular disease: &gt; 120 mg/dL <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_13');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_13');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_13" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[13]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_13" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<p>According to the Cleveland Clinic, high ApoB may be a result of pregnancy, high cholesterol, or kidney issues while low ApoB may be present if you have sepsis, liver disease, malabsorption, or high estrogen levels. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_14');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_14');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_14" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[14]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_14" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> Of course, there are a variety of other factors that may be associated with abnormal ApoB levels, so it is best to consult with a physician if you are concerned with your levels to determine the root cause and seek treatment.</p>
<p>If your ApoB levels are high, it is worth consulting your physician to see how you can manage your levels as underlying diseases may be at play. The SiPhox Heart Health Blueprint may also be a good option if you have elevated lipid levels or have a family history of poor cardiovascular health (see here: <a href="https://home.siphoxhealth.com/blueprints/heart-health">https://home.siphoxhealth.com/blueprints/heart-health</a>). If you have slightly elevated levels, you can try:</p>
<ul>
<li>Engaging in at least 30 minutes of exercise each day <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_15');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_15');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_15" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[15]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_15" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Limiting your intake of saturated fats <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_16');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_16');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_16" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[16]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_16" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> This can be done by avoiding foods like butter, coconut oil, cakes, biscuits, fatty cuts of meat, cheese, etc. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_17');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_17');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_17" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[17]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_17" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Avoiding tobacco products like cigarettes <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_18');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_18');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_18" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[18]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_18" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Maintaining a healthy weight <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_19');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_19');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_19" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[19]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_19" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Limiting trans fat intake <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_20');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_20');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_20" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[20]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_20" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Consuming omega-3s (cold-water fish, walnuts, etc.), psyllium, and/or phytosterols (nuts, whole grains, etc.) <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_21');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_21');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_21" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[21]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_21" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Following a Mediterranean diet <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_22');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_22');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_22" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[22]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_22" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Increase your intake of foods rich in soluble fiber <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_23');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2809_5('footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_23');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_23" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[23]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2809_5_23" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> such as wheat bran, psyllium seeds, cooked pinto beans, etc. (view the Soluble &amp; Insoluble Fiber Foods List <a href="https://www.northottawawellnessfoundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/NOWF-Fiber-Content-of-Foods.pdf"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">here)</span></a></li>
</ul>
<h2>Why is tracking your ApoB important?</h2>
<p>Cardiovascular health is no joke. Several studies mentioned earlier in this guide have revealed just how vital ApoB is as a predictor for cardiovascular events. The good news is that LDL, HDL, ApoB, ApoA, and triglycerides are all modifiable. But the first step in monitoring your levels is to test your levels, and that’s where SiPhox Health comes in. The benefit of <a href="https://home.siphoxhealth.com/"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">SiPhox Health</span></a> is having the freedom to track such volatile biomarkers frequently, affordably, and conveniently from the comfort of your home. Want to see what your ApoB levels are right now? How about testing every week to see if limiting saturated fats or exercising are actually changing your levels? Or maybe you’re thinking of trying statins and want to monitor your levels to determine whether the prescribed dosage is right for you? With <a href="https://home.siphoxhealth.com/"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">SiPhox Health</span></a>, your health is in your hands. Check out our website to learn more about <a href="https://home.siphoxhealth.com/blueprints/heart-health"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">SiPhox Health’s Heart Health Blueprint</span></a>.</p>
<h2>Tracking your ApoB with SiPhox Health:</h2>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li>$295 one-time or subscribe to get $85 per test*</li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 (7 cardiovascular markers including LDL, HDL, ApoA, ApoB, triglycerides, Lp(a), etc.)</li>
<li>Heart Health Blueprint: Optimize for the lowest effective dose of lipid-lowering medication as needed.</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- notionvc: 84b0c795-4a53-4795-add3-0f45efc23e0a --></p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2809_5();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2809_5();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2809_5">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2809_5" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Heart Disease Facts.” <span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="1">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</span>, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 15 May 2023, www.cdc.gov/heartdisease/facts.htm#:~:text=Heart%20disease%20is%20the%20leading,groups%20in%20the%20United%20States.&amp;text=One%20person%20dies%20every%2033,United%20States%20from%20cardiovascular%20disease.&amp;text=About%20695%2C000%20people%20in%20the,1%20in%20every%205%20deaths.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Heart Disease Facts.” <span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="1">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</span>, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 15 May 2023, www.cdc.gov/heartdisease/facts.htm#:~:text=Heart%20disease%20is%20the%20leading,groups%20in%20the%20United%20States.&amp;text=One%20person%20dies%20every%2033,United%20States%20from%20cardiovascular%20disease.&amp;text=About%20695%2C000%20people%20in%20the,1%20in%20every%205%20deaths.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“What Is Cholesterol?” <a href="http://www.heart.org/">Www.Heart.Org</a>, 16 Feb. 2024, <a href="http://www.heart.org/en/health-topics/cholesterol/about-cholesterol">www.heart.org/en/health-topics/cholesterol/about-cholesterol</a>. </td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Sniderman, A. D., Thanassoulis, G., Glavinovic, T., Navar, A. M., Pencina, M., Catapano, A., &amp; Ference, B. A. (2019). Apolipoprotein B Particles and Cardiovascular Disease: A Narrative Review. JAMA cardiology, 4(12), 1287–1295. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2019.3780"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2019.3780</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Sniderman, A. D., Thanassoulis, G., Glavinovic, T., Navar, A. M., Pencina, M., Catapano, A., &amp; Ference, B. A. (2019). Apolipoprotein B Particles and Cardiovascular Disease: A Narrative Review. JAMA cardiology, 4(12), 1287–1295. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2019.3780"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2019.3780</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Walldius, Gran. ‘The apoB/apoA-I Ratio Is a Strong Predictor of Cardiovascular Risk’. Lipoproteins &#8211; Role in Health and Diseases, InTech, 3 Oct. 2012. Crossref, doi:10.5772/47869.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Behbodikhah, J., Ahmed, S., Elyasi, A., Kasselman, L. J., De Leon, J., Glass, A. D., &amp; Reiss, A. B. (2021). Apolipoprotein B and Cardiovascular Disease: Biomarker and Potential Therapeutic Target. <em>Metabolites</em>, <em>11</em>(10), 690. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/metabo11100690"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3390/metabo11100690</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Sniderman, A. D., Thanassoulis, G., Glavinovic, T., Navar, A. M., Pencina, M., Catapano, A., &amp; Ference, B. A. (2019). Apolipoprotein B Particles and Cardiovascular Disease: A Narrative Review. JAMA cardiology, 4(12), 1287–1295. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2019.3780"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamacardio.2019.3780</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Glavinovic, T., Thanassoulis, G., de Graaf, J., Couture, P., Hegele, R. A., &amp; Sniderman, A. D. (2022). Physiological Bases for the Superiority of Apolipoprotein B Over Low-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol and Non-High-Density Lipoprotein Cholesterol as a Marker of Cardiovascular Risk. Journal of the American Heart Association, 11(20), e025858. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/JAHA.122.025858"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1161/JAHA.122.025858</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">APOLB &#8211; Overview: Apolipoprotein B, Serum, <a href="http://www.mayocliniclabs.com/test-catalog/overview/614544#Clinical-and-Interpretive">www.mayocliniclabs.com/test-catalog/overview/614544#Clinical-and-Interpretive</a>. Accessed 1 May 2024.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_11" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_11');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >11</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Apo B Test.” Cleveland Clinic, 16 May 2023, <a href="http://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test">my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test</a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_12" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_12');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >12</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Apolipoprotein B-100.” <em>University of Rochester Medical Center</em>, <a href="http://www.urmc.rochester.edu/encyclopedia/content.aspx?contenttypeid=167&amp;contentid=apolipoprotein_b100#:~:text=Normal%20levels%20of%20ApoB%2D100,risk%20of%20developing%20cardiovascular%20disease">www.urmc.rochester.edu/encyclopedia/content.aspx?contenttypeid=167&amp;contentid=apolipoprotein_b100#:~:text=Normal levels of ApoB-100,risk of developing cardiovascular disease</a>. Accessed 1 May 2024.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_13" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_13');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >13</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Sniderman, A. D., Williams, K., Contois, J. H., Monroe, H. M., McQueen, M. J., de Graaf, J., &amp; Furberg, C. D. (2011). A meta-analysis of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, non-high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, and apolipoprotein B as markers of cardiovascular risk. <em>Circulation. Cardiovascular quality and outcomes</em>, <em>4</em>(3), 337–345. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.110.959247"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.110.959247</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_14" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_14');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >14</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Apo B Test.” Cleveland Clinic, 16 May 2023, <a href="http://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test">my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test</a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_15" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_15');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >15</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Apo B Test.” Cleveland Clinic, 16 May 2023, <a href="http://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test">my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test</a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_16" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_16');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >16</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Apo B Test.” Cleveland Clinic, 16 May 2023, <a href="http://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test">my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/24992-apolipoprotein-b-test</a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_17" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_17');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >17</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“How to Eat Less Saturated Fat.” <em>NHS</em>, NHS, 19 June 2023, <a href="http://www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/eat-less-saturated-fat/.%7D"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/eat-less-saturated-fat/</span>.</a> </td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_18" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_18');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >18</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“How to Eat Less Saturated Fat.” <em>NHS</em>, NHS, 19 June 2023, <a href="http://www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/eat-less-saturated-fat/.%7D">www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/eat-less-saturated-fat/.</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_19" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_19');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >19</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“How to Eat Less Saturated Fat.” <em>NHS</em>, NHS, 19 June 2023, <a href="http://www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/eat-less-saturated-fat/.%7D">www.nhs.uk/live-well/eat-well/how-to-eat-a-balanced-diet/eat-less-saturated-fat/.</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_20" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_20');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >20</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Lamantia, V., Sniderman, A., &amp; Faraj, M. (2016). Nutritional management of hyperapoB. <em>Nutrition research reviews</em>, <em>29</em>(2), 202–233. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954422416000147"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954422416000147</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_21" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_21');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >21</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Lamantia, V., Sniderman, A., &amp; Faraj, M. (2016). Nutritional management of hyperapoB. <em>Nutrition research reviews</em>, <em>29</em>(2), 202–233. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954422416000147"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954422416000147</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_22" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_22');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >22</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Lamantia, V., Sniderman, A., &amp; Faraj, M. (2016). Nutritional management of hyperapoB. <em>Nutrition research reviews</em>, <em>29</em>(2), 202–233. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954422416000147"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0954422416000147</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2809_5_23" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2809_5_23');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >23</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Jenkins, D. J., Wolever, T. M., Rao, A. V., Hegele, R. A., Mitchell, S. J., Ransom, T. P., Boctor, D. L., Spadafora, P. J., Jenkins, A. L., &amp; Mehling, C. (1993). Effect on blood lipids of very high intakes of fiber in diets low in saturated fat and cholesterol. <em>The New England journal of medicine</em>, <em>329</em>(1), 21–26. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199307013290104"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJM199307013290104</span></a></td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2809_5() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2809_5').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2809_5').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2809_5() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2809_5').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2809_5').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2809_5() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2809_5').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2809_5(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2809_5(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2809_5(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2809_5(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2809_5(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2809_5(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>HbA1c At Home- A Tool for Metabolic Health</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/optimizing-lower-hba1c-better-metabolic-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pavel Korecky]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 13:50:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HbA1C]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[A1C]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diabetes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[glucose]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HbA1c]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hemoglobin A1C]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[insulin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[metabolism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pre-diabetes]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2490</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Learn more about HbA1c, an important metabolic marker and long-term indicator of glycemic control.]]></description>
			
							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p><strong>Key Takeaways</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Hemoglobin A1C is an important screen for diabetic risk, providing a long-term snapshot of blood glucose concentration in comparison to other tests.</li>
<li>Levels that are consistently above 5.6% may warrant a visit to a physician.</li>
<li>Because of its role in diagnosing diabetes, HbA1c is included in SiPhox Health&#8217;s base panel.</li>
</ul>
<p>A1C results can be interpreted using the following reference ranges, but it is important to consult with your physician if your level falls outside the normal range.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.abim.org/Media/bfijryql/laboratory-reference-ranges.pdf">Normal</a></span>: 4 &#8211; 5.6%</li>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=A%20normal%20A1C%20level%20is,for%20developing%20type%202%20diabetes.">Pre-Diabetes</a></span>: 5.7 &#8211; 6.4%</li>
<li><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=A%20normal%20A1C%20level%20is,for%20developing%20type%202%20diabetes."><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Diabetes</span>:</a> &gt; 6.5%</li>
<li><a href="https://www.singlecare.com/blog/normal-a1c-levels/"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Critical</span></a>: &gt; 9%</li>
</ul>
<p>According to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=The">CDC</a>, several factors can provide a false report of your A1C results, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Kidney failure, liver disease, anemia</li>
<li>Less common hemoglobin types that people of African, Mediterranean, or Southeast Asian descent may have</li>
<li>Certain medications</li>
<li>Blood loss or blood transfusions</li>
<li>Early or late pregnancy</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- notionvc: 6fe1567e-2865-4cb0-93ef-9932c9e94f17 --></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: 38b58bcd-39ae-4912-80dc-a87dbebd79d1 --></p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p><strong>Key Takeaways</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Hemoglobin A1C is an important screen for diabetic risk, providing a long-term snapshot of blood glucose concentration in comparison to other tests.</li>
<li>Levels that are consistently above 5.6% may warrant a visit to a physician.</li>
<li>Because of its role in diagnosing diabetes, HbA1c is included in SiPhox Health&#8217;s base panel.</li>
</ul>
<p>A1C results can be interpreted using the following reference ranges, but it is important to consult with your physician if your level falls outside the normal range.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.abim.org/Media/bfijryql/laboratory-reference-ranges.pdf">Normal</a></span>: 4 &#8211; 5.6%</li>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=A%20normal%20A1C%20level%20is,for%20developing%20type%202%20diabetes.">Pre-Diabetes</a></span>: 5.7 &#8211; 6.4%</li>
<li><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=A%20normal%20A1C%20level%20is,for%20developing%20type%202%20diabetes."><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Diabetes</span>:</a> &gt; 6.5%</li>
<li><a href="https://www.singlecare.com/blog/normal-a1c-levels/"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Critical</span></a>: &gt; 9%</li>
</ul>
<p>According to the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=The">CDC</a>, several factors can provide a false report of your A1C results, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Kidney failure, liver disease, anemia</li>
<li>Less common hemoglobin types that people of African, Mediterranean, or Southeast Asian descent may have</li>
<li>Certain medications</li>
<li>Blood loss or blood transfusions</li>
<li>Early or late pregnancy</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- notionvc: 6fe1567e-2865-4cb0-93ef-9932c9e94f17 --></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: 38b58bcd-39ae-4912-80dc-a87dbebd79d1 --></p>

</div><h2>What is Hemoglobin A1C?</h2>
<p>Hemoglobin (Hb) is a type of protein that circulates in the blood and is responsible for transporting oxygen from the lungs to tissues throughout the body. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span></p>
<p>A HbA1c test is a measure of the percent of total hemoglobin that has been glycosylated, or attached to glucose (sugar). This is significant because the percentage of glycosylated HbA1c correlates to the average amount of glucose that is present in the bloodstream over the past 2 to 3 months. Since diabetes is a disease in which blood glucose levels are too high, elevated HbA1c can be indicative of pre-diabetes or diabetes. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>Why is measuring HbA1c important?</h2>
<p>Many sources suggest that A1C levels between 5.7% and 6.4% are indicative of pre-diabetes, whereas higher levels are indicative of diabetes. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>. According to the CDC, 136 million American adults have either diabetes or pre-diabetes <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, and out of all American adults with diabetes, 47.4% had A1C values over 7%.</span></p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">That’s where the HbA1c test really shines— in its value as a predictor and monitor of this serious metabolic disease. Unlike daily blood sugar tests, HbA1c reflects average glucose levels over two to three months, offering a more comprehensive picture of how well diabetes is being controlled.</span></p>
<p>This helps in making informed decisions about treatment adjustments and lifestyle changes. High HbA1c levels indicate poor blood sugar control, increasing the risk of diabetes-related complications such as cardiovascular disease, kidney damage (nephropathy), eye damage (retinopathy), nerve damage (neuropathy), and poor wound healing. These complications can have a significant impact on quality of life and overall health. Therefore, maintaining HbA1c levels within the recommended range is crucial for reducing the risk of these long-term effects. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>What factors can influence HbA1c values?</h2>
<p>Several factors can influence HbA1c readings. Conditions like anemia or hemoglobinopathies can alter hemoglobin levels, affecting HbA1c accuracy. Changes in red blood cell lifespan due to recent blood loss, transfusion, or certain chronic conditions (e.g., kidney or liver disease) can skew results. Some medications impact glucose metabolism, thus influencing HbA1c. Racial and ethnic differences have been observed in HbA1c levels, requiring careful interpretation. Pregnancy also affects HbA1c, necessitating different evaluation standards for pregnant women. It&#8217;s important to consider these factors for accurate assessment of HbA1c results. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>What lifestyle modifications can be made to regulate HbA1c?</h2>
<p>Chronic stress can raise blood glucose levels due to the release of stress hormones like cortisol, which can lead to higher HbA1c readings. Finding ways to mitigate this such as deep breathing exercises, meditation, yoga, mindfulness exercises, and adequate sleep may help. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> Smoking can increase HbA1c levels independently of glucose concentration. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> A higher BMI, often associated with increased fat mass, can lead to insulin resistance, which in turn may raise HbA1c levels. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> Conversely, regular exercise improves insulin sensitivity and glucose metabolism, potentially lowering HbA1c. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> These lifestyle factors, along with dietary habits, play a significant role in determining HbA1c values and overall metabolic health. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_11');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_11');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_11" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[11]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_11" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>If your A1C is elevated, Johns Hopkins Medicine <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_12');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_12');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_12" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[12]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_12" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> suggests:</p>
<ul>
<li>Losing weight by leading a healthy lifestyle</li>
<li>Increasing fiber in your diet by choosing veggies, whole grains, and fruit</li>
<li>Regularly exercising &#8211; particularly, aerobic exercise and strength training</li>
<li>Quitting smoking</li>
</ul>
<div id="1712931477.193009" class="c-virtual_list__item" tabindex="0" role="listitem" aria-setsize="-1" data-qa="virtual-list-item" data-item-key="1712931477.193009">
<div class="c-message_kit__background c-message_kit__background--hovered p-message_pane_message__message c-message_kit__message" role="presentation" data-qa="message_container" data-qa-unprocessed="false" data-qa-placeholder="false">
<div class="c-message_kit__hover c-message_kit__hover--hovered" role="document" aria-roledescription="message" data-qa-hover="true">
<div class="c-message_kit__actions c-message_kit__actions--above">
<div class="c-message_kit__gutter">
<div class="c-message_kit__gutter__right" role="presentation" data-qa="message_content">
<div class="c-message_kit__blocks c-message_kit__blocks--rich_text">
<div class="c-message__message_blocks c-message__message_blocks--rich_text" data-qa="message-text">
<div class="p-block_kit_renderer" data-qa="block-kit-renderer">
<div class="p-block_kit_renderer__block_wrapper p-block_kit_renderer__block_wrapper--first">
<div class="p-rich_text_block" dir="auto">
<div class="p-rich_text_section">To manage blood sugar levels effectively, consider reducing carbohydrate intake, as carbs are broken down into sugars by the body. <span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);"><span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_13');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_13');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_13" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[13]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_13" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> </span>Opt for foods with a lower glycemic index, such as non-starchy vegetables and whole fruits, which are digested and absorbed more slowly, resulting in fewer blood glucose spikes. Additionally, incorporating soluble fiber into your diet can help slow sugar absorption and stabilize blood glucose levels. Good sources of soluble fiber include oats, peas, beans, lentils, vegetables, nuts, flaxseeds, and avocado. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_14');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_14');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_14" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[14]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_14" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> Avoiding high-glycemic foods like sugary treats, white bread, white rice, potatoes, fruit juice, and sweet corn can further support blood sugar management. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_15');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_15');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_15" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[15]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_15" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> Using a Glucometer or CGM (Continuous Glucose Monitor) is a valuable tool for real-time monitoring of how food and exercise impact blood glucose levels. By identifying patterns that may not be apparent otherwise, these devices help refine glycemic control and enhance overall management of blood sugar levels. <span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);"><span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_16');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_16');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_16" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[16]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_16" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>.</span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Several supplements may aid in lowering HbA1c levels. While the following may aid in lowering A1C, relying solely on supplements for glycemic control is not recommended.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cinnamon <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_17');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_17');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_17" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[17]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_17" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Magnesium <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_18');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_18');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_18" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[18]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_18" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Chromium Picolinate <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_19');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_19');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_19" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[19]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_19" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Berberine <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_20');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_20');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_20" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[20]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_20" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Fiber (Metamucil or psyllium husk) <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_21');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2490_6('footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_21');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_21" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[21]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2490_6_21" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<p>These supplements show promise in improving insulin sensitivity and reducing blood sugar levels and have been targets for therapeutic studies. However, it&#8217;s important to consult a healthcare provider before starting any supplement regimen, especially for individuals with diabetes or pre-diabetes, as these supplements may interact with other medications and may not be suitable for everyone.</p>
<h2>Tracking HbA1c with SiPhox Health:</h2>
<p>&#8211; At-home kit delivered to your home<br />
&#8211; Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)<br />
&#8211; $295 one-time, $85 subscription<br />
&#8211; Number of biomarkers included: 17 in the base panel (Thyroid+ and Hormone+ add-on panels available)<br />
&#8211; Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported<br />
&#8211; CGM tracking<br />
&#8211; 2-5 business days after collection</p>
<p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your HbA1c + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity, and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>
<p><a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/pricing-tiers"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Learn more about SiPhox Health testing here.</strong></span></a></p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2490_6();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2490_6();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2490_6">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2490_6" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><span style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Billett HH. Hemoglobin and Hematocrit. In: Walker HK, Hall WD, Hurst JW, editors. Clinical Methods: The History, Physical, and Laboratory Examinations. 3rd edition. Boston: Butterworths; 1990. Chapter 151.</span><span class="bk_cite_avail" style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);"> Available from: <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK259/</span></span><span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);"></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">MedlinePlus [Internet]. Bethesda (MD): National Library of Medicine (US). Blood Glucose; [updated 2024 Mar 6]. Available from: <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://medlineplus.gov/bloodglucose.html#</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><i>A1C Looks Back</i>. Understanding A1C Test | ADA. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://diabetes.org/about-diabetes/a1c</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><span style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. National Diabetes Statistics Report website. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/data/statistics-report/index.html.</span> Accessed 2024 April 10.</span><span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);"></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Department of Health &amp; Human Services. (2004, October 28). <i>Diabetes &#8211; long-term effects</i>. Better Health Channel. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.betterhealth.vic.gov.au/health/conditionsandtreatments/diabetes-long-term-effects</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (2022, September 30). <i>All About Your A1C</i>. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/managing/managing-blood-sugar/a1c.html#:~:text=The</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Hilliard, M. E., Yi-Frazier, J. P., Hessler, D., Butler, A. M., Anderson, B. J., &amp; Jaser, S. (2016). Stress and A1c Among People with Diabetes Across the Lifespan. <i>Current diabetes reports</i>, <i>16</i>(8), 67. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11892-016-0761-3</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (2022a, June 20). <i>Smoking and Diabetes</i>. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.cdc.gov/diabetes/library/features/smoking-and-diabetes.html</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Sarnings, W., Aman, A., Rasyid, H., Bakri, S., Sanusi, H., As Daud, N., &amp; Zainuddin, A. (2022). Obesity Measurement Index Is Associated With Hemoglobin A1c Level in Young Adult Without Diabetes: A Single-Center Cross-Sectional Study. <em>Journal Of Endocrinology And Metabolism, 12</em>(4-5), 140-145. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://jofem.org/index.php/jofem/article/view/823/284284589</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Sheri R. Colberg<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Ronald J. Sigal<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Jane E. Yardley<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Michael C. Riddell<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>David W. Dunstan<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Paddy C. Dempsey<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Edward S. Horton<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Kristin Castorino<span class="al-author-delim">, </span>Deborah F. Tate; Physical Activity/Exercise and Diabetes: A Position Statement of the American Diabetes Association. <em>Diabetes Care</em> 1 November 2016; 39 (11): 2065–2079. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2337/dc16-1728" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.2337/dc16-1728</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_11" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_11');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >11</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Managing Diabetes: Six Healthy Steps with the Most Benefit. Johns Hopkins Medicine. (2021, November 1). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/diabetes/managing-diabetes-six-healthy-steps-with-the-most-benefit</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_12" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_12');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >12</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Managing Diabetes: Six Healthy Steps with the Most Benefit. Johns Hopkins Medicine. (2021, November 1). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/diabetes/managing-diabetes-six-healthy-steps-with-the-most-benefit</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_13" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_13');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >13</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"></span><i style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);">Carbohydrates</i><span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);">. UF Health. (n.d.). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://ufhealth.org/conditions-and-treatments/carbohydrates</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_14" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_14');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >14</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">List of soluble fiber foods for IBS: Holiday edition. List of Soluble Fiber Foods for IBS: Holiday Edition | Bastyr University. (2023a, November 1). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://bastyr.edu/about/news/list-soluble-fiber-foods-ibs-holiday-edition</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_15" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_15');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >15</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><i>Understanding Carbs</i>. Carbs and Diabetes | ADA. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://diabetes.org/food-nutrition/understanding-carbs</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_16" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_16');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >16</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Wright, E. E., Jr, Kerr, M. S. D., Reyes, I. J., Nabutovsky, Y., &amp; Miller, E. (2021). Use of Flash Continuous Glucose Monitoring Is Associated With A1C Reduction in People With Type 2 Diabetes Treated With Basal Insulin or Noninsulin Therapy. </span><i style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);">Diabetes spectrum : a publication of the American Diabetes Association</i><span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);">, </span><i style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);">34</i><span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);">(2), 184–189. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.2337/ds20-0069</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_17" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_17');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >17</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Cleveland Clinic. (2024, March 19). Can taking cinnamon supplements lower your blood sugar? <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://health.clevelandclinic.org/can-taking-cinnamon-lower-your-blood-sugar</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_18" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_18');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >18</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">ELDerawi, W. A., Naser, I. A., Taleb, M. H., &amp; Abutair, A. S. (2018). The Effects of Oral Magnesium Supplementation on Glycemic Response among Type 2 Diabetes Patients. Nutrients, 11(1), 44. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3390/nu11010044</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_19" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_19');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >19</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Watts, M. (2023, October 29). Diabetes and Chromium. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.diabetes.co.uk/Diabetes-and-Chromium.html</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_20" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_20');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >20</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Yin, J., Xing, H., &amp; Ye, J. (2008). Efficacy of berberine in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Metabolism: clinical and experimental, 57(5), 712–717. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.metabol.2008.01.013</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2490_6_21" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2490_6_21');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >21</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Gibb, R. D., McRorie, J. W., Jr, Russell, D. A., Hasselblad, V., &amp; D&#8217;Alessio, D. A. (2015). Psyllium fiber improves glycemic control proportional to loss of glycemic control: a meta-analysis of data in euglycemic subjects, patients at risk of type 2 diabetes mellitus, and patients being treated for type 2 diabetes mellitus. The American journal of clinical nutrition, 102(6), 1604–1614. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3945/ajcn.115.106989</span></td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2490_6() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2490_6').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2490_6').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2490_6() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2490_6').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2490_6').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2490_6() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2490_6').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2490_6(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2490_6(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2490_6(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2490_6(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2490_6(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2490_6(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Blood Test Results Don&#8217;t Always Align: A SiPhox Health Insight</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/why-blood-test-results-dont-always-align/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 17:26:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood testing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bloodwork]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[capillary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fingerprick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fingerstick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hormones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lab results]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[LabCorp]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Quest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[venous]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2709</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From fluctuating hormones to lab analyzer variations, learn more about the nuance of blood test results and how you should interpret them.]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At SiPhox Health, accuracy isn’t just a goal—it&#8217;s a commitment. Every blood test we conduct is rigorously vetted in labs that boast CLIA certification and CAP accreditation. Furthermore, our clients frequently validate their blood test results against industry giants like Quest and LabCorp, reporting consistent positive correlations <span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="1">(see </span><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://proto.life/2022/12/at-home-blood-testing-just-got-a-whole-lot-better/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="2"><span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-419479582"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">here</span></span></a><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="3">, for example)</span>. Yet, the realm of clinical lab testing is inherently nuanced, and despite our best efforts, variations can occur.<!-- notionvc: 25407253-776b-4609-a1ed-5cae82011b50 --></p>
<h3><strong>The Precision Paradigm</strong></h3>
<p>Given that a whopping 70% of medical decisions hinge on lab tests, the stakes for accuracy are high. However, despite our (and others’) best efforts, variance has widely been accepted as commonplace in laboratory testing with lab errors having a reported frequency of 0.012–0.6% of all test results. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2709_7('footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2709_7('footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2709_7_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2709_7_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>At SiPhox Health, we&#8217;re committed to transparency and excellence throughout our product&#8217;s development. Our collaboration with CLIA-certified and CAP-accredited labs ensures our tests undergo rigorous validation against traditional venous draws. Despite this, it&#8217;s important to recognize the inherent variability within laboratory testing. Instrument variations, calibrator differences among reagent manufacturers, and unique lab reference ranges introduce a degree of variability. Unlike some in the at-home diagnostics field, we openly discuss the limitations of our technology, acknowledging that discrepancies can occur between labs, especially on immunoassay systems. A recognized industry standard accepts up to a 15% variation in results, known as the coefficient of variability, even when analyzing the same blood sample on identical machines. For a detailed look at the acceptable ranges for each analyte, visit <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://datainnovations.com/allowable-total-error-table">this link</a></span>. State-of-the-art equipment notwithstanding, minor calibration differences or reagent quality issues can lead to variances in outcomes.</p>
<p><span style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">The challenge of ensuring accurate blood test results is heightened by the use of different blood analyzing machines, such as Beckman or Abbott (the 2 leading diagnostic device manufacturers), which can lead to discrepancies in test outcomes. </span><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7271754/">This article</a></span><span style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);"> delves into the complexities of lab testing, highlighting the significant role that errors at various stages—before, during, and after analysis—play in affecting the precision of lab tests. Notably, many of these errors occur in the preanalytical phase, before the actual testing begins. The diversity of equipment used across laboratories underscores the difficulty in achieving standardized testing procedures and emphasizes the critical need for ongoing enhancements in lab practices. Our</span><span style="color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base); background-color: var(--global--color-background);"> openness about these challenges underscores our commitment to quality and the continuous improvement of our services, ensuring we provide reliable and accurate health monitoring solutions.</span></p>
<h3><strong>SiPhox Liquichek Analysis</strong></h3>
<p>Immunoassays are scientific tests conducted in laboratories to find out how much of a specific substance is present in a fluid, often used to detect levels of biomarkers in the body. The Liquichek Immunoassay Control is a product that clinical labs use to make sure their immunoassay tests are accurate and dependable. These controls have known concentration levels and are used to verify analyzer performance and calibration needs. Ideally, when using different testing machines (analyzers) to measure the same Liquichek control sample, the results should be consistent. However, this method is imperfect and variations do occur.</p>
<p>SiPhox Health analyzed <a href="https://siphox.notion.site/Bio-Rad-Liquichek-Data-38550f998562408b83b0778621000685?pvs=4"><span style="text-decoration: underline;">data from Bio-Rad</span></a> to see how much results can vary depending on the analyzer used across several Liquichek controls (L1, L2, and L3). We discovered that for some substances, like cortisol and insulin, the measured concentrations are fairly consistent across different analyzers. But for others, like testosterone and vitamin D, the results could vary dramatically, with discrepancies over 300% and 600%, respectively. This means that for these markers, different machines could show results that differ by more than six times, highlighting the challenge of ensuring uniformity in immunoassay testing across different equipment. (Note: the number of data points varies for each biomarker.)</p>
<p><!-- notionvc: 4143e600-6208-4e4b-8456-3208e495f052 --></p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-06-27-105416.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-3267" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-06-27-105416.png" alt="Why Blood Test Results Don’t Always Align: A SiPhox Health Insight" width="605" height="414" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-06-27-105416.png 823w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-06-27-105416-300x205.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Screenshot-2024-06-27-105416-768x525.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" /></a></p>
<h3><strong>Human Error</strong></h3>
<p>The inherent nature of at-home self-testing introduces a greater likelihood of human error compared to traditional sample collection methods. Common issues contributing to errors include insufficient sample quantity, contamination, and damaged samples (ex. smeared, hemolyzed), all of which are frequently cited as reasons for discrepancies in test results. To help counteract these potential sources of error, SiPhox Health provides free phlebotomy calls and recommends following specific collection guidelines:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Circulation is important</strong>. Instead of testing immediately after rolling out of bed, drink some water, wash your hands in warm water to remove potential contaminants, do some light exercises to get the blood going, and ensure that your hands are warm. Collecting your sample while standing up can let gravity do some of the work.</li>
<li><strong>Use proper pricking technique</strong>. After wiping the fingertip with alcohol, let the residual disinfectant air-dry for about 30 seconds. If you have callused fingertips, try to find an area on the finger that is softer. Press the lancet down firmly until you hear a click and feel a pinch.</li>
<li><strong>Collecting the sample</strong>. Flip the hand over and use your other hand to massage the pricked finger, starting at the knuckle and gently gliding down toward the fingertip until a large drop is formed. Droplets should be large enough to drip off the fingertip. Collect four large drops in one square before moving to the next. Don’t take too long to collect one square since this could lead to poor absorption and serum separation.
<ul>
<li>Trouble collecting enough blood? SiPhox Health is releasing a patented finger pump!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Shipping the test</strong>. Leave the card on the table for 30 minutes to an hour until it is completely dry to avoid smearing. Make sure to register your test, as unregistered tests cannot be analyzed by the lab. Samples are viable for 14 days, so ship them off in a timely manner to accommodate for transportation times.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Capillary Vs Venous</strong></h3>
<p>Capillary sampling has long since been used by the medical profession for those with difficult venous access, such as neonates, having shown a strong correlation with more traditional methods. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2709_7('footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2709_7('footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2709_7_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2709_7_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> SiPhox Health is at the vanguard, now utilizing this technology as a less invasive but equally reliable alternative to traditional venous draws, allowing for at-home collection without sacrificing accuracy. Our laboratories have undertaken rigorous validation studies comparing capillary samples directly with venous draws ensuring the reliability and accuracy of our results are upheld.</p>
<h3><strong>Understanding Natural Variabilities</strong></h3>
<p>Some biomarkers are subject to natural variation. Understanding these inherent variations is crucial for accurate health assessments. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cyclical Biological Patterns</strong>: Our hormonal landscape is dynamic, with cortisol and testosterone levels ebbing and flowing with the day&#8217;s rhythm. Other hormones such as TSH, estradiol, FSH, progesterone, and LH experience frequent fluctuations as well. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2709_7('footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2709_7('footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2709_7_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2709_7_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li><strong>Influences of Daily Living</strong>: The rhythms of our daily activities, including dietary habits, physical activity, fasting, and sleep patterns, significantly sway our biomarker levels.</li>
</ul>
<p>To mitigate the impact of these natural oscillations, we recommend consistent, periodic testing. A morning fasting test, ideally at a consistent time after waking up with every test, is recommended to standardize results and mitigate daily fluctuations.</p>
<p>Many biomarkers, including those mentioned, are influenced by daily biological cycles and lifestyle factors. These variables mean that for a truly comparative analysis, simultaneous blood draws across different laboratories would need to be conducted at the same time to detect true result errors.</p>
<p>For analytes like Vitamin D and Testosterone that are not commonly measured, there exists a broader industry issue: differing results across laboratories based on the specific instruments used, such as those from Beckman, Abbott, or Roche. This variation underscores a broader industry issue regarding uniformity in testing outcomes.</p>
<p>At SiPhox Health, we&#8217;ve dedicated ourselves to ensuring our tests&#8217; repeatability and validity, particularly against traditional venous draws. Our extensive internal studies, conducted during our product&#8217;s alpha phase, have confirmed that our measurements are consistent and responsive to changes in lifestyle and supplementation. This robust validation process underscores our commitment to providing accurate, reliable health monitoring solutions that reflect the dynamic nature of human biology.</p>
<p>The following is data from one of our clients shared with permission illustrating the responsive nature of blood tests to lifestyle events:</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Untitled.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2710" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Untitled.png" alt="" width="1211" height="475" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Untitled.png 1211w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Untitled-300x118.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Untitled-1024x402.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/Untitled-768x301.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1211px) 100vw, 1211px" /></a></p>
<p><em>Data shared from a client with permission</em></p>
<p>In general, some of these measurements work better as serial measurements because one is able to establish a baseline and then see deviations. Right now, doctors rely on single measurements because of logistical issues. In reality, a single measurement of many biomarkers contains a lot of uncertainty because they can change easily.</p>
<h3><strong>Embracing the Complexity</strong></h3>
<p>Acknowledging these factors doesn’t undermine the value of blood tests; rather, it highlights the importance of context, serial measurements, and choosing reputable labs like SiPhox Health. We&#8217;re transparent about the inherent challenges we face and committed to pushing the boundaries for accuracy.</p>
<h3><strong>Moving Forward</strong></h3>
<p>Variability in lab results is a known entity, yet it doesn’t detract from the utility of these tests. Instead, it underscores the need for careful interpretation, consistency in testing conditions, and ongoing technological improvements. SiPhox Health is leading the charge, ensuring that you can access reliable, precise health insights from the comfort of your own home, this year we plan to fully replace our current ADX collection card-based kits with our superior SiPhox Home readers &#8211; the same accurate results with quicker turnaround. Our goal? To empower you with the information you need to make informed health decisions, today and into the future.</p>
<p><!-- notionvc: dc112e9a-828c-482d-9c84-77654d7f0467 --></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2709_7();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2709_7();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2709_7">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2709_7" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2709_7('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2709_7_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Agarwal R. Measurement of errors in clinical laboratories. Indian J Clin Biochem. 2013 Jul;28(3):227-34. doi: 10.1007/s12291-013-0314-3. Epub 2013 Mar 26. PMID: 24426216; PMCID: PMC3689332. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3689332/#:~:text=in%20laboratory%20medicine.-,Laboratory%20errors%20have%20a%20reported%20frequency%20of%200.012%E2%80%930.6%20%25%20of,of%20laboratory%20tests%20%5B1%5D">Measurement of Errors in Clinical Laboratories &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2709_7('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2709_7_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Mrazek C, Lippi G, Keppel MH, Felder TK, Oberkofler H, Haschke-Becher E, Cadamuro J. Errors within the total laboratory testing process, from test selection to medical decision-making &#8211; A review of causes, consequences, surveillance and solutions. Biochem Med (Zagreb). 2020 Jun 15;30(2):020502. doi: 10.11613/BM.2020.020502. PMID: 32550813; PMCID: PMC7271754. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7271754/">Errors within the total laboratory testing process, from test selection to medical decision-making – A review of causes, consequences, surveillance and solutions &#8211; PMC (nih.gov</a>)</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2709_7_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2709_7('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2709_7_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Mazzoccoli G, Giuliani F, Sothern RB. A method to evaluate dynamics and periodicity of hormone secretion. J Biol Regul Homeost Agents. 2011 Apr-Jun;25(2):231-8. PMID: 21880212. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21880212/">A method to evaluate dynamics and periodicity of hormone secretion &#8211; PMC (nih.org)</a></td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2709_7() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2709_7').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2709_7').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2709_7() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2709_7').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2709_7').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2709_7() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2709_7').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2709_7(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2709_7(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2709_7(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2709_7(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2709_7(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2709_7(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Optimizing FSH for Enhanced Fertility: A Guide</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/optimizing-fsh-for-enhanced-fertility-a-guide/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colin Budries]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 18:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FSH]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[female fertility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fertility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[womens health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2476</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[FSH is key to understanding your fertility. It has many variables across age, gender, and lifestyle. Here are ways to better understand FSH. ]]></description>
			




							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>FSH is crucial for reproductive functions, regulating the menstrual cycle in women and sperm production in men. Understanding its role is key for assessing fertility and reproductive health.</li>
<li>Abnormal FSH levels can indicate health issues like POI and PCOS in women and testicular damage in men. Its measurement is essential for diagnosing and understanding various reproductive conditions.</li>
<li>Regular monitoring of FSH levels provides insights into changes in ovarian reserve and sperm production quality. This is crucial for informed decisions regarding fertility and overall reproductive health management.</li>
</ol>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>FSH is crucial for reproductive functions, regulating the menstrual cycle in women and sperm production in men. Understanding its role is key for assessing fertility and reproductive health.</li>
<li>Abnormal FSH levels can indicate health issues like POI and PCOS in women and testicular damage in men. Its measurement is essential for diagnosing and understanding various reproductive conditions.</li>
<li>Regular monitoring of FSH levels provides insights into changes in ovarian reserve and sperm production quality. This is crucial for informed decisions regarding fertility and overall reproductive health management.</li>
</ol>

</div><h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) plays a crucial role in the human body, particularly in the reproductive system. It is produced by the pituitary gland and is involved in sexual development and reproduction for both males and females. <strong>In females, FSH stimulates the production of <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/estradiol">estradiol</a> and regulates the menstrual cycle, peaking just before ovulation. In males, FSH works with <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/testosterone-page">testosterone</a> to maintain normal sperm count and function. FSH levels fluctuate during the menstrual cycle, with a peak in levels typically triggering ovulation.</strong></p>
<p>In women’s health, FSH is particularly significant. High levels of FSH may indicate conditions such as primary ovarian insufficiency (POI), polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), perimenopause, ovarian tumor, or Turner syndrome. Low FSH may indicate a pituitary gland disorder, hypothalamus disorder, insufficient egg production, or significant malnutrition. For males, high FSH may indicate testicular damage or Klinefelter syndrome, while low FSH may indicate pituitary gland or hypothalamus disorders. While high or low FSH may indicate certain conditions, FSH alone should not be used for diagnosis. FSH should be used in conjunction with other symptoms, biomarkers, and disease indicators. For these reasons, if you are concerned with your results, it is important to consult with your physician.</p>
<h2>Understanding FSH</h2>
<p>Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) is a gonadotropin, a type of hormone essential for reproductive processes in both females and males. In women, FSH is key to the growth and maturation of ovarian follicles, each containing an egg. It&#8217;s released by the pituitary gland and plays a critical role in regulating the menstrual cycle and stimulating the ovaries to produce estrogen. In the context of fertility, FSH levels are inversely indicative of ovarian reserve and function <strong>(i.e. high FSH indicates low ovarian reserve)</strong>, making it crucial for understanding a woman&#8217;s fertility potential at different stages of her reproductive life.</p>
<p>In men, Follicle-Stimulatin Hormone (FSH) plays a crucial role in reproduction, primarily by regulating the function of the testes. In males, FSH is secreted by the pituitary gland and is instrumental in the development and maturation of sperm. It acts directly on the Sertoli cells in the testes, which are essential for nurturing and supporting the development of sperm cells through the process of spermatogenesis. FSH stimulates these cells to produce and secrete various substances that promote sperm cell growth. Additionally, FSH is involved in increasing the concentration of testosterone-binding protein, which ensures a high local concentration of testosterone &#8211; essential for proper sperm development. This hormone&#8217;s activity is closely regulated by the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis, ensuring that sperm production is maintained at optimal levels for male fertility.</p>
<h2>Importance of Tracking FSH for Females</h2>
<ul>
<li>Repeat testing of FSH levels allows women to track changes over time, providing a clearer picture of their reproductive health and fertility status. Regular monitoring can indicate the onset of changes in ovarian reserve, especially as women age, and assist in making informed decisions about family planning and potential fertility treatments. It&#8217;s a valuable tool in understanding and managing reproductive health across different life stages.</li>
<li>SiPhox Health facilitates this through at-home tests, providing convenient and regular monitoring of FSH levels, and empowering women with valuable information for informed decision-making regarding their reproductive health.</li>
<li>Typically, a doctor might order an FSH test only once or infrequently, often in response to specific symptoms or concerns. This limited testing can miss fluctuations and trends in FSH levels over time, which are crucial for understanding a woman&#8217;s reproductive health and fertility status comprehensively. Regular, long-term tracking provides a more detailed and dynamic picture, allowing for better-informed decisions and timely interventions. This approach is more optimal than relying on single or infrequent tests for understanding and managing reproductive health changes.</li>
</ul>
<!-- <div class="block-quotes px-lg-40px ps-lg-60px ps-8px mb-32px">
    <div class="d-flex align-items-start">
        <img class="pe-20px" src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg' alt=""/>
        <div>
         
        <div class="bq-main"> <p>Research from <a href="https://journals.lww.com/co-obgyn/abstract/1998/06000/follicle_stimulating_hormone_as_a_predictor_of.9.aspx">&#8216;Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology&#8217;</a> highlights the predictive value of FSH levels in assessing ovarian function. One key insight is that elevated FSH levels in women, particularly in the early follicular phase of the menstrual cycle, can be a sign of reduced ovarian reserve. This information is crucial for understanding fertility potential and planning for conception.</p>

        </div> 
            
        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->


<div class="block-quotes">
    <img decoding="async" class="first" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">
    <img decoding="async" class="second" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">

    

    <div class="bq-main mb-28px">
        <p>Research from <a href="https://journals.lww.com/co-obgyn/abstract/1998/06000/follicle_stimulating_hormone_as_a_predictor_of.9.aspx">&#8216;Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology&#8217;</a> highlights the predictive value of FSH levels in assessing ovarian function. One key insight is that elevated FSH levels in women, particularly in the early follicular phase of the menstrual cycle, can be a sign of reduced ovarian reserve. This information is crucial for understanding fertility potential and planning for conception.</p>

    </div>

    
   

</div><h2>Importance of Tracking FSH for Males</h2>
<h3>Assessing Reproductive Health</h3>
<p>FSH is integral to male reproductive health, primarily because it governs spermatogenesis, the process of sperm production in the testes. In cases of infertility or reduced fertility, measuring FSH levels can provide crucial insights. Low levels of FSH are often linked to a decreased sperm count or poor sperm quality, whereas high levels might suggest a failure in the testicular response. This information is vital for understanding an individual&#8217;s reproductive capabilities and planning appropriate interventions or treatments. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Diagnosing Hormonal Imbalances</h3>
<p>Hormonal balance is crucial for overall health, and FSH plays a significant role in this equilibrium. Disorders like hypogonadism, where the body produces insufficient testosterone, can be detected through abnormal FSH levels. Symptoms of hormonal imbalances, such as reduced libido, erectile dysfunction, or changes in physical characteristics, can be distressing. By tracking FSH levels, healthcare providers can diagnose these imbalances early and prescribe suitable treatments to alleviate symptoms and restore hormonal balance. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Evaluating Testicular Function</h3>
<p>The health and functionality of the testes are directly reflected in FSH levels. Abnormal readings can indicate various conditions, ranging from testicular atrophy to damage caused by trauma, surgery, or infections. Men who have experienced such issues can benefit significantly from regular FSH monitoring, as it helps in early detection and treatment of potential complications, ensuring better long-term testicular health. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Monitoring Treatment Response</h3>
<p>For men undergoing treatments for infertility or hormonal imbalances, monitoring FSH levels is a key part of the therapeutic process. It allows healthcare providers to track how effectively the body is responding to the treatment. Therapy adjustments, whether they involve hormone replacement, surgical interventions, or lifestyle changes, can be guided by changes in FSH levels, leading to more successful outcomes. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Detecting Underlying Conditions</h3>
<p>Elevated FSH levels can sometimes signal issues beyond the reproductive system, such as disorders of the pituitary gland, which regulates the production of various hormones. Conditions like Klinefelter syndrome, a genetic disorder affecting male chromosomes, or varicocele, an enlargement of the veins within the scrotum, can also alter FSH levels. Detecting these conditions early can lead to more effective management and treatment. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Guiding Clinical Decisions</h3>
<p>Understanding a patient&#8217;s FSH levels helps clinicians make more informed decisions regarding their care. It plays a crucial role in determining the best approach to treatment, be it hormone therapies, surgical interventions, or assisted reproductive techniques like in vitro fertilization (IVF). Additionally, FSH levels provide valuable information for counseling men about their fertility prospects and future family planning options. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>FSH Levels and Pregnancy</h2>
<ul>
<li>Optimal FSH levels for conception typically range from about 4.7 to 21.5 mIU/mL <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></a>, depending on a woman&#8217;s age and the specific phase of her menstrual cycle. Lower FSH levels are generally more favorable for fertility. However, individual factors and health conditions can influence these levels. It&#8217;s important to consult with a healthcare provider for personalized assessment and guidance.</li>
<li>Even with higher FSH levels, conception can still be possible, but it may become more challenging. Each woman’s fertility profile is unique, and FSH is just one of many factors influencing it.</li>
<li>Knowing FSH levels before and after attempting to get pregnant helps in understanding a woman&#8217;s fertility window and potential challenges. Pre-pregnancy, it can indicate ovarian reserve and readiness for conception. Post-pregnancy, it aids in monitoring recovery and understanding any changes in fertility, especially in cases of difficulties in conceiving or planning for future pregnancies. This knowledge is vital for informed health decisions and family planning. For personalized advice, consult with a healthcare provider.</li>
</ul>
<h2>FSH and Women&#8217;s Age-Related Fertility</h2>
<p>FSH levels naturally vary with age in women. In the reproductive years, FSH levels fluctuate within the menstrual cycle, with a notable increase triggering ovulation. As women approach menopause, their ovarian reserve declines, leading to a significant rise in FSH levels. This increase is a response to decreased estrogen production, as the body attempts to stimulate the ovaries to produce more estrogen. The elevated FSH levels during this phase can be a marker of the transition into menopause. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>As women approach their late 30s and 40s, FSH levels may start to rise, signaling a decrease in ovarian reserve. This increase becomes more pronounced as women near menopause, typically in their late 40s to 50s, reflecting the diminished estrogen production and reduced fertility. These age-related changes in FSH levels are key indicators of a woman&#8217;s reproductive life stage. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>Strategies to Optimize FSH Levels</h2>
<h3>Lifestyle Changes</h3>
<p>Managing stress through techniques like meditation, yoga, or regular exercise can help regulate hormone levels, including FSH. Adequate sleep is crucial, as disrupted sleep patterns can affect hormonal balance. Avoiding smoking and limiting alcohol consumption is also beneficial, as these can impact FSH levels and overall fertility.</p>
<h3>Dietary Changes</h3>
<p>A balanced diet rich in antioxidants can support reproductive health. Foods high in antioxidants, such as fruits, vegetables, nuts, and whole grains, are recommended. Reducing intake of processed foods and maintaining a healthy weight through diet and exercise is key, as obesity can affect hormone levels.</p>
<h3 class="p-rich_text_section">Supplement Regimen</h3>
<ul>
<li>To Lower FSH Levels:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Royal Jelly: This nutrient-rich substance can help reduce FSH levels.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Omega-3 Fatty Acids: Found in supplements like fish oil, they can assist in regulating hormone levels.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Vitamin D: Essential for hormonal regulation, it can be supplemented or obtained from sun exposure.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Zinc: A crucial mineral for reproductive health, which can aid in hormonal balance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>To Increase FSH Levels:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Oyster Polypeptides: Derived from oysters, these supplements may increase FSH levels.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Probiotics: Supporting gut health, which in turn can impact hormonal balance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>While lifestyle and dietary changes can influence overall health, they may not directly alter FSH levels significantly and should be viewed as part of a broader health strategy. Always follow the advice of your physician when making dietary changes or introducing a new supplement.</p>
<h2>Interpreting your Results</h2>
<p>Females should take FSH tests on day 3<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_8('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_8_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></a> of their menstrual cycle. When interpreting results for FSH, it is important to consider how dynamic this hormone can be. In those who menstruate, FSH varies considerably between the follicular and luteal phases of the menstrual cycle. Levels increase with age, but a surge occurs during perimenopause (the start of menopause) and remains high post-menopause. In males, FSH is low and is relatively static in comparison.</p>
<p>The following graph by <a href="https://www.straighthealthcare.com/female-hormone-physiology.html">Straight Healthcare</a> shows how variable FSH can be for menstruating females, along with other hormones that are important for the regulation of the menstrual cycle.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2410" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image.png" alt="" width="2000" height="1294" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image.png 2000w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-300x194.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-1024x663.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-768x497.png 768w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-1536x994.png 1536w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-1568x1014.png 1568w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" /></p>
<h2>Reference Ranges</h2>
<p>To assist in the interpretation of test results, the <a href="https://www.abim.org/Media/bfijryql/laboratory-reference-ranges.pdf">American Board of Internal Medicine</a> published reference ranges for FSH:</p>
<ul>
<li>Normally Menstruating Females:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Follicular phase: 2 – 9 mIU/mL</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Mid-cycle peak: 4 – 22 mIU/mL</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Luteal phase: 2 – 9 mIU/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Postmenopausal Females:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">30 mIU/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Males:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">1 – 7 mIU/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Abnormally high or low levels of FSH could be indicative of a more serious issue, so please consult with your physician if you are concerned with any of your results.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>At SiPhox Health, we firmly believe in the power of understanding your body through regular FSH monitoring. This knowledge is not just a number; it&#8217;s a window into your reproductive well-being, guiding you in making informed decisions about your fertility journey and overall health. Our easy-to-use at-home testing kits bring this vital health information right to your doorstep, making it easier than ever to keep track of your fertility health.</p>
<h3><span id="Tracking_your_Vitamin_D_with_SiPhox_Health">Tracking your FSH with SiPhox Health:</span></h3>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li><strong>$295 one-time or subscribe to get $85 per test*</strong></li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 (4 Hormonal Balance markers including FSH in the female Base Panel)</li>
<li>Hormone+ (includes FSH for males, as well) and Thyroid+ add-on panels</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<div class="next-chapter">
    <div class="text-uppercase">
        <h4 class="m-0">
            start your siphox health journey
        </h4>
    </div>
    <div class="title">
        <h3 class="mt-0">
            Home health testing has never been this good
        </h3>
    </div>
    <p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your FSH + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>

    <a href='https://l.siphox.health/fsh'class='btn-cta'>Get started<span class='ms-8px'><img src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/right-arrow-light.svg' /></span></a>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2636" role="img" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg" alt="" width="1182" height="1001" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2476_8();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2476_8();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2476_8">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2476_8" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Santi D, Crépieux P, Reiter E, Spaggiari G, Brigante G, Casarini L, Rochira V, Simoni M. Follicle-stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles. J Clin Med. 2020 Apr 3;9(4):1014. doi: 10.3390/jcm9041014. PMID: 32260182; PMCID: PMC7230878. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7230878/"><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles</span> &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Kumar P, Kumar N, Thakur DS, Patidar A. Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment. J Adv Pharm Technol Res. 2010 Jul;1(3):297-301. doi: 10.4103/0110-5558.72420. PMID: 22247861; PMCID: PMC3255409. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3255409/">Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Santi D, Crépieux P, Reiter E, Spaggiari G, Brigante G, Casarini L, Rochira V, Simoni M. Follicle-stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles. J Clin Med. 2020 Apr 3;9(4):1014. doi: 10.3390/jcm9041014. PMID: 32260182; PMCID: PMC7230878. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7230878/"><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles</span> &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Leslie SW, Soon-Sutton TL, Khan MAB. Male Infertility. 2023 Mar 3. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan–. PMID: 32965929. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK562258/">Male Infertility &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Kumar P, Kumar N, Thakur DS, Patidar A. Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment. J Adv Pharm Technol Res. 2010 Jul;1(3):297-301. doi: 10.4103/0110-5558.72420. PMID: 22247861; PMCID: PMC3255409. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3255409/">Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Leslie SW, Soon-Sutton TL, Khan MAB. Male Infertility. 2023 Mar 3. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan–. PMID: 32965929. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK562258/">Male Infertility &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/24638-follicle-stimulating-hormone-fsh**"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/24638-follicle-stimulating-hormone-fsh</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Santoro N, Randolph JF Jr. Reproductive hormones and the menopause transition. Obstet Gynecol Clin North Am. 2011 Sep;38(3):455-66. doi: 10.1016/j.ogc.2011.05.004. PMID: 21961713; PMCID: PMC3197715. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3197715/">Reproductive hormones and the menopause transition &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Jirge PR. Poor ovarian reserve. J Hum Reprod Sci. 2016 Apr-Jun;9(2):63-9. doi: 10.4103/0974-1208.183514. PMID: 27382229; PMCID: PMC4915288. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4915288/">Poor ovarian reserve &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_8_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_8_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><a href="https://www.illumefertility.com/fertility-care/fertility-testing/what-is-cycle-day-3#:~:text=When%20a%20woman%20is%20undergoing,)%20and%20estradiol%20(E2).)"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.illumefertility.com/fertility-care/fertility-testing/what-is-cycle-day-3#:~:text=When</span> a woman is undergoing,) and estradiol (E2).)</td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_8() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2476_8').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2476_8').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2476_8() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2476_8').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2476_8').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2476_8() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2476_8').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_8(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2476_8(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2476_8(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_8(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_8(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_8(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cortisol Levels Unveiled: Managing Stress Through At-Home Testing</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/cortisol-levels-unveiled-managing-stress-through-at-home-testing/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 17:38:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cortisol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[at-home test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cortisol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hormones]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sleep]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stress]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2837</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Find out how stress and cortisol levels are intertwined, and what you can do to prevent adverse health effects.]]></description>
			


							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Key Takeaways:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Cortisol is a hormone crucial for stress regulation, metabolism, and immune function. Its levels follow a diurnal rhythm, peaking in the morning and declining by evening.</li>
<li>Cortisol aids in managing physical and psychological stress. Chronic high cortisol levels can lead to serious health issues related to inflammation and cardiovascular health, while low levels may indicate adrenal insufficiency.</li>
<li>Regular at-home testing of cortisol can detect abnormal levels early, helping prevent potential health issues. SiPhox Health offers convenient testing kits to monitor cortisol along with other important health markers.</li>
</ul>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>When stress is short-lived, the onset of atrophy is reversible, but long-term stress can lead to the death of neurons located in the hippocampus. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>When stress is short-lived, the onset of atrophy is reversible, but long-term stress can lead to the death of neurons located in the hippocampus. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>

</div><h2>What is cortisol?</h2>
<p>Cortisol is a hormone synthesized and secreted by the adrenal glands of the kidneys that plays a major role in regulating stress, metabolism, and immunity.</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/labeledadrenalglandandkidneybyscottholmes.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2840" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/labeledadrenalglandandkidneybyscottholmes.jpg" alt="" width="740" height="678" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/labeledadrenalglandandkidneybyscottholmes.jpg 740w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/labeledadrenalglandandkidneybyscottholmes-300x275.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></a></p>
<p><em>“Adrenal Disorders.” Baylor College of Medicine, www.bcm.edu/healthcare/specialties/endocrinology/endocrinology-diabetes-and-metabolism/adrenal-disorders. Accessed 3 May 2024.</em></p>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>It follows a diurnal rhythm affected by sleep- naturally rising in the early morning and falling in the evening.</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/adrenal_curve_normal.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2838" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/adrenal_curve_normal.jpg" alt="" width="359" height="299" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/adrenal_curve_normal.jpg 359w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/adrenal_curve_normal-300x250.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 359px) 100vw, 359px" /></a></div>
<div>
<p><em>“Diurnal Cortisol Curves.” ZRT Laboratory, www.zrtlab.com/landing-pages/diurnal-cortisol-curves/. Accessed 3 May 2024.</em></p>
<p>Although cortisol is ultimately secreted by the kidneys, it all starts in the brain— more specifically, the hypothalamus. The hypothalamus is a part of the brain that bridges the gap between the nervous system (thoughts and sensations traveling between the brain, spinal cord, and nerves) and the endocrine system (hormones secreted by glands). In doing so, it helps maintain homeostasis within the body by regulating phenomena such as body temperature, heart rate, hunger, mood, sleep, thirst, etc. through the modulation of hormones. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>Like many hormones, the secretion of cortisol involves a few steps. The hypothalamus secretes a hormone that prompts the anterior pituitary gland to secrete a hormone that signals the adrenal glands to secrete cortisol. This cross-communication is called the HPA (hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal) axis.</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2839" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1.png" alt="" width="5118" height="4200" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1.png 5118w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1-300x246.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1-1024x840.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1-768x630.png 768w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1-1536x1260.png 1536w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1-2048x1681.png 2048w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/230413-figure-1-1568x1287.png 1568w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 5118px) 100vw, 5118px" /></a></p>
<p><em>“Cortisol | You and Your Hormones from the Society of Endocrinology.” You and Your Hormones, Jan. 2019, www.yourhormones.info/hormones/cortisol/.</em></p>
</div>
<p>It all seems complicated because it is! The fascinating complexity of the human body allows for fine-tuned regulation of important responses and integration between different systems (neurological and hormonal).</p>
<h2>How is stress related to cortisol?</h2>
<p>A stress response can result from any physical or psychological stimulus (stressor) that disrupts the body’s homeostasis. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> </span>Cortisol helps the body manage stress by maintaining fluid balance and blood pressure, regulating metabolism, and suppressing non-essential functions (like the immune system) to focus resources on dealing with the stressor. While stress is important in moderation to motivate us through our day-to-day activities, excessive amounts can be detrimental and lead to long-term health implications such as the development of coronary heart disease, for example. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: e74ff0a5-dcae-45d2-9eba-ddb3ffc53527 --></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: 84c840cc-1cd5-4a68-bf88-cba38693d37a --></p>
<p>High cortisol levels are an indicator of acute (sudden), chronic (long-term), and/or traumatic (life-threatening) stress. Secondary factors associated with mental stress include alcohol drinking, smoking, a lack of exercise, inadequate sleep, and poor nutrition. Over time, prolonged high levels of cortisol (Cushing&#8217;s disease or hypercortisolism) can lead to weight gain, fat redistribution, poor sleep, a lowered immune system, and increased inflammation. High cortisol levels can also inhibit testosterone secretion due to stress-related suppression. Elevated levels of cortisol in older adults have been linked to higher levels of psychosocial stress, poorer cognitive performance, and atrophy of memory-related structures in the brain. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>On the flip side, low levels of cortisol might indicate poor adrenal function or Addison&#8217;s disease. This could lead to symptoms including fatigue, unintentional weight loss, poor appetite, and hypotension. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>The Importance of Cortisol Testing</h2>
<p>Because of cortisol’s widespread effects on a variety of important physiological areas (inflammation, immunity, metabolism, cardiovascular health, cognitive fitness, etc.), testing cortisol can help to identify potential issues before they progress. With SiPhox Health’s frequent testing capabilities, you can monitor your own cortisol levels (along with 16 other markers of inflammation, metabolic, hormonal, and cardiovascular health) to ensure they are within normal physiological range and catch abnormalities.</p>
<p>Normal serum cortisol ranges for adults: <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Peaks in the morning between 6 am &#8211; 8 am: 10-20 ug/dL</li>
<li>Falls in the evening around 4 pm: 3-10 ug/dL</li>
</ul>
<p>While levels in the lower range are better for inflammation, morning cortisol levels under 3 ug/dL may indicate adrenal insufficiency. Cortisol levels consistently above the normal range may indicate Cushing&#8217;s disease which could point towards the presence of tumors. Keep in mind that certain medications can alter cortisol production, so it is important to talk to your doctor if you are concerned with your levels. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span></p>
<p>A 3-point cortisol test, often referred to as a &#8220;diurnal cortisol test,&#8221; measures cortisol levels at three different times of the day to assess the adrenal gland&#8217;s function and the body&#8217;s stress response. Although it is expected to see natural variations, atypically high or low results at these specific times may indicate an adrenal gland disorder. Because saliva is convenient to collect, the 3-point salivary cortisol test may be more beneficial for those who are looking to confirm the presence of abnormalities or underlying diseases through repeat testing throughout the day compared to a blood test.</p>
<p>Ultimately, the main difference between the saliva and blood tests is that the three-point test is more diagnostic in nature, especially for conditions that affect cortisol rhythm, while the fingerprick test is more suited for general monitoring.</p>
<h2>What lifestyle changes can help regulate my cortisol levels?</h2>
<p>If your cortisol levels are on the <strong>higher</strong> side, studies suggests the following interventions may help with regulation:</p>
<ul>
<li>Herbs and natural supplements such as <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23439798/">ashwagandha</a> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13651501.2017.1417442">Rhodiola</a> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_11');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_11');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_11" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[11]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_11" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4245564/">lemon balm</a> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_12');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_12');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_12" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[12]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_12" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, and <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29080520/">chamomile</a> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_13');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_13');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_13" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[13]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_13" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Aim for 8 hours of restful <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9415946/">sleep</a> (avoid caffeine after midday <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_14');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_14');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_14" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[14]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_14" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, wear blue-light blocking glasses <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_15');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_15');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_15" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[15]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_15" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, put the screens away before bed <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_16');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_16');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_16" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[16]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_16" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>)</li>
<li>Spend more time in nature <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_17');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_17');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_17" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[17]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_17" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span></li>
<li>Practice yoga, tai chi, qi gong, and other mindfulness meditation and breathing exercises <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_18');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_18');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_18" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[18]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_18" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Foods such as dark chocolate, garlic, fermented foods (kimchi, yogurt), and plants high in vitamin C (oranges, broccoli) <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_19');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_19');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_19" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[19]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_19" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span></li>
<li>Surround yourself with healthy relationships <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_20');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_20');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_20" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[20]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_20" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> (<a href="https://newsinhealth.nih.gov/sites/nihNIH/files/2018/February/NIHNiHFeb2018.pdf">pets</a> are a plus! <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_21');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2837_9('footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_21');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_21" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[21]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2837_9_21" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>)</span></li>
</ul>
<h2>Testing with SiPhox Health</h2>
<h4>The Scientific Benefits of SiPhox Health include:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced Frequency:</strong> Our regular testing can detect health marker changes more swiftly than annual screenings.</li>
<li><strong>Convenience and Comfort:</strong> The ease of SiPhox Health’s at-home testing eliminates the need for scheduling clinic visits and enduring long waits.</li>
<li><strong>Health Data:</strong> SiPhox Health reports provide insights tailored to individual health profiles, enabling more informed healthcare decisions.</li>
<li><strong>Early Detection and Prevention:</strong> The comprehensive nature of our testing facilitates the early detection of potential health issues, allowing for timely intervention.</li>
<li><strong>Data-Driven Lifestyle Adjustments:</strong> With a more detailed health profile, individuals can adjust their lifestyle choices more precisely to match their health needs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What’s included with a SiPhox Health test panel:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>At-Home Convenience:</strong> Our kit comes to your door. Specially designed for easy, low-pain blood collection through a simple fingerprick method.</li>
<li><strong>Flexible Pricing:</strong> Access our services at $345 for a one-time test, or embrace regular health monitoring with subscriptions at just $85 per test.</li>
<li><strong>Comprehensive Biomarker Analysis:</strong> Our base panel examines 17 essential biomarkers, plus delves deeper with our Hormone+ and Thyroid+ add-on panels for a full health spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Integrated Health Tracking:</strong> We support sleep and activity tracking across more than 200 wearable devices, ensuring you get a holistic view of your health, with results delivered swiftly within 2-5 business days.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- notionvc: e22ab155-4a9a-4521-a7aa-f0b46da3a0ff --></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: d380c66e-c7d1-4d7d-b33f-fdc61ff55da2 --></p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2837_9();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2837_9();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2837_9">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2837_9" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Dziurkowska, E., &amp; Wesolowski, M. (2021). Cortisol as a Biomarker of Mental Disorder Severity. <i>Journal of clinical medicine</i>, <i>10</i>(21), 5204. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm10215204</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Dziurkowska, E., &amp; Wesolowski, M. (2021). Cortisol as a Biomarker of Mental Disorder Severity. <i>Journal of clinical medicine</i>, <i>10</i>(21), 5204. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3390/jcm10215204</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“Hypothalamus: Medlineplus Medical Encyclopedia.” <i>MedlinePlus</i>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, medlineplus.gov/ency/article/002380.htm. Accessed 3 May 2024.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><span style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Chu B, Marwaha K, Sanvictores T, et al. Physiology, Stress Reaction. [Updated 2022 Sep 12]. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2024 Jan-. </span><span class="bk_cite_avail" style="background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-family: var(--global--font-secondary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Available from: <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK541120/</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Smith, G. D., Ben-Shlomo, Y., Beswick, A., Yarnell, J., Lightman, S., &amp; Elwood, P. (2005). Cortisol, testosterone, and coronary heart disease: prospective evidence from the Caerphilly study. <i>Circulation</i>, <i>112</i>(3), 332–340. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.104.489088</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Lavretsky, H., &amp; Newhouse, P. A. (2012). Stress, inflammation, and aging. <i>The American journal of geriatric psychiatry : official journal of the American Association for Geriatric Psychiatry</i>, <i>20</i>(9), 729–733. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1097/JGP.0b013e31826573cf</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Cleveland Clinic. “Cortisol: What It Is, Function, Symptoms &amp; Levels.” <i>Cleveland Clinic</i>, 10 Dec. 2021, my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/22187-cortisol.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Cleveland Clinic. “Cortisol: What It Is, Function, Symptoms &amp; Levels.” <i>Cleveland Clinic</i>, 10 Dec. 2021, my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/22187-cortisol.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Munir S, Quintanilla Rodriguez BS, Waseem M. Addison Disease. [Updated 2024 Jan 30]. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2024 Jan-. <span class="bk_cite_avail">Available from: <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK441994/</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Chandrasekhar, K., Kapoor, J., &amp; Anishetty, S. (2012). A prospective, randomized double-blind, placebo-controlled study of safety and efficacy of a high-concentration full-spectrum extract of ashwagandha root in reducing stress and anxiety in adults. <i>Indian journal of psychological medicine</i>, <i>34</i>(3), 255–262. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.4103/0253-7176.106022</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_11" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_11');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >11</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Anghelescu, I. G., Edwards, D., Seifritz, E., &amp; Kasper, S. (2018). Stress management and the role of <i>Rhodiola rosea</i>: a review. <i>International journal of psychiatry in clinical practice</i>, <i>22</i>(4), 242–252. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1080/13651501.2017.1417442</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_12" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_12');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >12</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Scholey, A., Gibbs, A., Neale, C., Perry, N., Ossoukhova, A., Bilog, V., Kras, M., Scholz, C., Sass, M., &amp; Buchwald-Werner, S. (2014). Anti-stress effects of lemon balm-containing foods. <i>Nutrients</i>, <i>6</i>(11), 4805–4821. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3390/nu6114805</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_13" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_13');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >13</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Keefe, J. R., Guo, W., Li, Q. S., Amsterdam, J. D., &amp; Mao, J. J. (2018). An exploratory study of salivary cortisol changes during chamomile extract therapy of moderate to severe generalized anxiety disorder. <i>Journal of psychiatric research</i>, <i>96</i>, 189–195. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpsychires.2017.10.011</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_14" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_14');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >14</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Gardiner, C., Weakley, J., Burke, L. M., Roach, G. D., Sargent, C., Maniar, N., Townshend, A., &amp; Halson, S. L. (2023). The effect of caffeine on subsequent sleep: A systematic review and meta-analysis. <i>Sleep medicine reviews</i>, <i>69</i>, 101764. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.smrv.2023.101764</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_15" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_15');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >15</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Hester, L., Dang, D., Barker, C. J., Heath, M., Mesiya, S., Tienabeso, T., &amp; Watson, K. (2021). Evening wear of blue-blocking glasses for sleep and mood disorders: a systematic review. <i>Chronobiology international</i>, <i>38</i>(10), 1375–1383. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1080/07420528.2021.1930029</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_16" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_16');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >16</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">AlShareef S. M. (2022). The impact of bedtime technology use on sleep quality and excessive daytime sleepiness in adults. <i>Sleep science (Sao Paulo, Brazil)</i>, <i>15</i>(Spec 2), 318–327. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.5935/1984-0063.20200128</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_17" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_17');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >17</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Antonelli, M., Barbieri, G. &amp; Donelli, D. Effects of forest bathing (shinrin-yoku) on levels of cortisol as a stress biomarker: a systematic review and meta-analysis. <i style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Int J Biometeorol</i><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);"> </span><b style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">63</b><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">, 1117–1134 (2019). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00484-019-01717-x</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_18" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_18');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >18</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Turakitwanakan, W., Mekseepralard, C., &amp; Busarakumtragul, P. (2013). Effects of mindfulness meditation on serum cortisol of medical students. <i>Journal of the Medical Association of Thailand = Chotmaihet thangphaet</i>, <i>96 Suppl 1</i>, S90–S95.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_19" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_19');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >19</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Heckman, William. “The Best Foods to Relieve Stress (and Some to Avoid).” <i style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">The American Institute of Stress</i><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">, 11 Aug. 2021, www.stress.org/the-best-foods-to-relieve-stress-and-some-to-avoid.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_20" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_20');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >20</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Shrout, M. R., Renna, M. E., Madison, A. A., Jaremka, L. M., Fagundes, C. P., Malarkey, W. B., &amp; Kiecolt-Glaser, J. K. (2020). Cortisol slopes and conflict: A spouse&#8217;s perceived stress matters. <i>Psychoneuroendocrinology</i>, <i>121</i>, 104839. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psyneuen.2020.104839</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2837_9_21" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2837_9_21');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >21</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">“The Power of Pets.” <i style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">NIH News in Health</i><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); background-color: var(--global--color-background); color: var(--global--color-primary); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">, Feb. 2018, newsinhealth.nih.gov/sites/nihNIH/files/2018/February/NIHNiHFeb2018.pdf.</td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2837_9() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2837_9').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2837_9').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2837_9() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2837_9').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2837_9').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2837_9() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2837_9').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2837_9(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2837_9(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2837_9(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2837_9(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2837_9(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2837_9(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Predicting Biological Age with DNA Methylation</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/predicting-biological-age-with-dna-methylation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pavel Korecky]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 17:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DNA Methylation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aging]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[at-home test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biological age]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biological clock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DNA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[epigenetic clock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[longevity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[methylation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2781</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By understanding DNA methylation, individuals can take proactive steps to improve their health span and enhance their quality of life.]]></description>
			
							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the quest to understand aging and its impact on health, scientists have developed innovative tools to peer into the molecular mechanisms underlying the aging process. One key distinction is between biological aging, which reflects the true wear and tear on our bodies, and chronological aging, simply a count of the years since birth.</p>
<h2><strong>What is DNA Methylation?</strong></h2>
<p>A methyl group is a chemical entity composed of one carbon atom bonded to three hydrogen atoms. It acts as a fundamental building block in various biological processes and plays a crucial role in DNA methylation. DNA methylation is a biological process that modifies our cellular DNA by adding methyl groups, effectively signaling genes to turn on or off without altering the underlying DNA sequence. This molecular mechanism serves as a regulatory switchboard, modifying the expression of genes, influencing how they function, and affecting various biological processes in the body including the manifestation of various biological traits. Much like adding annotations or post-it notes to a book can alter how we interpret and interact with the text.</p>
<h2><strong>Predicting Biological Age with DNA Methylation</strong></h2>
<p>Recent advances in research have demonstrated that DNA methylation patterns can serve as reliable predictors of biological age. Scientists have developed epigenetic clocks, such as GrimAge, which analyzes specific DNA methylation markers to estimate an individual&#8217;s biological age. By scrutinizing thousands of these markers and their correlations, these clocks can accurately assess how an individual&#8217;s DNA has aged over time.</p>
<h2><strong>Interpreting GrimAge Results</strong></h2>
<p>Receiving your GrimAge report for <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/">SiPhox Health</a></span>, unveils a personalized snapshot of your biological age journey. A GrimAge lower than your chronological age signifies a promising start on your aging trajectory, indicative of a younger biological age. Percentile rank further contextualizes your results, offering insights into how you fare compared to others of the same chronological age. A percentile rank of 87 on your biological age test, it would mean that your biological age is younger than 87% of others of the same chronological age. By contrast, if you scored 50% or less, that means your biological age is higher than average compared to others of your same chronological age.</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screenshot-2024-04-26-111247.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2795" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screenshot-2024-04-26-111247.png" alt="" width="1048" height="538" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screenshot-2024-04-26-111247.png 1048w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screenshot-2024-04-26-111247-300x154.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screenshot-2024-04-26-111247-1024x526.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screenshot-2024-04-26-111247-768x394.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1048px) 100vw, 1048px" /></a><em>SiPhox Health data shared from a client with permission</em></p>
<h2><strong>Embracing the Potential for Change</strong></h2>
<p>Perhaps most compellingly, GrimAge underscores the modifiability of biological age, offering hope in the quest for healthy aging. Armed with insights from GrimAge, individuals can track the impact of lifestyle choices, dietary habits, and anti-aging interventions on their rate of aging. This dynamic approach empowers individuals to take proactive steps in optimizing their health span and lifespan, ultimately shaping a future characterized by vitality and well-being.</p>
<h2><strong>Predicted Telomere Length</strong></h2>
<p>Predicted telomere length is another biomarker used to assess aspects of biological aging, focused specifically on telomere dynamics and cellular aging.</p>
<p>Telomeres are repetitive DNA sequences found at the ends of chromosomes that protect them from deterioration and fusion with neighboring chromosomes. With each cell division telomeres undergo shortening, serving as crucial markers of cellular aging.</p>
<p>A notable advancement in telomere length assessment is the DNA methylation-based estimator (DNAmTL), developed by the Horvath lab. This method analyzes blood methylation data from numerous individuals, identifying CpG sites (a specific DNA sequence) whose methylation levels best predict telomere length. DNAmTL surpasses traditional telomere length measurement (LTL) in predicting mortality, heart disease, and age-related conditions. Furthermore, it correlates with lifestyle factors like diet, physical activity, and smoking.</p>
<h2><strong>Improving Your DNA Methylation Results</strong></h2>
<p>There are several ways individuals can improve their DNA methylation results and promote healthy aging. Lifestyle factors such as diet, exercise, and stress management play critical roles in shaping DNA methylation patterns. Similarly, smoking has been linked to decreased methylation. However, quitting smoking has been shown to reverse this effect, leading to increased methylation. This reversal suggests that former smokers can eventually exhibit gene expression levels comparable to those of non-smokers through cessation. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2781_10('footnote_plugin_reference_2781_10_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2781_10('footnote_plugin_reference_2781_10_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2781_10_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2781_10_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2781_10('footnote_plugin_reference_2781_10_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2781_10('footnote_plugin_reference_2781_10_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2781_10_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2781_10_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>In conclusion, DNA methylation analysis offers a powerful tool for predicting biological age and assessing individual health risks. By understanding and interpreting DNA methylation results, individuals can take proactive steps to improve their health span and enhance their quality of life.</p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2781_10();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2781_10();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2781_10">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2781_10" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2781_10_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2781_10('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2781_10_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Abraham, M. J., El Sherbini, A., El-Diasty, M., Askari, S., &amp; Szewczuk, M. R. (2023). Restoring Epigenetic Reprogramming with Diet and Exercise to Improve Health-Related Metabolic Diseases. Biomolecules, 13(2), 318. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.3390/biom13020318</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2781_10_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2781_10('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2781_10_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (2022, August 15). <i>What is epigenetics?</i>. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.cdc.gov/genomics/disease/epigenetics.htm</span></td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2781_10() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2781_10').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2781_10').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2781_10() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2781_10').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2781_10').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2781_10() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2781_10').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2781_10(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2781_10(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2781_10(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2781_10(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2781_10(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2781_10(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hs-CRP: The #1 Inflammation Marker</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/why-measure-your-inflammation-hs-crp-and-what-does-it-mean/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2023 08:34:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hs-CRP]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1830</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[hs-CRP is key in detecting chronic inflammation. It impacts health, longevity, and disease prevention.]]></description>
			



							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>Chronic inflammation, detectable through high-sensitivity CRP (hs-CRP) blood tests, is a major contributor to several leading causes of death, including heart disease, cancer, and diabetes. It can be silently harmful for years.</li>
<li>Chronically elevated CRP levels are linked to an increased risk for noncommunicable diseases and are now recognized as an active cause of inflammation, not just a marker.</li>
<li>Lifestyle changes, such as improved diet, regular exercise, and quitting smoking, along with certain supplements like curcumin and Omega-3, can effectively lower CRP levels and reduce inflammation.</li>
</ol>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>Chronic inflammation, detectable through high-sensitivity CRP (hs-CRP) blood tests, is a major contributor to several leading causes of death, including heart disease, cancer, and diabetes. It can be silently harmful for years.</li>
<li>Chronically elevated CRP levels are linked to an increased risk for noncommunicable diseases and are now recognized as an active cause of inflammation, not just a marker.</li>
<li>Lifestyle changes, such as improved diet, regular exercise, and quitting smoking, along with certain supplements like curcumin and Omega-3, can effectively lower CRP levels and reduce inflammation.</li>
</ol>

</div><h2>Why Measure Your Inflammation (hs-CRP), and What Does It Mean</h2>
<p>There are two main types of inflammation. Acute (short-term) and chronic inflammation (long-term, low-level).</p>
<p>Classically, inflammation is viewed as an acute response to tissue injury, infection, or another disease state that produces characteristic symptoms (swelling, redness, and warmth). In most cases, this is a functional and useful immune response. However, in some cases, the inflammatory system can be operating at a persistently elevated level, which is known as chronic inflammation.</p>
<p>The medical community has been aware of chronic inflammation for a long time, but only in recent decades has it become possible to track low levels of inflammation using high-sensitivity blood tests. This has shed light on chronic, systemic inflammation as a highly destructive process that drives disease pathogenesis <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> and the aging process itself. It contributes so significantly to the deterioration associated with aging that it has been coined “Inflammaging.” <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>Chronic inflammation contributes to the development of at least 7 of the 10 leading causes of death in the United States. It may go undetected for years or even decades without proactive tracking, silently threatening your health.</p>
<p>C-Reactive Protein, or CRP, is used to measure acute inflammation, but with the advent of hsCRP (high-sensitivity CRP) testing, it became possible to use it for tracking chronic inflammation as well. CRP is one of several proteins rapidly produced by the liver during an inflammatory response. Its primary goal in acute inflammation is to coat damaged cells and bacteria to make them easier to recognize by other immune cells.</p>
<p>Chronically elevated CRP may signal an increased risk for practically all noncommunicable diseases (NCDs<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6008573/">)</a>, <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> including heart disease, cancer, diabetes, stroke, Alzheimer’s disease, chronic kidney disease, osteoporosis, chronic lower respiratory disease, and more &#8211; even if you are asymptomatic. However, conventionally, it is not treated on its own until it occurs in association with another medical condition (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis.)</p>
<p>CRP, in recent years, has also become understood as an active cause of inflammation in addition to simply being a marker of inflammation.</p>
<h2>Chronically elevated CRP: A Direct Link to Decreased Longevity</h2>
<p>CRP is an immune system protein produced by the liver in response to injury, infection, or other inflammatory events. Physicians often look at CRP as one of the major markers of chronic and acute inflammation.</p>
<p>Meta-analyses of all-cause mortality studies find that for longevity, the ideal baseline CRP is essentially as low as possible. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/crp-blog-inflammation-chart.webp" /></p>
<p>This empirical evidence agrees well with aging clocks like the Morgan Levine PhenoAge clock, <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> where baseline CRP is a major component, and with leading Inflammaging <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> research.</p>
<p>Chronic inflammation is a contributing factor <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> to cancer, heart disease, lung disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, chronic kidney disease, Alzheimer’s disease, and irritable bowel syndrome. It is also connected to an array of metabolic disorders, including pre-diabetes and diabetes, obesity (animal studies suggest that high levels of CRP may even directly cause weight gain <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>by interfering with metabolism), and high blood pressure (CRP causes chronic contraction of blood vessels). <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>This is why tracking and optimizing baseline CRP using high-sensitivity CRP (hsCRP) tests is just as important for longevity and healthspan as blood glucose tracking (diabetes prevention), and lipid (ApoA1, ApoB, HDL, LDL) tracking (cardiovascular risk reduction).</p>
<h2>How can I better understand my results?</h2>
<p>The CDC/AHA divides the risk of cardiovascular events into the 3 following categories<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<ul>
<li>Low risk: less than 1.0 mg/L</li>
<li>Average risk: 1.0 to 3.0 mg/L</li>
<li>High risk or acute inflammation: above 3.0 mg/L (consider discussing with your physician</li>
</ul>
<p>It is important to note that research supports targeting baseline CRP levels below 0.5 mg/dL. Commonly, lab tests will report &#8220;&lt;0.2 mg/L&#8221; if you have an ideal/ undetectable value.</p>
<p>For example, a study <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_11');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_11');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_11" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[11]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_11" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> of 27,939 women, showed that hsCRP and cardiovascular risk are proportional, meaning that lower hsCRP was linked to reduced risk—even at the lowest levels measured (&lt;0.5 mg/L).</p>
<h2>hsCRP vs. CRP</h2>
<p>You may have seen CRP and hsCRP in your test results. These both refer to the same inflammation protein. CRP, or C-reactive protein, is also called “standard CRP.” CRP is also used in the diagnosis of severe inflammation related to acute conditions. The standard CPR test measures it in the range of 10 to 1000 mg/L. An hsCRP or “high sensitivity CRP” accurately detects lower levels of the protein and is used to evaluate individuals for low-grade inflammation and risk of heart disease. hsCRP measures CRP in the range from 0.2 to 10 mg/L.</p>
<p><strong>Note: A high CRP value alone cannot be used to diagnose any specific issue. Consult your physician for any interpretation of your CRP test results.</strong></p>
<h2>What are the causes of persistently high baseline CRP?</h2>
<p>Short-term CRP can spike for many reasons including intense exercise, infection, and other factors. Putting those aside, persistently elevated CRP (e.g. above 1mg/L) can have many underlying causes.</p>
<p><strong>Nearly every common chronic disease has an inflammatory component. Even mental health conditions such as anxiety and depression tend to be </strong><strong>associated with elevated CRP</strong><strong>. </strong><span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_12');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_12');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_12" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[12]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_12" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span><strong> As scientists learn more about the brain-body relationship, new connections of this type between blood biomarkers and mental health conditions are being found.</strong></p>
<p>Chronic inflammation can last for months or indefinitely. It can be driven by underlying issues including pathogens (like a fungus or parasite), foreign material (such as a toxic chemical), or autoimmune disorders (like IBD or rheumatoid arthritis). <strong>However, fo</strong><strong>r many modern Americans, </strong><strong>lifestyle factors</strong> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_13');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_13');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_13" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[13]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_13" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span><strong> such as poor diet, nutritional or hormonal imbalance, cigarette, and alcohol use, and disrupted sleep can be the main driver of long-term inflammation.</strong></p>
<h2>Evidence-Based Approaches to Lowering Baseline CRP</h2>
<p>Proactively making an effort to lower CRP levels is both feasible and recommended. Lifestyle has a direct impact on CRP levels. For example, the consumption of trans-fatty acids can <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1943036630">increase CRP levels</span><span class="discussion-id-9cf793ba-8fb7-4821-85c3-19e65a3b5133 discussion-id-69afd8c3-29c6-40d9-8cba-6e59b1aeed34 notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="3" data-reactroot=""> <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_14');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_14');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_14" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[14]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_14" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span> </span>within the 0.9 &#8211; 2.3 mg/L range<span class="discussion-id-9cf793ba-8fb7-4821-85c3-19e65a3b5133 notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="5" data-reactroot="">. Whereas moderate exercise has been shown to be a means </span><span class="discussion-id-9cf793ba-8fb7-4821-85c3-19e65a3b5133 discussion-id-a2466060-97a3-48c8-a507-40faa135a2bd notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="6" data-reactroot="">of </span><span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--1906650134">lowering high CRP</span><span class="discussion-id-9cf793ba-8fb7-4821-85c3-19e65a3b5133 discussion-id-a2466060-97a3-48c8-a507-40faa135a2bd notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="8" data-reactroot="">. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_15');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_15');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_15" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[15]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_15" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span></p>
<p>Below are diet, lifestyle, and supplementation protocols that have strong evidence (references included) for improving elevated baseline CRP levels. Note that where possible we generally only reference Randomly Controlled Studies (RCTs) and Meta-analyses of RCTs.</p>
<p><strong>Note: The information below is provided for reference, please consult your physician before starting any new health regimen.</strong></p>
<h2>Evidence for commonly suggested dietary and lifestyle changes that lower CRP:</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Improved sleep</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Complete and partial sleep deprivation has been shown to increase CRP levels in healthy adults.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_16');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_16');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_16" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[16]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_16" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>SiPhox user data shows a strong -0.46 inverse correlation between the SiPhox sleep score (based on wearable device sleep data) and hsCRP.</li>
<li>Top SiPhox sleep insight:</li>
</ul>
<p>“Consider leaving your smartphone and any other screens outside your bedroom before going to bed. This will help you fall asleep faster and improve your sleep efficiency.”</p>
<ol start="2">
<li><strong>Weight loss (if overweight) and improved diet</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Following a Mediterranean-style diet for a duration of 12 weeks has been shown to decrease CRP levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_17');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_17');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_17" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[17]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_17" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>Weight loss is correlated with lowered CRP levels.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/Untitled_480x480.webp" /></p>
<ol start="3">
<li><strong>Exercise</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Medium-intensity exercise (20 minutes to 1 hour of running) is known to lower your CRP levels<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_18');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_18');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_18" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[18]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_18" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
<li>SiPhox user data shows a significant -0.3 inverse correlation between daily steps taken (based on wearable device activity data) and hsCRP.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4">
<li><strong>Cessation of smoking</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>When levels of CRP were compared in smoking status groups for 1926 men aged 40 to 69 years, it was found that long-term cessation brought CRP levels down to non-smoker levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_19');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_19');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_19" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[19]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_19" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="5">
<li><strong>Removal of processed foods and refined sugars from your diet</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>A low-glycemic index and low glycemic load diet (eating less simple carbohydrates and lower portions of carbs) has been shown to decrease CRP levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_20');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_20');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_20" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[20]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_20" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="6">
<li><strong>Heat Exposure</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Sauna usage [4-7x a week for 10-15 minutes] is associated with decreased hs-CRP levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_21');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_21');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_21" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[21]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_21" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<h2>Evidence for Commonly Used Supplements for Reducing CRP Levels:</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Curcumin</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>(0-3 mg per kilogram of body weight, or roughly 0-1.4 mg per pound.) supplementation is associated with lower CRP levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_22');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_22');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_22" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[22]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_22" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span><span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_23');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_23');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_23" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[23]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_23" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="2">
<li><strong>Zinc</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>A meta-analysis of 35 Randomized Control studies comprising 1995 participants has displayed a decrease in CRP following Zinc supplementation. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_24');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_24');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_24" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[24]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_24" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="3">
<li><strong>Vitamin D</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Increasing sun exposure (15-20 minutes a day) or supplementing with Vitamin D over the counter may increase your Vitamin D levels and increase your Inflammation Score.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_25');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_25');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_25" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[25]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_25" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="4">
<li><strong>Omega 3</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Omega 3 or fatty fish consumption is associated with lower CRP levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_26');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_26');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_26" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[26]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_26" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="5">
<li><strong>Probiotic</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Probiotic supplementation has been shown to decrease CRP levels in a meta-analysis of 31 studies.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_27');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_27');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_27" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[27]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_27" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="6">
<li><strong>Vitamin E (alpha-tocopherol)</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Supplementing vitamin E (15mg/day) can lower inflammation. A meta-analysis of 246 participants suggests that supplementation with vitamin E in the form of either α-tocopherol or γ-tocopherol would reduce serum CRP levels.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_28');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_28');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_28" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[28]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_28" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<ol start="7">
<li><strong>Quercetin</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Supplementing quercetin at doses above 500 mg/day can lower inflammation levels. This meta-analysis showed a significant effect of quercetin supplementation on the C-reactive protein-especially at doses above 500 mg/day and in patients with CRP &lt;3 mg/l.<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_29');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1830_11('footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_29');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_29" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[29]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1830_11_29" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></li>
</ul>
<p>Note: All of the lifestyle, diet and supplementation approaches to lowering chronic inflammation have been shown to work for the <em>average person. </em>To know which ones work for you, tracking your hsCRP on a regular basis is the most effective approach.</p>
<h2>Tracking your hsCRP with SiPhox Health:</h2>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li><strong>$295 one-time or subscribe to get $85 per test*</strong></li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 (4 inflammation markers including hsCRP)</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<h3>Revolutionizing hsCRP tracking:</h3>
<p>SiPhox Health is developing next-generation at-home testing hardware that will deliver biomarker results, including hsCRP, in under 10 minutes using only 5 microliters of blood, similar to a glucometer. This advancement will reduce the cost, time, and difficulty of tracking hsCRP by a factor of ten. Read more <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/siphox-home-device">here</a>.<br />
<a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/siphox-home-device"><br />
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-2502 size-full" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-300x169.webp" alt="SiPhox Home Reader" width="1420" height="798" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-300x169.webp 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-1024x575.webp 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-768x432.webp 768w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-1536x863.webp 1536w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-2048x1151.webp 2048w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/crp-blog-reader-1568x881.webp 1568w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1420px) 100vw, 1420px" /></a></p>
<div class="next-chapter">
    <div class="text-uppercase">
        <h4 class="m-0">
            Start your siphox health journey
        </h4>
    </div>
    <div class="title">
        <h3 class="mt-0">
            Home testing has never been this good
        </h3>
    </div>
    <p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your hsCRP + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>

    <a href='https://l.siphox.health/hscrp'class='btn-cta'>Get started<span class='ms-8px'><img src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/right-arrow-light.svg' /></span></a>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2636" role="img" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg" alt="" width="1182" height="1001" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">*Subscription fee of $24/month, plus $85 per test</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_1830_11();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_1830_11();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_1830_11">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_1830_11" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Pahwa R, Goyal A, Jialal I. Chronic Inflammation. [Updated 2023 Aug 7]. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan-. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK493173/">Chronic Inflammation &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Franceschi, C., Garagnani, P., Parini, P. <i>et al.</i> Inflammaging: a new immune–metabolic viewpoint for age-related diseases. <i>Nat Rev Endocrinol</i> <b>14</b>, 576–590 (2018). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-018-0059-4</span> <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41574-018-0059-4">Inflammaging: a new immune–metabolic viewpoint for age-related diseases</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Luan YY, Yao YM. The Clinical Significance and Potential Role of C-Reactive Protein in Chronic Inflammatory and Neurodegenerative Diseases. Front Immunol. 2018 Jun 7;9:1302. doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2018.01302. PMID: 29951057; PMCID: PMC6008573. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6008573/">The Clinical Significance and Potential Role of C-Reactive Protein in Chronic Inflammatory and Neurodegenerative Diseases &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Li Y, Zhong X, Cheng G, Zhao C, Zhang L, Hong Y, Wan Q, He R, Wang Z. Hs-CRP and all-cause, cardiovascular, and cancer mortality risk: A meta-analysis. Atherosclerosis. 2017 Apr;259:75-82. doi: 10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2017.02.003. Epub 2017 Feb 9. PMID: 28327451. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28327451/">Hs-CRP and all-cause, cardiovascular, and cancer mortality risk: A meta-analysis -PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Levine ME, Lu AT, Quach A, Chen BH, Assimes TL, Bandinelli S, Hou L, Baccarelli AA, Stewart JD, Li Y, Whitsel EA, Wilson JG, Reiner AP, Aviv A, Lohman K, Liu Y, Ferrucci L, Horvath S. An epigenetic biomarker of aging for lifespan and healthspan. Aging (Albany NY). 2018 Apr 18;10(4):573-591. doi: 10.18632/aging.101414. PMID: 29676998; PMCID: PMC5940111. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5940111/">An epigenetic biomarker of aging for lifespan and healthspan &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Franceschi, C., Garagnani, P., Parini, P. <i>et al.</i> Inflammaging: a new immune–metabolic viewpoint for age-related diseases. <i>Nat Rev Endocrinol</i> <b>14</b>, 576–590 (2018). <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41574-018-0059-4</span> <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41574-018-0059-4">Inflammaging: a new immune–metabolic viewpoint for age-related diseases</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Pahwa R, Goyal A, Jialal I. Chronic Inflammation. [Updated 2023 Aug 7]. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan-. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK493173/">Chronic Inflammation &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Li Q, Wang Q, Xu W, Ma Y, Wang Q, Eatman D, You S, Zou J, Champion J, Zhao L, Cui Y, Li W, Deng Y, Ma L, Wu B, Wang G, Zhang X, Wang Q, Bayorh MA and Song Q (2020) C-Reactive Protein Causes Adult-Onset Obesity Through Chronic Inflammatory Mechanism. <i>Front. Cell Dev. Biol.</i> 8:18. doi: 10.3389/fcell.2020.00018 <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fcell.2020.00018/full">C-Reactive Protein Causes Adult-Onset Obesity Through Chronic Inflammatory Mechanism</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Quynh N. Dinh, Grant R. Drummond, Christopher G. Sobey, Sophocles Chrissobolis, &#8220;Roles of Inflammation, Oxidative Stress, and Vascular Dysfunction in Hypertension&#8221;, <i>BioMed Research International</i>, vol. 2014, Article ID 406960, 11 pages, 2014. <span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/406960</span> <a href="https://www.hindawi.com/journals/bmri/2014/406960/">Roles of Inflammation, Oxidative Stress, and Vascular Dysfunction in Hypertension</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Ridker, P.M. (2003) “C-reactive protein,” Circulation, 108(12). Available at: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/01.cir.0000093381.57779.67"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://doi.org/10.1161/01.cir.0000093381.57779.67</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_11" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_11');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >11</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Ridker M, Cook N <a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/01.CIR.0000125690.80303.A8">Clinical Usefulness of Very High and Very Low Levels of C-Reactive Protein Across the Full Range of Framingham Risk Scores</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_12" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_12');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >12</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Jesper Krogh, Michael E. Benros, Martin Balslev Jørgensen, Lone Vesterager, Betina Elfving, Merete Nordentoft, The association between depressive symptoms, cognitive function, and inflammation in major depression, Brain, Behavior, and Immunity, Volume 35, 2014, Pages 70-76 <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0889159113004480">The association between depressive symptoms, cognitive function, and inflammation in major depression</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_13" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_13');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >13</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">O&#8217;Connor MF, Irwin MR. Links between behavioral factors and inflammation. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 2010 Apr;87(4):479-82. doi: 10.1038/clpt.2009.255. Epub 2010 Feb 3. PMID: 20130566; PMCID: PMC2866374. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2866374/">Links between behavioral factors and inflammation &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_14" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_14');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >14</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Lopez-Garcia E, Schulze MB, Meigs JB, Manson JE, Rifai N, Stampfer MJ, Willett WC, Hu FB. Consumption of trans fatty acids is related to plasma biomarkers of inflammation and endothelial dysfunction. J Nutr. 2005 Mar;135(3):562-6. doi: 10.1093/jn/135.3.562. PMID: 15735094. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15735094/">Consumption of trans fatty acids is related to plasma biomarkers of inflammation and endothelial dysfunction &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_15" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_15');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >15</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Zhao H, He Z, Yun H, Wang R, Liu C. A Meta-Analysis of the Effects of Different Exercise Modes on Inflammatory Response in the Elderly. Int J Environ Res Public Health. 2022 Aug 22;19(16):10451. doi: 10.3390/ijerph191610451. PMID: 36012088; PMCID: PMC9407701. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36012088/">A Meta-Analysis of the Effects of Different Exercise Modes on Inflammatory Response in the Elderly &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_16" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_16');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >16</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Meier-Ewert HK;Ridker PM;Rifai N;Regan MM;Price NJ;Dinges DF;Mullington JM; “Effect of Sleep Loss on C-Reactive Protein, an Inflammatory Marker of Cardiovascular Risk.” Journal of the American College of Cardiology, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14975482/."><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/14975482/.</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_17" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_17');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >17</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Basu, Arpita, et al. “Dietary Factors That Promote or Retard Inflammation.” <em>Arteriosclerosis, Thrombosis, and Vascular Biology</em>, 16 Feb. 2006, <a href="https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/01.atv.0000214295.86079.d1"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.ahajournals.org/doi/10.1161/01.atv.0000214295.86079.d1</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_18" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_18');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >18</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">CL;, Fedewa MV;Hathaway ED;Ward-Ritacco. “Effect of Exercise Training on C Reactive Protein: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomised and Non-Randomised Controlled Trials.” <em>British Journal of Sports Medicine</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27445361/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27445361/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_19" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_19');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >19</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Ohsawa M;Okayama A;Nakamura M;Onoda T;Kato K;Itai K;Yoshida Y;Ogawa A;Kawamura K;Hiramori K; “CRP Levels Are Elevated in Smokers but Unrelated to the Number of Cigarettes and Are Decreased by Long-Term Smoking Cessation in Male Smokers.” <em>Preventive Medicine</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15917065/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15917065/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_20" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_20');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >20</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Anette E Buyken, Janina Goletzke, Gesa Joslowski, Anna Felbick, Guo Cheng, Christian Herder, Jennie C Brand-Miller. “Association between Carbohydrate Quality and Inflammatory Markers: Systematic Review of Observational and Interventional Studies.” <em>Oxford Academic</em>, The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition, Volume 99, Issue 4, April 2014, Pages 813–833, <a href="https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/article/99/4/813/4637862"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/article/99/4/813/4637862</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_21" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_21');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >21</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">T;, Laukkanen JA;Laukkanen. “Sauna Bathing and Systemic Inflammation.” <em>European Journal of Epidemiology</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29209938/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29209938/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_22" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_22');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >22</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Gorabi AM;Abbasifard M;Imani D;Aslani S;Razi B;Alizadeh S;Bagheri-Hosseinabadi Z;Sathyapalan T;Sahebkar A; “Effect of Curcumin on C-Reactive Protein as a Biomarker of Systemic Inflammation: An Updated Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.” <em>Phytotherapy Research : PTR</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34586711/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34586711/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_23" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_23');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >23</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Tabrizi R;Vakili S;Akbari M;Mirhosseini N;Lankarani KB;Rahimi M;Mobini M;Jafarnejad S;Vahedpoor Z;Asemi Z; “The Effects of Curcumin-Containing Supplements on Biomarkers of Inflammation and Oxidative Stress: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.” <em>Phytotherapy Research : PTR</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30402990/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30402990/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_24" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_24');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >24</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Jafari A;Noormohammadi Z;Askari M;Daneshzad E; “Zinc Supplementation and Immune Factors in Adults: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Clinical Trials.” <em>Critical Reviews in Food Science and Nutrition</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33356467/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33356467/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_25" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_25');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >25</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Chen N;Wan Z;Han SF;Li BY;Zhang ZL;Qin LQ; “Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on the Level of Circulating High-Sensitivity C-Reactive Protein: A Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.” <em>Nutrients</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24918698/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24918698/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_26" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_26');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >26</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Mortazavi, Akramsadat, et al. “The Effect of Omega-3 Fatty Acids on Serum Apelin Levels in Cardiovascular Disease: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial.” <em>Reports of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology</em>, Varastegan Institute for Medical Sciences, Oct. 2018, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6175591/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6175591/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_27" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_27');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >27</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Milajerdi A;Mousavi SM;Sadeghi A;Salari-Moghaddam A;Parohan M;Larijani B;Esmaillzadeh A; “The Effect of Probiotics on Inflammatory Biomarkers: A Meta-Analysis of Randomized Clinical Trials.” <em>European Journal of Nutrition</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30854594/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30854594/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_28" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_28');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >28</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Saboori S;Shab-Bidar S;Speakman JR;Yousefi Rad E;Djafarian K; “Effect of Vitamin E Supplementation on Serum C-Reactive Protein Level: A Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.” <em>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25669317/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25669317/</span></a>.</td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1830_11_29" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1830_11_29');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >29</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Mohammadi-Sartang M;Mazloom Z;Sherafatmanesh S;Ghorbani M;Firoozi D; “Effects of Supplementation with Quercetin on Plasma C-Reactive Protein Concentrations: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis of Randomized Controlled Trials.” <em>European Journal of Clinical Nutrition</em>, U.S. National Library of Medicine, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28537580/"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28537580/</span></a>.</td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_1830_11() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_1830_11').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_1830_11').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_1830_11() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_1830_11').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_1830_11').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_1830_11() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_1830_11').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_1830_11(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_1830_11(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_1830_11(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_1830_11(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_1830_11(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_1830_11(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
