<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Eva Medved &#8211; SiPhox Health</title>
	<atom:link href="/hub/author/eva-medved/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/hub/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 04:22:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Vitamin D: A Biohacker&#8217;s Guide</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/how-to-optimize-your-vitamin-d-a-biohackers-guide-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eva Medved]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 12:57:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Vitamin D]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1786</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Find out what makes Vitamin D so important to overall health and what you can do to optimize your levels.]]></description>
			



							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>There is a widespread deficiency of Vitamin D globally, influencing various health conditions.</li>
<li>Specific groups, like pregnant women and older adults, require close monitoring of Vitamin D levels.</li>
<li>Vitamin D can be obtained from sunlight, diet, and supplements, each with recommended dosages.</li>
<li>Low levels of Vitamin D are linked to various health issues, including bone diseases and chronic conditions.</li>
</ol>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>There is a widespread deficiency of Vitamin D globally, influencing various health conditions.</li>
<li>Specific groups, like pregnant women and older adults, require close monitoring of Vitamin D levels.</li>
<li>Vitamin D can be obtained from sunlight, diet, and supplements, each with recommended dosages.</li>
<li>Low levels of Vitamin D are linked to various health issues, including bone diseases and chronic conditions.</li>
</ol>

</div><h2>Who can best benefit from Vitamin D level determination?</h2>
<p>Nearly one in two (48%) individuals worldwide have vitamin D deficiency (Vitamin D level less than 20 mg/dL, or less than 50 nmol/L) <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>, and less than one in four (23%) people worldwide have optimal levels of Vitamin D in their blood (between 30 and 100 mg/dL) <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>. Cardiovascular disease, cancer, stroke, diabetes, dementia and osteoporosis are common chronic diseases worldwide that contribute greatly to illness and death in the population. Each of these debilitating diseases is influenced by Vitamin D levels, and low levels of Vitamin D are a risk factor for developing all of these common and chronic diseases. Moreover, common acute respiratory infections are influenced by Vitamin D levels, and may be prevented by Vitamin D supplementation to adequate levels. Thus, anyone who is interested in improving their general health and avoiding common diseases should monitor their blood levels of Vitamin D.</p>
<p>Pregnant women should pay particular interest to Vitamin D blood levels, since pregnancy health and the health of the newborn are affected by Vitamin D.</p>
<p>Others that are particularly at risk for low Vitamin D levels and should be tested include individuals who:</p>
<ul>
<li>are over age 65</li>
<li>are obese</li>
<li>just had bariatric surgery (weight loss surgery)</li>
<li>have limited exposure to the sun</li>
<li>wear long clothing outdoors</li>
<li>have dark skin</li>
<li>have osteoporosis or thin bones</li>
<li>are taking medicines that may lower Vitamin D levels (see list of drugs under “Prescription Medicines” below)</li>
<li>have problems with intestinal absorption of vitamins because of an underlying condition such as colitis or celiac disease.</li>
</ul>
<h2>When is the best time to measure Vitamin D levels?</h2>
<p>You can measure your Vitamin D levels at any time you wish, since the blood levels of Vitamin D tend to be stable over the course of any 24-hour period.</p>
<h2>How can I better understand my Vitamin D level results?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Optimal: 30 to 100 ng/dL.</li>
<li>Suboptimal: 21 to 29 ng/dL.</li>
<li>Deficient: Equal to or less than 20 ng/dL.</li>
<li>Too high: Greater than 100 ng/dL.</li>
</ul>
<p>Deficient levels of Vitamin D can lead to elevated levels of parathyroid hormone (a hormone that regulates bone and calcium metabolism), a condition known as secondary hyperparathyroidism. Secondary hyperparathyroidism can cause bone disease, and it can also cause calcium to build up in tissues and organs such as the heart and blood vessels.</p>
<h2>How can I raise my Vitamin D levels?</h2>
<h3>Dietary and other lifestyle modifications</h3>
<ul>
<li>Exposure to daily sunlight for a sufficient length of time (30 minutes per day) is important during the winter time to maintain Vitamin D3 levels, especially for individuals with darker skin tone. Although sunscreen blocks most of the UVB rays that are required for Vitamin D production, it is recommended to wear sunscreen when outdoors for long periods of time (greater than 30 minutes) to prevent skin cancer. Extended outdoor exposure to the sun with sunscreen may allow enough UVB penetration for sufficient production of Vitamin D <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>.</li>
<li>Vitamin D3 can also be obtained from dietary consumption of various types of fatty fish, including salmon, sardines, tuna, herring, or mackerel, chicken breast, egg yolks, beef liver or fish liver, or food that is artificially supplemented with Vitamin D3, such as milk, almond or soy milk, tofu, cereal, or orange juice.</li>
<li>Vitamin D2 can be obtained from the diet by consumption of certain plant fluids, such as mushrooms.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Supplement additions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin D3 supplementation is an easy and efficient method to restore Vitamin D levels to healthy levels.</li>
<li>The recommended amount of Vitamin D3 supplementation depends on the age, health status, and medical history of the person taking the supplement:
<ul>
<li>For infants and toddlers less than 1 year of age, the recommended dose is 2000 International Units (IU) of Vitamin D3 per day for six weeks until target blood levels are reached, followed by 400 to 1000 IU per day once blood levels are in range.</li>
<li>For children between 1 and 18 years of age, the recommended dose is 2000 IU of Vitamin D3 per day for six weeks until target blood levels are reached, followed by 600 to 1000 IU per day for maintenance.</li>
<li>For adults, the recommended dose is 6000 IU of Vitamin D3 per day for eight weeks until target blood levels are reached, followed by 1500 to 2000 IU per day once blood levels are in range.</li>
<li>For obese individuals, people with malabsorption diseases, and people taking certain medications, the recommended dose is 6,000 to 10,000 IU/day, until target blood levels are reached, followed by a maintenance dose of 3,000 to 6,000 IU/day to maintain blood levels in the desired range.</li>
<li>Vitamin D supplementation may interact with other medications, and individuals taking these other medications should talk to their doctor before taking any Vitamin D supplement: aluminum-containing phosphate binders for kidney disease, atorvastatin (Lipitor) for elevated cholesterol, calcipotriene (Dovonex, Sorilux) for psoriasis, cytochrome P-450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates, or digoxin (Lanoxin) for heart disease.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Common natural supplements that many people take may decrease Vitamin D levels as a side effect, including St. John’s wort and kava kava. Individuals taking these supplements may require higher levels of Vitamin D supplementation.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Exercise</h3>
<ul>
<li>A recent report that analyzes many other studies concludes that for older adults, combining Vitamin D supplementation with resistance exercise training leads to an additive improvement in musculoskeletal strength, suggesting that exercise and sufficient Vitamin D blood levels are both important for physical strength <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Smoking</h3>
<ul>
<li>Smoking has been associated with lower Vitamin D levels, and expectant mothers who smoke have an increased risk of Vitamin D lowering during low-sun exposure months in northern regions <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>, suggesting a link between smoking, low Vitamin D levels, and poor maternal health.</li>
<li>Passive smoking is also associated with lower Vitamin D level in children <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>, suggesting that those who spend time with smokers should carefully monitor their Vitamin D levels.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Alcohol</h3>
<ul>
<li>There is little evidence that alcohol intake levels substantially affect Vitamin D levels <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>, suggesting that modifying alcohol intake will not dramatically alter Vitamin D levels in the long term.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Prescription Medicines</h2>
<p>Drugs that lower Vitamin D levels include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anti-seizure medications, including phenytoin, phenobarbital and carbamazepine.</li>
<li>Certain blood pressure medicines, such as nifedipine and spironolactone.</li>
<li>Cancer treatments and chemotherapies, such as taxol.</li>
<li>Estrogen-blocking drugs for breast cancer, including tamoxifen and fulvestrant.</li>
<li>Drugs for various infections, such as rifampin or isoniazid for tuberculosis, ritonavir for HIV, and clotrimazole for fungal infections.</li>
<li>Various steroidal medications, including prednisone, dexamethasone, and methylprednisolone.</li>
<li>Drugs that interfere with intestinal absorption of vitamins, including Orlistat (Xenical, Alli) or stimulant laxatives.</li>
</ul>
<p>Individuals taking any of the above medications may require higher Vitamin D3 supplement doses to restore blood levels to an optimal value.</p>
<h2>Where can I learn more?</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://hubermanlab.com/dr-rhonda-patrick-micronutrients-for-health-and-longevity/"><strong>Dr. Andrew Huberman’s interview with Dr. Rhonda Patrick covers relevant topics around Vitamin D</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/vitamin-d-whats-right-level-2016121910893"><strong>A good commentary on Vitamin D topics from a Harvard physician</strong></a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/vitamins-and-minerals/vitamin-d/">**Read the National Health Service (UK) Vitamin D Review</a>**</li>
</ul>
<h2>Health and medical importance of Vitamin D levels</h2>
<p>Vitamin D is important to help the body absorb phosphorus and calcium into the bloodstream, and these elements are essential for bone growth. Thus, Vitamin D is important for bone metabolism, and low Vitamin D levels can lead to bone diseases including osteoporosis <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. Osteoporosis is a disease that causes bones to be weak or brittle, and can lead to bone fractures, falls and injury. Osteoporosis is very common in most countries, particularly among post menopausal women, with a worldwide prevalence of 1 in 5 <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. Patients with osteoporosis frequently have mildly lower levels of Vitamin D.</p>
<p>Recent evidence suggests that Vitamin D is important for many other body functions, and that Vitamin D has substantial effects on many different organs in the body. For example, individuals with low circulating levels of Vitamin D are more prone to suffer from acute respiratory infections. Furthermore, it has been shown from many studies that increasing blood levels of Vitamin D to suitable levels can diminish the risk for these acute respiratory infections <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. Moreover, low Vitamin D blood levels are associated with worsening of asthma, and supplementation with Vitamin D to restore suitable blood levels prevents these complications of asthma as well <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_11');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_11');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_11" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[11]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_11" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>.</p>
<p>In addition, low Vitamin D blood levels have been associated with other serious diseases, including multiple types of cancer such as colon, breast, and prostate cancer <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_12');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_12');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_12" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[12]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_12" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. Supplementation with Vitamin D to achieve sufficient blood levels has been shown to decrease the overall death from cancer, according to a recent analysis, although Vitamin D supplementation does not decrease the incidence (occurrence) of cancer <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_13');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_13');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_13" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[13]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_13" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>. Importantly, low levels of Vitamin D have been associated with the development of cognitive impairment (brain decline) and Alzheimer’s disease <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_14');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_14');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_14" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[14]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_14" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>, and there is recent evidence that supplementation with Vitamin D may prevent cognitive decline in healthy Black adults <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_15');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_15');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_15" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[15]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_15" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>.</span></p>
<p>Low Vitamin D levels are also correlated with the development of Type II, or adult onset diabetes <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_16');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_16');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_16" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[16]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_16" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>. Whether supplementation of Vitamin D can reverse Type II diabetes is controversial, but there is evidence that supplementation with high levels of Vitamin D for short periods of time can be used to effectively treat some aspects of this disease for some groups of patients <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_17');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_17');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_17" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[17]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_17" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>.</p>
<p>Moreover, low levels of Vitamin D are associated with inflammatory bowel disease, including Chron’s disease and ulcerative colitis, and supplementation with Vitamin D has been show to reduce the incidence of these d<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_18');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_18');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_18" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[18]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_18" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span> In addition, a recent review concludes that supplementation with Vitamin D to achieve desired blood levels is associated with reduction of symptoms of several other diseases, including relief from major depression, pain from fibromyalgia (a disorder characterized by widespread body pain and fatigue), and the symptoms of atopic dermatitis (a condition characterized by itchy, dry, and inflamed skin) <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_19');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_19');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_19" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[19]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_19" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>.</p>
<p>Pregnant women who are deficient in Vitamin D have an increased risk for medical complications during their pregnancy, including preeclampsia (high blood pressure during pregnancy) and the need for cesarean section <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_20');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_20');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_20" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[20]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_20" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. In addition, the children born from mothers with low Vitamin D levels may suffer from asthma or dental cavities.</p>
<p>However, blood levels of Vitamin D that are too high can cause health problems as well, including too much calcium in the blood (hypercalcemia) and kidney damage. These changes can lead to nausea, vomiting, and muscle weakness <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_21');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_21');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_21" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[21]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_21" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span>. Thus, it is important to regularly monitor one’s Vitamin D blood levels to make sure that they are neither too high nor too low.</p>
<h2>What forms of Vitamin D should be measured for health monitoring?</h2>
<p>There are several different forms of Vitamin D in the human body, including Vitamin D3 and Vitamin D2 <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_22');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_22');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_22" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[22]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_22" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. Almost all (about 90%) of Vitamin D3 in the body is obtained from sunlight ultraviolet B (UVB) rays on the skin, which converts 7-dehydrocholesterol (a normal molecule in the skin) to Vitamin D3 <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_23');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_1786_1('footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_23');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_23" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[23]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_1786_1_23" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></span>. A small amount (about 10%) of Vitamin D3 in the body is obtained from dietary consumption of fish or eggs, or food that is artificially supplemented with Vitamin D3, or supplements that contain Vitamin D3. Vitamin D2 is a different form of Vitamin D that can obtained from the diet by consumption of certain plant fluids, such as mushrooms, or supplements than contain Vitamin D2.</p>
<p>Once Vitamin D3 or D2 is in the bloodstream, the liver converts Vitamin D3 or D2 to a different form of the vitamin, called 25-hydroxyvitamin D3 or D2 (we will refer to either of these Vitamin D forms here as “25OH Vitamin D”). 25OH Vitamin D lasts for a long time in the blood stream, with a half-life of two to three weeks, meaning that after two to three weeks, the amount of 25OH Vitamin D in the blood is one-half of the original value, assuming no new sources for accumulation. For this reason, 25OH Vitamin D is the best measure of total storage levels of Vitamin D in the body. Thus, 25OH Vitamin D is the preferred form of Vitamin D for doctors and medical scientists to measure for human health and disease, since blood levels of 25OH Vitamin D correlate best with the health-related effects of this vitamin. Hence, the 25OH Vitamin D blood level is measured by SiPhox as a marker for Vitamin D status.</p>
<p>25OH Vitamin D is further converted by the kidney and other tissues to a different form of Vitamin D, called 1,25 (OH)2 Vitamin D, which is the biologically active form of Vitamin D. However, since 1,25 (OH)2 Vitamin D is rapidly converted to other forms of the Vitamin (i.e. rapidly metabolized), 1,25 (OH)2 Vitamin D does not accurately reflect body storage levels of Vitamin D. Therefore, blood levels of 1,25 (OH)2 Vitamin D do not correlate well with the health-related effects of this vitamin, and SiPhox does not measure 1,25 (OH)2 Vitamin D.</p>
<h3>Tracking your Vitamin D with SiPhox Health:</h3>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li><strong>$295 one-time or subscribe to get $85 per test*</strong></li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 (4 inflammation markers including Vitamin D)</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<div class="next-chapter">
    <div class="text-uppercase">
        <h4 class="m-0">
            Start your siphox health journey
        </h4>
    </div>
    <div class="title">
        <h3 class="mt-0">
            Home health testing has never been this good
        </h3>
    </div>
    <p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your Vitamin D + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>

    <a href='https://l.siphox.health/vitaminD'class='btn-cta'>Get started<span class='ms-8px'><img src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/right-arrow-light.svg' /></span></a>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2636" role="img" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg" alt="" width="1182" height="1001" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_1786_1();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_1786_1();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_1786_1">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_1786_1" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Cui A, Zhang T, Xiao P, Fan Z, Wang H, Zhuang Y. Global and regional prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in population-based studies from 2000 to 2022: A pooled analysis of 7.9 million participants. Front Nutr. 2023 Mar 17;10:1070808. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2023.1070808. PMID: 37006940; PMCID: PMC10064807. <a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37006940/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1"><span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--188510839">Global and regional prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in population-based studies from 2000 to 2022: A pooled analysis of 7.9 million participants &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Cui A, Zhang T, Xiao P, Fan Z, Wang H, Zhuang Y. Global and regional prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in population-based studies from 2000 to 2022: A pooled analysis of 7.9 million participants. Front Nutr. 2023 Mar 17;10:1070808. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2023.1070808. PMID: 37006940; PMCID: PMC10064807. <a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/37006940/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1"><span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--188510839">Global and regional prevalence of vitamin D deficiency in population-based studies from 2000 to 2022: A pooled analysis of 7.9 million participants &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</span></a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Neale RE, Khan SR, Lucas RM, Waterhouse M, Whiteman DC, Olsen CM. The effect of sunscreen on vitamin D: a review. Br J Dermatol. 2019 Nov;181(5):907-915. doi: 10.1111/bjd.17980. Epub 2019 Jul 9. PMID: 30945275. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-7704825"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30945275/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">The effect of sunscreen on vitamin D: a review &#8211; PubMed </a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Antoniak AE, Greig CA. The effect of combined resistance exercise training and vitamin D3 supplementation on musculoskeletal health and function in older adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ Open. 2017 Jul 20;7(7):e014619. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2016-014619. PMID: 28729308; PMCID: PMC5541589. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1044191657"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28729308/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">The effect of combined resistance exercise training and vitamin D3 supplementation on musculoskeletal health and function in older adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Lokki AI, Heikkinen-Eloranta J, Öhman H, Heinonen S, Surcel HM, Nielsen HS. Smoking during pregnancy reduces vitamin D levels in a Finnish birth register cohort. Public Health Nutr. 2020 May;23(7):1273-1277. doi: 10.1017/S1368980018003932. Epub 2019 Feb 8. PMID: 30732669; PMCID: PMC10200425. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--1798583924"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30732669/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Smoking during pregnancy reduces vitamin D levels in a Finnish birth register cohort &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Yang L, Sato M, Saito-Abe M, Miyaji Y, Sato C, Nishizato M, Kumasaka N, Mezawa H, Yamamoto-Hanada K, Ohya Y. Smoking Exposure Is Associated with Serum Vitamin D Deficiency in Children: Evidence from the Japan Environment and Children&#8217;s Study. Nutrients. 2022 Jul 29;14(15):3121. doi: 10.3390/nu14153121. PMID: 35956297; PMCID: PMC9370804. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--589359344"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9370804/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Smoking Exposure Is Associated with Serum Vitamin D Deficiency in Children: Evidence from the Japan Environment and Children’s Study &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Janssen HC, Emmelot-Vonk MH, Verhaar HJ, van der Schouw YT. Determinants of vitamin D status in healthy men and women aged 40-80 years. Maturitas. 2013 Jan;74(1):79-83. doi: 10.1016/j.maturitas.2012.10.008. Epub 2012 Nov 28. PMID: 23200514. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-712013893"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23200514/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Determinants of vitamin D status in healthy men and women aged 40-80 years &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Holick MF. The vitamin D deficiency pandemic: Approaches for diagnosis, treatment and prevention. Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2017 Jun;18(2):153-165. doi: 10.1007/s11154-017-9424-1. PMID: 28516265. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--762239537"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28516265/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">The vitamin D deficiency pandemic: Approaches for diagnosis, treatment and prevention &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Xiao PL, Cui AY, Hsu CJ, Peng R, Jiang N, Xu XH, Ma YG, Liu D, Lu HD. Global, regional prevalence, and risk factors of osteoporosis according to the World Health Organization diagnostic criteria: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Osteoporos Int. 2022 Oct;33(10):2137-2153. doi: 10.1007/s00198-022-06454-3. Epub 2022 Jun 10. PMID: 35687123. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1880607149"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/35687123/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Global, regional prevalence, and risk factors of osteoporosis according to the World Health Organization diagnostic criteria: a systematic review and meta-analysis &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Martineau AR, Jolliffe DA, Greenberg L, Aloia JF, Bergman P, Dubnov-Raz G, Esposito S, Ganmaa D, Ginde AA, Goodall EC, Grant CC, Janssens W, Jensen ME, Kerley CP, Laaksi I, Manaseki-Holland S, Mauger D, Murdoch DR, Neale R, Rees JR, Simpson S, Stelmach I, Trilok Kumar G, Urashima M, Camargo CA, Griffiths CJ, Hooper RL. Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory infections: individual participant data meta-analysis. Health Technol Assess. 2019 Jan;23(2):1-44. doi: 10.3310/hta23020. PMID: 30675873; PMCID: PMC6369419. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1726227215"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30675873/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory infections: individual participant data meta-analysis &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_11" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_11');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >11</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Martineau AR, Jolliffe DA, Greenberg L, Aloia JF, Bergman P, Dubnov-Raz G, Esposito S, Ganmaa D, Ginde AA, Goodall EC, Grant CC, Janssens W, Jensen ME, Kerley CP, Laaksi I, Manaseki-Holland S, Mauger D, Murdoch DR, Neale R, Rees JR, Simpson S, Stelmach I, Trilok Kumar G, Urashima M, Camargo CA, Griffiths CJ, Hooper RL. Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory infections: individual participant data meta-analysis. Health Technol Assess. 2019 Jan;23(2):1-44. doi: 10.3310/hta23020. PMID: 30675873; PMCID: PMC6369419. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1726227215"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30675873/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Vitamin D supplementation to prevent acute respiratory infections: individual participant data meta-analysis &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_12" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_12');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >12</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Meeker S, Seamons A, Maggio-Price L, Paik J. Protective links between vitamin D, inflammatory bowel disease and colon cancer. World J Gastroenterol. 2016 Jan 21;22(3):933-48. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v22.i3.933. PMID: 26811638; PMCID: PMC4716046. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--1589850395"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26811638/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Protective links between vitamin D, inflammatory bowel disease and colon cancer &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_13" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_13');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >13</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Keum N, Lee DH, Greenwood DC, Manson JE, Giovannucci E. Vitamin D supplementation and total cancer incidence and mortality: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Ann Oncol. 2019 May 1;30(5):733-743. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdz059. PMID: 30796437; PMCID: PMC6821324. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30796437/">Vitamin D supplementation and total cancer incidence and mortality: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_14" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_14');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >14</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Soni M, Kos K, Lang IA, Jones K, Melzer D, Llewellyn DJ. Vitamin D and cognitive function. Scand J Clin Lab Invest Suppl. 2012;243:79-82. doi: 10.3109/00365513.2012.681969. PMID: 22536767. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1723207660"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22536767/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Vitamin D and cognitive function &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_15" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_15');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >15</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Kang JH, Vyas CM, Okereke OI, Ogata S, Albert M, Lee IM, D&#8217;Agostino D, Buring JE, Cook NR, Grodstein F, Manson JE. Effect of vitamin D on cognitive decline: results from two ancillary studies of the VITAL randomized trial. Sci Rep. 2021 Dec 1;11(1):23253. doi: 10.1038/s41598-021-02485-8. PMID: 34853363; PMCID: PMC8636504. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1823286065"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34853363/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Effect of vitamin D on cognitive decline: results from two ancillary studies of the VITAL randomized trial &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_16" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_16');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >16</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Li X, Liu Y, Zheng Y, Wang P, Zhang Y. The Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on Glycemic Control in Type 2 Diabetes Patients: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Nutrients. 2018 Mar 19;10(3):375. doi: 10.3390/nu10030375. PMID: 29562681; PMCID: PMC5872793. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5872793/">The Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on Glycemic Control in Type 2 Diabetes Patients: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_17" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_17');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >17</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Li X, Liu Y, Zheng Y, Wang P, Zhang Y. The Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on Glycemic Control in Type 2 Diabetes Patients: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Nutrients. 2018 Mar 19;10(3):375. doi: 10.3390/nu10030375. PMID: 29562681; PMCID: PMC5872793. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5872793/">The Effect of Vitamin D Supplementation on Glycemic Control in Type 2 Diabetes Patients: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_18" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_18');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >18</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Holick MF. The vitamin D deficiency pandemic: Approaches for diagnosis, treatment and prevention. Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2017 Jun;18(2):153-165. doi: 10.1007/s11154-017-9424-1. PMID: 28516265. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--762239537"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28516265/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">The vitamin D deficiency pandemic: Approaches for diagnosis, treatment and prevention &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_19" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_19');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >19</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Michael W, Couture AD, Swedlund M, Hampton A, Eglash A, Schrager S. An Evidence-Based Review of Vitamin D for Common and High-Mortality Conditions. J Am Board Fam Med. 2022 Dec 23;35(6):1217-1229. doi: 10.3122/jabfm.2022.220115R1. Epub 2022 Nov 17. PMID: 36396409. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-988699708"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36396409/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">An Evidence-Based Review of Vitamin D for Common and High-Mortality Conditions &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_20" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_20');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >20</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Holick MF. The vitamin D deficiency pandemic: Approaches for diagnosis, treatment and prevention. Rev Endocr Metab Disord. 2017 Jun;18(2):153-165. doi: 10.1007/s11154-017-9424-1. PMID: 28516265. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--762239537"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28516265/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">The vitamin D deficiency pandemic: Approaches for diagnosis, treatment and prevention &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_21" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_21');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >21</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">e Vincentis S, Russo A, Milazzo M, Lonardo A, De Santis MC, Rochira V, Simoni M, Madeo B. How Much Vitamin D is Too Much? A Case Report and Review of the Literature. Endocr Metab Immune Disord Drug Targets. 2021;21(9):1653-1659. doi: 10.2174/1871530320666201007152230. PMID: 33030138; PMCID: PMC8811610. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33030138/">How Much Vitamin D is Too Much? A Case Report and Review of the Literature -PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_22" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_22');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >22</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Altieri B, Cavalier E, Bhattoa HP, Pérez-López FR, López-Baena MT, Pérez-Roncero GR, Chedraui P, Annweiler C, Della Casa S, Zelzer S, Herrmann M, Faggiano A, Colao A, Holick MF. Vitamin D testing: advantages and limits of the current assays. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2020 Feb;74(2):231-247. doi: 10.1038/s41430-019-0553-3. Epub 2020 Jan 6. PMID: 31907366. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-1637874459"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31907366/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Vitamin D testing: advantages and limits of the current assays &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_1786_1_23" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_1786_1_23');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >23</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Heureux N. Vitamin D Testing-Where Are We and What Is on the Horizon? Adv Clin Chem. 2017;78:59-101. doi: 10.1016/bs.acc.2016.07.002. Epub 2016 Aug 24. PMID: 28057189. <span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--789378266"><a class="notion-link-token notion-focusable-token notion-enable-hover" tabindex="0" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28057189/" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-token-index="1">Vitamin D Testing-Where Are We and What Is on the Horizon? &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_1786_1() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_1786_1').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_1786_1').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_1786_1() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_1786_1').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_1786_1').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_1786_1() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_1786_1').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_1786_1(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_1786_1(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_1786_1(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_1786_1(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_1786_1(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_1786_1(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cholesterol: A Key Measure of Cardiovascular and Metabolic Health</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/how-to-optimize-your-cholesterol-a-biohackers-guide/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eva Medved]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 10:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cholesterol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1720</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Delve into expert opinions on the ideal cholesterol ranges, dietary choices, lifestyle changes, and the role of supplements and exercise in achieving and maintaining optimal cholesterol levels.]]></description>
			



							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h3>Key Takeaways:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Cholesterol is essential for cell building, hormone synthesis, and vitamin production, and is produced by the liver and obtained from diet.</li>
<li>HDL cholesterol is protective against heart disease, while high levels of LDL cholesterol and triglycerides increase heart disease risk.</li>
<li>Regular testing of cholesterol levels is crucial as high cholesterol increases the risk of heart disease and strokes.</li>
<li>Optimal cholesterol management includes diet changes, exercise, and possibly supplements.</li>
</ol>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h3>Key Takeaways:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Cholesterol is essential for cell building, hormone synthesis, and vitamin production, and is produced by the liver and obtained from diet.</li>
<li>HDL cholesterol is protective against heart disease, while high levels of LDL cholesterol and triglycerides increase heart disease risk.</li>
<li>Regular testing of cholesterol levels is crucial as high cholesterol increases the risk of heart disease and strokes.</li>
<li>Optimal cholesterol management includes diet changes, exercise, and possibly supplements.</li>
</ol>

</div><h2>What is Cholesterol?</h2>
<p>Cholesterol is a waxy, fat-like substance that the body uses to build cells, make hormones, and synthesize vitamins. The liver produces the cholesterol required by the body, and it can also be obtained through diet, mainly from animal products. Cholesterol travels through the bloodstream, attached to proteins. These cholesterol-protein units are called lipoproteins.</p>
<h2>Understanding HDL, LDL, and Triglycerides</h2>
<p>Common cholesterol panels measure three types of lipids in your blood: high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, and triglycerides. Here&#8217;s what each of these lipids does:</p>
<ul>
<li>HDL cholesterol: HDL is often referred to as the &#8220;good cholesterol&#8221; because it helps remove LDL cholesterol from the bloodstream and protects against cardiovascular diseases. Higher levels of HDL cholesterol are associated with a lower risk of heart disease.</li>
<li>LDL cholesterol: LDL is commonly referred to as the &#8220;bad cholesterol&#8221; because it contributes to the buildup of fatty deposits or plaques in the arteries. High levels of LDL cholesterol increase the risk of heart attacks, strokes, and heart disease.</li>
<li>Triglycerides: Triglycerides are a type of fat found in the blood. They are used by the body for energy, but high levels can contribute to the hardening and narrowing of arteries, increasing the risk of heart disease.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Why measure Cholesterol levels</h2>
<p>Measuring cholesterol levels is essential because high cholesterol can lead to the buildup of fatty deposits or plaques in the arteries. This increases the risk of age-related conditions such as heart attacks, strokes, and heart disease. Regular cholesterol testing helps assess heart health, estimate the risk of cardiovascular disease, and monitor the impact of lifestyle changes on cholesterol levels.</p>
<h2>What are the risks of high/low Cholesterol? A link to longevity</h2>
<p>High cholesterol, specifically high levels of LDL cholesterol, increases the risk of heart attacks, strokes, and heart disease. On the other hand, high levels of HDL cholesterol protect against cardiovascular diseases.<br />
Low levels of HDL cholesterol may increase the risk of heart disease and premature death. Extremely low levels of LDL cholesterol and triglycerides are not associated with any health risks but may indicate an underlying medical condition.</p>
<p>Several studies have shown that maintaining optimal cholesterol levels can contribute to a longer and healthier life, while high cholesterol levels can lead to a higher risk of cardiovascular diseases and reduced life expectancy.</p>
<h2>Interpretation of Cholesterol test results and optimal ranges</h2>
<p>Cholesterol test results provide insights into an individual&#8217;s risk of heart attack, stroke, and cardiovascular disease. The optimal ranges for cholesterol and triglycerides are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Total cholesterol: 125-200 mg/dL</li>
<li>LDL cholesterol: &lt;130 mg/dL</li>
<li>HDL cholesterol: &gt;45 mg/dL for men; &gt;55 mg/dL for women</li>
<li>Triglycerides: &lt;150 mg/dL</li>
</ul>
<h2>Reaching and maintaining optimal cholesterol levels could potentially add decades to one&#8217;s life.</h2>
<h3>Diet</h3>
<p>Eating Heart-Healthy Foods plays a significant role in managing cholesterol levels.</p>
<ul>
<li>Reduce Saturated and Trans Fats: Saturated fats found in red meat and dairy products increase total cholesterol. Worse still, trans fats — often labeled as &#8220;partially hydrogenated oils&#8221; in store-bought cookies, crackers, and cakes — can raise your LDL (&#8220;bad&#8221;) cholesterol levels.</li>
<li>Increase Soluble Fiber: Foods rich in soluble fiber can lower your LDL cholesterol. Good sources include oatmeal, kidney beans, brussels sprouts, apples, and pears.</li>
<li>Add Omega-3 Fatty Acids: Foods rich in omega-3 fatty acids can boost HDL (&#8220;good&#8221;) cholesterol and reduce your risk of heart disease. Salmon, albacore tuna, mackerel, and sardines are high in omega-3 fatty acids. Flaxseeds and walnuts also offer these beneficial fats.</li>
<li>Reduce Sugar Consumption: The consumption of sugar (sucrose, high fructose corn syrup) increases plasma levels of triglycerides, LDL and apoB, and reduces plasma levels of HDL-C and apoA. The removal of sugar reverses each of these.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Behavioral Change</h3>
<ul>
<li>Quit Smoking: Quitting smoking improves your HDL cholesterol levels. Moreover, the benefits happen quickly: Within 20 minutes of quitting, your blood pressure and heart rate decrease.</li>
<li>Reduce Alcohol Intake: While moderate alcohol use has been linked with higher levels of HDL cholesterol, the benefits aren&#8217;t strong enough to recommend alcohol for anyone who doesn&#8217;t drink already. Too much alcohol can lead to serious health problems, including high blood pressure, heart failure, and strokes.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Dietary Supplements</h3>
<p>Supplements may play a role in helping you to optimize cholesterol, however, make sure to discuss this with your healthcare provider before starting any new supplement regimen.</p>
<ul>
<li>Plant sterols and stanols.</li>
<li>soluble fiber (psyllium).</li>
<li>omega-3 fatty acids.</li>
<li>coenzyme Q10.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Exercise</h3>
<p>Moderate and High-Intensity Cardio has been shown to be the most effective form of exercise to improve HDL function and overall lipid profile.</p>
<h3>Consistent Testing</h3>
<ul>
<li>Identification of Baseline Levels: The first step in managing cholesterol is to know your starting point. This initial test, such as the SiPhox Health Panel, provides the baseline for future tests, allowing you and your doctor to track changes over time.</li>
<li>Early Detection of Potential Issues: Regular blood testing can catch elevated cholesterol levels before they lead to health issues such as atherosclerosis (hardening of the arteries) or heart disease. By identifying these changes early, you can take proactive measures to lower your cholesterol and reduce your risk.</li>
<li>Monitoring the Effectiveness of Interventions: If you&#8217;re making lifestyle changes or taking medication to manage cholesterol, regular blood testing can show whether these strategies are working. If your cholesterol levels aren&#8217;t improving, or if they&#8217;re getting worse, you may need to adjust your strategies.</li>
</ul>
<h2>What do the experts say?</h2>
<p>Dr. Robert H. Eckel- former President of the American Heart Association</p>
<ul>
<li>&#8220;LDL cholesterol is a significant risk factor for cardiovascular disease. The optimal LDL cholesterol level is less than 100 mg/dL for most people. However, for those at higher risk, such as those with a history of heart disease or diabetes, an LDL level of less than 70 mg/dL is often recommended&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Dr. Patrick Moriarty- Director of the Atherosclerosis and LDL-Apheresis Center at the University of Kansas Medical Center</p>
<ul>
<li>&#8220;While focusing on lowering LDL cholesterol, we shouldn&#8217;t neglect HDL, or &#8216;good&#8217; cholesterol. For men, an HDL level of 40 mg/dL or higher is protective against heart disease, while for women, it should be 50 mg/dL or higher&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>Dr. Peter Attia- Founder, <em>Early Medical</em></p>
<ul>
<li>&#8220;If you want to stop atherosclerosis, you <strong>must lower the LDL particle number</strong>.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Tracking your Cholesterol with SiPhox Health:</h3>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li><strong>$295 one-time or subscribe to get $85 per test*</strong></li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 (6 cardiovascular markers including LDL, HDL, ApoA, ApoB, triglycerides, etc.)</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<div class="next-chapter">
    <div class="text-uppercase">
        <h4 class="m-0">
            Start your SiPhox Health journey
        </h4>
    </div>
    <div class="title">
        <h3 class="mt-0">
            Home health testing has never been this good
        </h3>
    </div>
    <p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your LDL + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>

    <a href='https://l.siphox.health/cholesterol'class='btn-cta'>Get started<span class='ms-8px'><img src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/right-arrow-light.svg' /></span></a>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2636" role="img" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg" alt="" width="1182" height="1001" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Life-Saving Ferritin Discovery</title>
		<link>/hub/blog/a-life-saving-ferritin-discovery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eva Medved]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 20:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[User]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1610</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this user case study, we explore how our simple test played a pivotal role in a customer's life-saving discovery, illustrating the power of comprehensive blood testing in empowering individuals to take charge of their health.]]></description>
			
							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Understanding the importance of proactive healthcare, SiPhox Health has revolutionized the field of at-home blood testing by enabling customers in the United States and Canada to access low-cost testing for 17 essential biomarkers. In this user case study, we explore how our simple test played a pivotal role in a customer&#8217;s life-saving discovery, illustrating the power of comprehensive blood testing in empowering individuals to take charge of their health.</p>
<h2>The Problem: A Reactive Healthcare System</h2>
<p>Traditionally, annual visits to the doctor&#8217;s office involve a limited set of blood tests, reflecting a medical system that prioritized reactive rather than proactive care. Patients in the United States and Canada often found it challenging to obtain relevant and comprehensive blood panels, leading to potential health issues going unnoticed until they manifested in more severe symptoms. Without frequent testing, patients are left clueless to their health for 364 days a year. Annual doctor&#8217;s visits leave a gap in detection, making the prospect of early detection difficult. Moreover, the costs associated with comprehensive testing act as a barrier for many individuals. <a href="https://www.talktomira.com/post/the-cost-of-a-doctor-visit-without-insurance">According to Mirah Health</a>, the average doctors visit without insurance can range between $300 and $600, while the cost of bloodwork alone is $432.</p>
<h2>The Solution: SiPhox Health&#8217;s Proactive Approach</h2>
<p>SiPhox Health has addressed these challenges by offering a cost-effective mail-in blood testing service, enabling patients to take a proactive approach to their health and well-being. Our low-cost panel allows our users to increase the frequency of their testing, making the prospect of early detection more likely.</p>
<p>By leveraging SiPhox Health&#8217;s comprehensive panel, a 39-year-old male, who was otherwise healthy and fit, made a potentially life-saving discovery.</p>
<p>Through SiPhox Health&#8217;s service, <strong>the customer identified abnormally high ferritin levels, which explained his previously unexplained fatigue and joint pain.</strong> Empowered with this crucial data, the customer took the initiative to seek treatment from his primary care physician (PCP).</p>
<h2>The Proof is in the Data</h2>
<ul>
<li>Test 1: January 4th, 2023 Upon receiving his SiPhox Health test results, the customer confirmed them at LabCorp and promptly sought care from his PCP. <strong>The diagnosis was revealed: Hereditary Hemochromatosis</strong>, a condition characterized by extreme iron overload.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1945 size-full" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-1.png" alt="" width="1218" height="717" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-1.png 1218w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-1-300x177.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-1-1024x603.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-1-768x452.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1218px) 100vw, 1218px" /></p>
<ul>
<li>Test 4: May 28th, 2023 Determined to regain his health, the customer diligently implemented the treatment recommendations provided by his PCP.</li>
</ul>
<p>He now regularly donates blood to lower his iron overload, and does monthly SiPhox Health tests.</p>
<p>With each subsequent test, the customer observed a consistent reduction in ferritin levels, a positive indicator of progress and improved health.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1946" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-2.png" alt="" width="1507" height="883" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-2.png 1507w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-2-300x176.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-2-1024x600.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-2-768x450.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1507px) 100vw, 1507px" /></p>
<h2>The Power of Comprehensive Blood Testing</h2>
<p>SiPhox Health&#8217;s comprehensive blood testing service has proven to be a game-changer, exemplifying the importance of proactive healthcare, principally through low-cost at-home blood testing. By empowering individuals with easily accessible and affordable tests, SiPhox Health enabled a life-saving discovery for this particular customer. Through early detection and prompt intervention, the customer&#8217;s condition was diagnosed and managed effectively, leading to improvements in health and well-being in just a few short months.</p>
<p>SiPhox Health&#8217;s dedication to putting the power of health in the hands of individuals showcases the immense potential for transformative change in the healthcare industry. By advocating for comprehensive blood panels and facilitating proactive healthcare, SiPhox Health continues to empower individuals to take control of their well-being and live healthier, more fulfilling lives.</p>
<h2>Hear it straight from the source</h2>
<div style="width: 750px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-1610-1" width="750" height="422" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/siphoxhealth_colingodby_v1-1080p.mp4?_=1" /><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/siphoxhealth_colingodby_v1-1080p.mp4">/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/siphoxhealth_colingodby_v1-1080p.mp4</a></video></div>
<p>The user left <a href="https://www.trustpilot.com/reviews/63df2e8c745e4800219b1fa8">this review on TrustPilot</a> after we helped him make a health discovery that potentially saved decades of his life.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-1948 size-full" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-3.png" alt="" width="916" height="615" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-3.png 916w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-3-300x201.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/ferritin-life-changing-3-768x516.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 916px) 100vw, 916px" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Huberman on Biohacking your Cortisol</title>
		<link>/hub/blog/huberman-on-biohacking-your-cortisol/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eva Medved]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 20:15:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Blogs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1567</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr. Andrew Huberman, a neuroscientist at Stanford University, highlights the crucial role that cortisol plays in regulating the body's energy levels, focus, immune system function, and inflammation regulation.]]></description>
			












							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Andrew Huberman is an American neuroscientist and tenured professor in the Department of Neurobiology at the Stanford University School of Medicine. In addition to his scientific research, Andrew Huberman has gained popularity for sharing his knowledge and insights on various platforms, such as podcasts, YouTube, and social media. He is the host of the &#8220;Huberman Lab Podcast,&#8221; where he discusses neuroscience, health, and human performance. Cortisol is one of the biomarkers that Andrew Huberman references frequently in his long-form health optimization episodes on sleep, energy, mood, and hormonal balance. Below are the highlights of Huberman on what role cortisol levels play in your body and how to biohack them.</p>
<h2>What is cortisol?</h2>
<p>Cortisol is a steroid hormone derived from cholesterol and produced by the adrenal glands, involved in stress response, metabolism, inflammation regulation, blood pressure control, and immune function. Managing cortisol levels is crucial to avoid health issues linked to chronic stress and maintain overall well-being.</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>In the Huberman Lab Podcast #18, Andrew Huberman explains that cortisol and adrenaline are essential hormones that regulate our energy levels, focus, and immune system function. He emphasizes that these hormones are not inherently good or bad, but rather their regulation is crucial. Huberman states, &#8220;They&#8217;re terrific when they&#8217;re regulated, they are terrible when they&#8217;re misregulated.&#8221;</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>In the Huberman Lab Podcast #18, Andrew Huberman explains that cortisol and adrenaline are essential hormones that regulate our energy levels, focus, and immune system function. He emphasizes that these hormones are not inherently good or bad, but rather their regulation is crucial. Huberman states, &#8220;They&#8217;re terrific when they&#8217;re regulated, they are terrible when they&#8217;re misregulated.&#8221;</p>

</div><h2>What does cortisol do and how does it relate to your circadian rythm?</h2>
<p>Cortisol plays several specific roles in the body:<br />
1. Stress response<br />
2. Glucose metabolism<br />
3. Anti-inflammatory properties<br />
4. Blood pressure regulation<br />
5. Immune function modulation</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>In his podcast, Dr. Andrew Huberman explains that cortisol is a hormone that is released in the morning to wake us up and stimulate movement. He emphasizes that “cortisol is not necessarily a stress hormone, but rather a hormone of energy.”</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>In his podcast, Dr. Andrew Huberman explains that cortisol is a hormone that is released in the morning to wake us up and stimulate movement. He emphasizes that “cortisol is not necessarily a stress hormone, but rather a hormone of energy.”</p>

</div><p>This is why it’s linked to wakefulness and circadian rythm.</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>“So the first tool is to make sure that your highest levels of cortisol are first thing in the morning when you wake up. One way or another, every 24 hours, you will get an increase in cortisol. That is non-negotiable. That is written into your genome. That increase in cortisol is there to wake you up and to make you alert.”</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>“So the first tool is to make sure that your highest levels of cortisol are first thing in the morning when you wake up. One way or another, every 24 hours, you will get an increase in cortisol. That is non-negotiable. That is written into your genome. That increase in cortisol is there to wake you up and to make you alert.”</p>

</div><p>Cortisol levels naturally vary throughout the day, following a pattern called the cortisol awakening response (CAR), which is closely related to the circadian rhythm. The circadian rhythm is the body&#8217;s internal 24-hour clock that regulates various physiological processes, including sleep, metabolism, and hormone production.</p>
<p>Cortisol levels are typically lowest around midnight and start to increase in the early morning hours before waking. They reach their peak approximately 30 minutes after.</p>
<p>Huberman on Biohacking your Cortisol 3 waking up, which is known as the cortisol awakening response. This peak in cortisol levels helps to jumpstart the body and provide energy for the day. After this peak, cortisol levels gradually decline throughout the day, reaching their lowest levels in the evening, which facilitates relaxation and sleep.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1331" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3.png" alt="" width="2000" height="1250" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3.png 2000w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3-300x188.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3-1024x640.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3-768x480.png 768w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3-1536x960.png 1536w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Untitled-3-1568x980.png 1568w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" /></p>
<p>Disruptions to the natural cortisol pattern can negatively impact overall health and wellbeing. Factors such as stress, jet lag, shift work, and exposure to artificial light at night can disrupt the circadian rhythm and cortisol secretion patterns. In the context of biohacking and health optimization, it is essential to maintain a balanced circadian rhythm and cortisol pattern. Strategies include maintaining a consistent sleep-wake schedule, getting exposure to natural sunlight during the day, reducing stress, and avoiding exposure to blue light from electronic devices in the evening.</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>In his podcast, Dr. Andrew Huberman explains that cortisol is a hormone that is released in the morning to wake us up and stimulate movement. He emphasizes that cortisol is not necessarily a stress hormone, but rather a hormone of energy. According to Dr. Huberman, cortisol and adrenaline are not inherently good or bad, but rather their effects depend on their regulation and timing of release. He suggests that chronic stress can lead to a cascade of stress and negative effects on the body.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>In his podcast, Dr. Andrew Huberman explains that cortisol is a hormone that is released in the morning to wake us up and stimulate movement. He emphasizes that cortisol is not necessarily a stress hormone, but rather a hormone of energy. According to Dr. Huberman, cortisol and adrenaline are not inherently good or bad, but rather their effects depend on their regulation and timing of release. He suggests that chronic stress can lead to a cascade of stress and negative effects on the body.</p>

</div><h2>Cortisol’s relationship to testosterone and estrogen</h2>
<p>Excess Cortisol not only increases stress levels and makes it difficult to sleep, but it can also decrease your sex hormone levels, as Huberman points out:</p>
<blockquote><p>But seldom is it discussed how sleep actually adjusts things like testosterone and estrogen. And it does it by modifying cortisol. So the molecule cholesterol can be converted into testosterone or estrogen, but there&#8217;s a competition whereby the cholesterol will turn into cortisol and not testosterone, or it&#8217;ll turn into cortisol and not estrogen if stress levels are too high.</p></blockquote>
<h2>How to measure and track your cortisol</h2>
<h3>Quest Diagnostics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Appointment required</li>
<li>Clinic visit required</li>
<li>Venous blood draw</li>
<li>$65</li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 1</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Not Included</li>
<li>1-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<h3>Letsgetchecked</h3>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit</li>
<li>Huberman on Biohacking your Cortisol 5</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (one-size fits all lancets)</li>
<li>$99 one-time, $69 subscription</li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 1</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Not Included</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<h3>Inside Tracker</h3>
<ul>
<li>Appointment required</li>
<li>At-home blood draw visit</li>
<li>$348</li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 including Cortisol</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 3 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<h3>SiPhox Health Kit</h3>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li><a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/pricing">$295 one-time, $85 subscription</a></li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 including Cortisol</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<h2>Biohacking your cortisol with Huberman</h2>
<p>If you measure your cortisol and find that its out of range, don’t worry! There are plenty of hacks to try for regulating and normalizing your cortisol levels.</p>
<h3>Morning Sunlight</h3>
<p>One of the major tools Dr. Huberman recommends is getting sunlight in the morning to regulate cortisol levels. As he puts it, the best way to stimulate that increase in cortisol at the appropriate time is that very soon after waking within 30 minutes or so after waking, get outside view some sunlight, even if it&#8217;s overcast, get outside view some sunlight, no sunglasses.</p>
<h3>Avoiding blue light at night?</h3>
<p>And I should also say avoiding bright lights from artificial sources in the evening, generally 10 PM to 4 AM, but certainly in the evening trying to dim lights in your immediate environment, trying to avoid bright screens, bright artificial lights as much as possible and accessing that deep sleep.</p>
<h3>Eating carbs</h3>
<p>Huberman notes that you can use carbs (judiciously) to blunt cortisol levels.</p>
<p>Many people do that reflexively, however, they reach for carbohydrate-rich foods to blunt their cortisol, because that&#8217;s indeed what it does. It blunts cortisol when you ingest high carbohydrate foods, in particular starchy foods.</p>
<p>In summary, Dr. Andrew Huberman, a neuroscientist at Stanford University, highlights the crucial role that cortisol plays in regulating the body&#8217;s energy levels, focus, immune system function, and inflammation regulation. He explains that cortisol is not inherently good or bad but rather its regulation is critical. Disruptions to the natural cortisol pattern can negatively impact overall health and wellbeing. Therefore, Dr. Huberman suggests various strategies to maintain a balanced circadian rhythm and cortisol pattern, including maintaining a consistent sleep-wake schedule, getting exposure to natural sunlight during the day, reducing stress, and avoiding exposure to blue light from electronic devices in the evening. Measuring and tracking cortisol levels can also help optimize health and wellbeing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
