<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Colin Budries &#8211; SiPhox Health</title>
	<atom:link href="/hub/author/colin-budries/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/hub/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 04:22:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Optimizing FSH for Enhanced Fertility: A Guide</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/optimizing-fsh-for-enhanced-fertility-a-guide/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colin Budries]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2023 18:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FSH]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[female fertility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fertility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[womens health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2476</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[FSH is key to understanding your fertility. It has many variables across age, gender, and lifestyle. Here are ways to better understand FSH. ]]></description>
			




							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>FSH is crucial for reproductive functions, regulating the menstrual cycle in women and sperm production in men. Understanding its role is key for assessing fertility and reproductive health.</li>
<li>Abnormal FSH levels can indicate health issues like POI and PCOS in women and testicular damage in men. Its measurement is essential for diagnosing and understanding various reproductive conditions.</li>
<li>Regular monitoring of FSH levels provides insights into changes in ovarian reserve and sperm production quality. This is crucial for informed decisions regarding fertility and overall reproductive health management.</li>
</ol>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h3>Key Takeaways</h3>
<ol>
<li>FSH is crucial for reproductive functions, regulating the menstrual cycle in women and sperm production in men. Understanding its role is key for assessing fertility and reproductive health.</li>
<li>Abnormal FSH levels can indicate health issues like POI and PCOS in women and testicular damage in men. Its measurement is essential for diagnosing and understanding various reproductive conditions.</li>
<li>Regular monitoring of FSH levels provides insights into changes in ovarian reserve and sperm production quality. This is crucial for informed decisions regarding fertility and overall reproductive health management.</li>
</ol>

</div><h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) plays a crucial role in the human body, particularly in the reproductive system. It is produced by the pituitary gland and is involved in sexual development and reproduction for both males and females. <strong>In females, FSH stimulates the production of <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/estradiol">estradiol</a> and regulates the menstrual cycle, peaking just before ovulation. In males, FSH works with <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/testosterone-page">testosterone</a> to maintain normal sperm count and function. FSH levels fluctuate during the menstrual cycle, with a peak in levels typically triggering ovulation.</strong></p>
<p>In women’s health, FSH is particularly significant. High levels of FSH may indicate conditions such as primary ovarian insufficiency (POI), polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), perimenopause, ovarian tumor, or Turner syndrome. Low FSH may indicate a pituitary gland disorder, hypothalamus disorder, insufficient egg production, or significant malnutrition. For males, high FSH may indicate testicular damage or Klinefelter syndrome, while low FSH may indicate pituitary gland or hypothalamus disorders. While high or low FSH may indicate certain conditions, FSH alone should not be used for diagnosis. FSH should be used in conjunction with other symptoms, biomarkers, and disease indicators. For these reasons, if you are concerned with your results, it is important to consult with your physician.</p>
<h2>Understanding FSH</h2>
<p>Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) is a gonadotropin, a type of hormone essential for reproductive processes in both females and males. In women, FSH is key to the growth and maturation of ovarian follicles, each containing an egg. It&#8217;s released by the pituitary gland and plays a critical role in regulating the menstrual cycle and stimulating the ovaries to produce estrogen. In the context of fertility, FSH levels are inversely indicative of ovarian reserve and function <strong>(i.e. high FSH indicates low ovarian reserve)</strong>, making it crucial for understanding a woman&#8217;s fertility potential at different stages of her reproductive life.</p>
<p>In men, Follicle-Stimulatin Hormone (FSH) plays a crucial role in reproduction, primarily by regulating the function of the testes. In males, FSH is secreted by the pituitary gland and is instrumental in the development and maturation of sperm. It acts directly on the Sertoli cells in the testes, which are essential for nurturing and supporting the development of sperm cells through the process of spermatogenesis. FSH stimulates these cells to produce and secrete various substances that promote sperm cell growth. Additionally, FSH is involved in increasing the concentration of testosterone-binding protein, which ensures a high local concentration of testosterone &#8211; essential for proper sperm development. This hormone&#8217;s activity is closely regulated by the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis, ensuring that sperm production is maintained at optimal levels for male fertility.</p>
<h2>Importance of Tracking FSH for Females</h2>
<ul>
<li>Repeat testing of FSH levels allows women to track changes over time, providing a clearer picture of their reproductive health and fertility status. Regular monitoring can indicate the onset of changes in ovarian reserve, especially as women age, and assist in making informed decisions about family planning and potential fertility treatments. It&#8217;s a valuable tool in understanding and managing reproductive health across different life stages.</li>
<li>SiPhox Health facilitates this through at-home tests, providing convenient and regular monitoring of FSH levels, and empowering women with valuable information for informed decision-making regarding their reproductive health.</li>
<li>Typically, a doctor might order an FSH test only once or infrequently, often in response to specific symptoms or concerns. This limited testing can miss fluctuations and trends in FSH levels over time, which are crucial for understanding a woman&#8217;s reproductive health and fertility status comprehensively. Regular, long-term tracking provides a more detailed and dynamic picture, allowing for better-informed decisions and timely interventions. This approach is more optimal than relying on single or infrequent tests for understanding and managing reproductive health changes.</li>
</ul>
<!-- <div class="block-quotes px-lg-40px ps-lg-60px ps-8px mb-32px">
    <div class="d-flex align-items-start">
        <img class="pe-20px" src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg' alt=""/>
        <div>
         
        <div class="bq-main"> <p>Research from <a href="https://journals.lww.com/co-obgyn/abstract/1998/06000/follicle_stimulating_hormone_as_a_predictor_of.9.aspx">&#8216;Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology&#8217;</a> highlights the predictive value of FSH levels in assessing ovarian function. One key insight is that elevated FSH levels in women, particularly in the early follicular phase of the menstrual cycle, can be a sign of reduced ovarian reserve. This information is crucial for understanding fertility potential and planning for conception.</p>

        </div> 
            
        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->


<div class="block-quotes">
    <img decoding="async" class="first" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">
    <img decoding="async" class="second" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">

    

    <div class="bq-main mb-28px">
        <p>Research from <a href="https://journals.lww.com/co-obgyn/abstract/1998/06000/follicle_stimulating_hormone_as_a_predictor_of.9.aspx">&#8216;Clinical Obstetrics and Gynecology&#8217;</a> highlights the predictive value of FSH levels in assessing ovarian function. One key insight is that elevated FSH levels in women, particularly in the early follicular phase of the menstrual cycle, can be a sign of reduced ovarian reserve. This information is crucial for understanding fertility potential and planning for conception.</p>

    </div>

    
   

</div><h2>Importance of Tracking FSH for Males</h2>
<h3>Assessing Reproductive Health</h3>
<p>FSH is integral to male reproductive health, primarily because it governs spermatogenesis, the process of sperm production in the testes. In cases of infertility or reduced fertility, measuring FSH levels can provide crucial insights. Low levels of FSH are often linked to a decreased sperm count or poor sperm quality, whereas high levels might suggest a failure in the testicular response. This information is vital for understanding an individual&#8217;s reproductive capabilities and planning appropriate interventions or treatments. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_1');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_1');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_1" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[1]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_1" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Diagnosing Hormonal Imbalances</h3>
<p>Hormonal balance is crucial for overall health, and FSH plays a significant role in this equilibrium. Disorders like hypogonadism, where the body produces insufficient testosterone, can be detected through abnormal FSH levels. Symptoms of hormonal imbalances, such as reduced libido, erectile dysfunction, or changes in physical characteristics, can be distressing. By tracking FSH levels, healthcare providers can diagnose these imbalances early and prescribe suitable treatments to alleviate symptoms and restore hormonal balance. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_2');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_2');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_2" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[2]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_2" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Evaluating Testicular Function</h3>
<p>The health and functionality of the testes are directly reflected in FSH levels. Abnormal readings can indicate various conditions, ranging from testicular atrophy to damage caused by trauma, surgery, or infections. Men who have experienced such issues can benefit significantly from regular FSH monitoring, as it helps in early detection and treatment of potential complications, ensuring better long-term testicular health. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_3');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_3');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_3" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[3]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_3" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Monitoring Treatment Response</h3>
<p>For men undergoing treatments for infertility or hormonal imbalances, monitoring FSH levels is a key part of the therapeutic process. It allows healthcare providers to track how effectively the body is responding to the treatment. Therapy adjustments, whether they involve hormone replacement, surgical interventions, or lifestyle changes, can be guided by changes in FSH levels, leading to more successful outcomes. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_4');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_4');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_4" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[4]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_4" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Detecting Underlying Conditions</h3>
<p>Elevated FSH levels can sometimes signal issues beyond the reproductive system, such as disorders of the pituitary gland, which regulates the production of various hormones. Conditions like Klinefelter syndrome, a genetic disorder affecting male chromosomes, or varicocele, an enlargement of the veins within the scrotum, can also alter FSH levels. Detecting these conditions early can lead to more effective management and treatment. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_5');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_5');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_5" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[5]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_5" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h3>Guiding Clinical Decisions</h3>
<p>Understanding a patient&#8217;s FSH levels helps clinicians make more informed decisions regarding their care. It plays a crucial role in determining the best approach to treatment, be it hormone therapies, surgical interventions, or assisted reproductive techniques like in vitro fertilization (IVF). Additionally, FSH levels provide valuable information for counseling men about their fertility prospects and future family planning options. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_6');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_6');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_6" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[6]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_6" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>FSH Levels and Pregnancy</h2>
<ul>
<li>Optimal FSH levels for conception typically range from about 4.7 to 21.5 mIU/mL <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_7');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_7');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_7" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[7]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_7" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></a>, depending on a woman&#8217;s age and the specific phase of her menstrual cycle. Lower FSH levels are generally more favorable for fertility. However, individual factors and health conditions can influence these levels. It&#8217;s important to consult with a healthcare provider for personalized assessment and guidance.</li>
<li>Even with higher FSH levels, conception can still be possible, but it may become more challenging. Each woman’s fertility profile is unique, and FSH is just one of many factors influencing it.</li>
<li>Knowing FSH levels before and after attempting to get pregnant helps in understanding a woman&#8217;s fertility window and potential challenges. Pre-pregnancy, it can indicate ovarian reserve and readiness for conception. Post-pregnancy, it aids in monitoring recovery and understanding any changes in fertility, especially in cases of difficulties in conceiving or planning for future pregnancies. This knowledge is vital for informed health decisions and family planning. For personalized advice, consult with a healthcare provider.</li>
</ul>
<h2>FSH and Women&#8217;s Age-Related Fertility</h2>
<p>FSH levels naturally vary with age in women. In the reproductive years, FSH levels fluctuate within the menstrual cycle, with a notable increase triggering ovulation. As women approach menopause, their ovarian reserve declines, leading to a significant rise in FSH levels. This increase is a response to decreased estrogen production, as the body attempts to stimulate the ovaries to produce more estrogen. The elevated FSH levels during this phase can be a marker of the transition into menopause. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_8');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_8');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_8" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[8]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_8" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<p>As women approach their late 30s and 40s, FSH levels may start to rise, signaling a decrease in ovarian reserve. This increase becomes more pronounced as women near menopause, typically in their late 40s to 50s, reflecting the diminished estrogen production and reduced fertility. These age-related changes in FSH levels are key indicators of a woman&#8217;s reproductive life stage. <span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_9');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_9');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_9" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[9]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_9" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></p>
<h2>Strategies to Optimize FSH Levels</h2>
<h3>Lifestyle Changes</h3>
<p>Managing stress through techniques like meditation, yoga, or regular exercise can help regulate hormone levels, including FSH. Adequate sleep is crucial, as disrupted sleep patterns can affect hormonal balance. Avoiding smoking and limiting alcohol consumption is also beneficial, as these can impact FSH levels and overall fertility.</p>
<h3>Dietary Changes</h3>
<p>A balanced diet rich in antioxidants can support reproductive health. Foods high in antioxidants, such as fruits, vegetables, nuts, and whole grains, are recommended. Reducing intake of processed foods and maintaining a healthy weight through diet and exercise is key, as obesity can affect hormone levels.</p>
<h3 class="p-rich_text_section">Supplement Regimen</h3>
<ul>
<li>To Lower FSH Levels:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Royal Jelly: This nutrient-rich substance can help reduce FSH levels.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Omega-3 Fatty Acids: Found in supplements like fish oil, they can assist in regulating hormone levels.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Vitamin D: Essential for hormonal regulation, it can be supplemented or obtained from sun exposure.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Zinc: A crucial mineral for reproductive health, which can aid in hormonal balance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>To Increase FSH Levels:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Oyster Polypeptides: Derived from oysters, these supplements may increase FSH levels.</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Probiotics: Supporting gut health, which in turn can impact hormonal balance.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>While lifestyle and dietary changes can influence overall health, they may not directly alter FSH levels significantly and should be viewed as part of a broader health strategy. Always follow the advice of your physician when making dietary changes or introducing a new supplement.</p>
<h2>Interpreting your Results</h2>
<p>Females should take FSH tests on day 3<span class="footnote_referrer"><a role="button" tabindex="0" onclick="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_10');" onkeypress="footnote_moveToReference_2476_1('footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_10');" ><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_10" class="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text">[10]</span></a><span id="footnote_plugin_tooltip_text_2476_1_10" class="footnote_tooltip"></span></span></a> of their menstrual cycle. When interpreting results for FSH, it is important to consider how dynamic this hormone can be. In those who menstruate, FSH varies considerably between the follicular and luteal phases of the menstrual cycle. Levels increase with age, but a surge occurs during perimenopause (the start of menopause) and remains high post-menopause. In males, FSH is low and is relatively static in comparison.</p>
<p>The following graph by <a href="https://www.straighthealthcare.com/female-hormone-physiology.html">Straight Healthcare</a> shows how variable FSH can be for menstruating females, along with other hormones that are important for the regulation of the menstrual cycle.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-2410" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image.png" alt="" width="2000" height="1294" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image.png 2000w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-300x194.png 300w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-1024x663.png 1024w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-768x497.png 768w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-1536x994.png 1536w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/image-1568x1014.png 1568w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" /></p>
<h2>Reference Ranges</h2>
<p>To assist in the interpretation of test results, the <a href="https://www.abim.org/Media/bfijryql/laboratory-reference-ranges.pdf">American Board of Internal Medicine</a> published reference ranges for FSH:</p>
<ul>
<li>Normally Menstruating Females:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Follicular phase: 2 – 9 mIU/mL</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Mid-cycle peak: 4 – 22 mIU/mL</li>
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">Luteal phase: 2 – 9 mIU/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Postmenopausal Females:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">30 mIU/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Males:
<ul class="p-rich_text_list p-rich_text_list__bullet" data-stringify-type="unordered-list" data-indent="1" data-border="0">
<li data-stringify-indent="1" data-stringify-border="0">1 – 7 mIU/mL</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Abnormally high or low levels of FSH could be indicative of a more serious issue, so please consult with your physician if you are concerned with any of your results.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>At SiPhox Health, we firmly believe in the power of understanding your body through regular FSH monitoring. This knowledge is not just a number; it&#8217;s a window into your reproductive well-being, guiding you in making informed decisions about your fertility journey and overall health. Our easy-to-use at-home testing kits bring this vital health information right to your doorstep, making it easier than ever to keep track of your fertility health.</p>
<h3><span id="Tracking_your_Vitamin_D_with_SiPhox_Health">Tracking your FSH with SiPhox Health:</span></h3>
<ul>
<li>At-home kit delivered to your home</li>
<li>Fingerprick sample self-collection (low-pain, adjustable lancets)</li>
<li><strong>$295 one-time or subscribe to get $85 per test*</strong></li>
<li>Number of biomarkers included: 17 (4 Hormonal Balance markers including FSH in the female Base Panel)</li>
<li>Hormone+ (includes FSH for males, as well) and Thyroid+ add-on panels</li>
<li>Sleep and activity tracking: Included, 200 devices supported</li>
<li>2-5 business days after collection</li>
</ul>
<div class="next-chapter">
    <div class="text-uppercase">
        <h4 class="m-0">
            start your siphox health journey
        </h4>
    </div>
    <div class="title">
        <h3 class="mt-0">
            Home health testing has never been this good
        </h3>
    </div>
    <p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your FSH + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>

    <a href='https://l.siphox.health/fsh'class='btn-cta'>Get started<span class='ms-8px'><img src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/right-arrow-light.svg' /></span></a>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2636" role="img" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg" alt="" width="1182" height="1001" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
<div class="speaker-mute footnotes_reference_container"> <div class="footnote_container_prepare"><p><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_label pointer" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2476_1();">References</span><span role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button" style="" onclick="footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2476_1();">[<a id="footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2476_1">+</a>]</span></p></div> <div id="footnote_references_container_2476_1" style="display: none;"><table class="footnotes_table footnote-reference-container"><caption class="accessibility">References</caption> <tbody> 

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_1" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_1');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >1</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Santi D, Crépieux P, Reiter E, Spaggiari G, Brigante G, Casarini L, Rochira V, Simoni M. Follicle-stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles. J Clin Med. 2020 Apr 3;9(4):1014. doi: 10.3390/jcm9041014. PMID: 32260182; PMCID: PMC7230878. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7230878/"><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles</span> &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_2" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_2');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >2</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Kumar P, Kumar N, Thakur DS, Patidar A. Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment. J Adv Pharm Technol Res. 2010 Jul;1(3):297-301. doi: 10.4103/0110-5558.72420. PMID: 22247861; PMCID: PMC3255409. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3255409/">Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_3" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_3');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >3</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Santi D, Crépieux P, Reiter E, Spaggiari G, Brigante G, Casarini L, Rochira V, Simoni M. Follicle-stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles. J Clin Med. 2020 Apr 3;9(4):1014. doi: 10.3390/jcm9041014. PMID: 32260182; PMCID: PMC7230878. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7230878/"><span style="font-family: var(--list--font-family); font-size: var(--global--font-size-base);">Follicle-Stimulating Hormone (FSH) Action on Spermatogenesis: A Focus on Physiological and Therapeutic Roles</span> &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_4" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_4');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >4</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Leslie SW, Soon-Sutton TL, Khan MAB. Male Infertility. 2023 Mar 3. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan–. PMID: 32965929. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK562258/">Male Infertility &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_5" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_5');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >5</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Kumar P, Kumar N, Thakur DS, Patidar A. Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment. J Adv Pharm Technol Res. 2010 Jul;1(3):297-301. doi: 10.4103/0110-5558.72420. PMID: 22247861; PMCID: PMC3255409. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3255409/">Male hypogonadism: Symptoms and treatment &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_6" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_6');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >6</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Leslie SW, Soon-Sutton TL, Khan MAB. Male Infertility. 2023 Mar 3. In: StatPearls [Internet]. Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Publishing; 2023 Jan–. PMID: 32965929. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK562258/">Male Infertility &#8211; PubMed (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_7" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_7');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >7</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/24638-follicle-stimulating-hormone-fsh**"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/24638-follicle-stimulating-hormone-fsh</span></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_8" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_8');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >8</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Santoro N, Randolph JF Jr. Reproductive hormones and the menopause transition. Obstet Gynecol Clin North Am. 2011 Sep;38(3):455-66. doi: 10.1016/j.ogc.2011.05.004. PMID: 21961713; PMCID: PMC3197715. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3197715/">Reproductive hormones and the menopause transition &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_9" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_9');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >9</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text">Jirge PR. Poor ovarian reserve. J Hum Reprod Sci. 2016 Apr-Jun;9(2):63-9. doi: 10.4103/0974-1208.183514. PMID: 27382229; PMCID: PMC4915288. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4915288/">Poor ovarian reserve &#8211; PMC (nih.gov)</a></td></tr>

<tr class="footnotes_plugin_reference_row"> <th scope="row" id="footnote_plugin_reference_2476_1_10" class="footnote_plugin_index pointer" onclick="footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1('footnote_plugin_tooltip_2476_1_10');"><a role="button" tabindex="0" class="footnote_plugin_link" >10</a></th> <td class="footnote_plugin_text"><a href="https://www.illumefertility.com/fertility-care/fertility-testing/what-is-cycle-day-3#:~:text=When%20a%20woman%20is%20undergoing,)%20and%20estradiol%20(E2).)"><span class="footnote_url_wrap">https://www.illumefertility.com/fertility-care/fertility-testing/what-is-cycle-day-3#:~:text=When</span> a woman is undergoing,) and estradiol (E2).)</td></tr>

 </tbody> </table> </div></div><script type="text/javascript"> function footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_1() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2476_1').show(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2476_1').text('−'); } function footnote_collapse_reference_container_2476_1() { jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2476_1').hide(); jQuery('#footnote_reference_container_collapse_button_2476_1').text('+'); } function footnote_expand_collapse_reference_container_2476_1() { if (jQuery('#footnote_references_container_2476_1').is(':hidden')) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_1(); } else { footnote_collapse_reference_container_2476_1(); } } function footnote_moveToReference_2476_1(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_1(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } } function footnote_moveToAnchor_2476_1(p_str_TargetID) { footnote_expand_reference_container_2476_1(); var l_obj_Target = jQuery('#' + p_str_TargetID); if (l_obj_Target.length) { jQuery( 'html, body' ).delay( 0 ); jQuery('html, body').animate({ scrollTop: l_obj_Target.offset().top - window.innerHeight * 0.25 }, 500); } }</script>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Case Study in Holistic Medicine</title>
		<link>/hub/blog/a-case-study-in-holistic-medicine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colin Budries]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 15:15:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Customer B2B]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1632</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Learn about how SiPhox Health's at-home biomarker tracking allowed a leading holistic health center to unlock more convenient and faster blood testing for their patients.]]></description>
			
							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Case Study: A Leading Holistic Health Center in South Florida</h2>
<p>How SiPhox Health enabled a leading wellness clinic on a mission to improve early health tracking with at-home blood testing and biomarker tracking.</p>
<p>The customer is based in South Florida and is led by licensed wellness professionals focusing on PEMF therapy, biofeedback coaching, multiscan evaluation, body balance, and applied kinesiology.</p>
<h3>Key Areas of Focus:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Increase access and convenience of blood testing</li>
<li>Increase patient engagement and follow-ups based on test results</li>
<li>Unlock core clinic wellness treatments with at-home testing</li>
</ul>
<h3>SiPhox Health Offering:</h3>
<ul>
<li>SiPhox Health at-home kits testing for biomarkers for inflammation, metabolic fitness, hormone and nutritional balance, and cardiovascular health.</li>
<li>SiPhox Health platform that enables real-time access to test results and biomarker trends.</li>
</ul>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="0">The Problem</span></h3>
<p>The customer wanted to unlock more convenient and faster blood testing. They were previously operating with very limited biomarker data and were asking patients to go to a Quest or Labcorp. The team felt less empowered in their care without regular blood testing for their patients.</p>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="0">The Solution</span></h3>
<p>SiPhox Health deploys kits to the customer which the customer uses in two workflows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Kits are mailed directly to patients to take their blood at home. The sample is then shipped to our lab and results are presented to the wellness team within three days. Clinical decisions and follow-ups are conducted based on the data presented.</li>
<li>Kits are offered to patients in-office while they have an appointment. They are completed on-site at the office and shipped directly to our lab.</li>
</ul>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="0">By the Numbers</span></h3>
<ul>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="0">40% </span>growth in kits ordered month over month</li>
</ul>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="0">Hear it from Them:</span></h3>
<p>“It is very nice to know that our feedback is valued highly.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>At-Home Blood Tests for Canadians- SiPhox Health Delivers</title>
		<link>/hub/blog/canadian-blood-tests-siphox/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colin Budries]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 17:19:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[User]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=1619</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[SiPhox Health stood up an extensive Canadian logistical network, enabling us to offer low-cost testing outside the US. Canadian users can now order kits directly to their homes, receiving a comprehensive 17-marker panel.]]></description>
			
							<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>SiPhox Health cuts barriers to access in Canada and improves accessibility via low-cost testing.</h2>
<p>SiPhox Health launched in September 2022 with a <span class="notion-enable-hover" data-token-index="1">low-cost</span> comprehensive panel for inflammation, metabolic fitness, hormone and nutritional balance, and cardiovascular health in Canada.</p>
<h3>The Problem:</h3>
<p>The Canadian medical system may leave its citizens with long wait times and lackluster care. Canadians are thus forced to take extreme measures to receive a reasonable level of care, often leading to financial distress or an insufficient amount of care. Other at-home testing companies have attempted to meet the needs of Canadians, but have been met with logistical challenges or unacceptable costs.</p>
<h3>The Solution:</h3>
<p>SiPhox Health stood up an extensive Canadian logistical network, enabling us to offer low-cost testing outside of the United States. Canadian users can now order kits directly to their homes, receiving a comprehensive 17-marker panel without leaving their homes.</p>
<h2>Hear about the issues firsthand:</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1626" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada3.png" alt="" width="694" height="195" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada3.png 694w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada3-300x84.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 694px) 100vw, 694px" /><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1627" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada2.png" alt="" width="694" height="221" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada2.png 694w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada2-300x96.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 694px) 100vw, 694px" /><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-1628" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada1.png" alt="" width="691" height="179" srcset="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada1.png 691w, /hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/04/canada1-300x78.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 691px) 100vw, 691px" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ferritin: Slow Aging and Reduce Future Disease Risk</title>
		<link>/hub/guides/biomarkers/optimal-ferritin-levels-and-how-to-lower-ferritin-a-biohackers-guide/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colin Budries]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:36:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ferritin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Guides]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?post_type=guides&#038;p=1536</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ferritin acts as a reservoir for iron, releasing and storing it as needed. Whether you're addressing an iron deficiency or ensuring you're not accumulating excess iron, understanding your ferritin levels can be a valuable tool for maintaining your overall health and well-being.]]></description>
			













							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h3>Key Takeaways:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Ferritin is an essential biomarker for iron storage, indicating iron sufficiency or deficiency.</li>
<li>High ferritin levels are linked to various health issues, including heart disease, diabetes, and certain cancers.</li>
<li>Strategies to manage ferritin levels include blood donation, dietary adjustments, and careful use of supplements.</li>
<li> Monitoring and understanding ferritin levels are crucial for proactive health management and reducing disease risk.</li>
</ol>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h3>Key Takeaways:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Ferritin is an essential biomarker for iron storage, indicating iron sufficiency or deficiency.</li>
<li>High ferritin levels are linked to various health issues, including heart disease, diabetes, and certain cancers.</li>
<li>Strategies to manage ferritin levels include blood donation, dietary adjustments, and careful use of supplements.</li>
<li> Monitoring and understanding ferritin levels are crucial for proactive health management and reducing disease risk.</li>
</ol>

</div><!-- <div class="block-quotes px-lg-40px ps-lg-60px ps-8px mb-32px">
    <div class="d-flex align-items-start">
        <img class="pe-20px" src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg' alt=""/>
        <div>
         
        <div class="bq-main"> <p>Life was designed to exist at the very interface between iron sufficiency and deficiency.</p>

        </div> 
             <div class='d-block bq-attributes bq-below'>
<p class='m-0'>- Dr James R. Connor
</p>
</div>
        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->


<div class="block-quotes">
    <img decoding="async" class="first" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">
    <img decoding="async" class="second" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">

    

    <div class="bq-main mb-28px">
        <p>Life was designed to exist at the very interface between iron sufficiency and deficiency.</p>

    </div>

     <div class='d-block bq-attributes bq-below'>
<p class='m-0'>- Dr James R. Connor
</p>
</div>
   

</div><p>Iron is an essential nutrient, and low levels in the diet, improper absorption, or excessive bleeding can lead to iron deficiency, which can result in anemia, cognitive problems, and immune dysfunction. It is essential to a number of metabolic processes, including respiration, the metabolism of proteins, lipids, or ribosomes, DNA biosynthesis and repair, and others.</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Iron is a vital component of several proteins responsible for oxygen transport and metabolism. It must be transported throughout the body, stored, and made available to synthesize iron proteins.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>Iron is a vital component of several proteins responsible for oxygen transport and metabolism. It must be transported throughout the body, stored, and made available to synthesize iron proteins.</p>

</div><p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Iron deficiency, which has historically been more prevalent than iron excess, has been the subject of extensive research, resulting in a high level of awareness among medical professionals of the resulting adverse health conditions.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Additionally, ferritin is an effective iron deficiency biomarker. It provides an accurate guide for individuals who may be iron deficient.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">In contrast, excess iron is far less studied, and its adverse health effects are far less well-known. And clinical laboratories provide upper limits of ferritin &#8220;normal ranges&#8221; that are too high for optimal future disease-risk reduction and longevity.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Although anemia (iron deficiency) is well-known, iron overload is a more common and dangerous problem. Most adult men and women after menopause are at risk for iron excess.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Lowering ferritin levels may be beneficial until close to the point that iron deficiency occurs. In the absence of a deficiency, it seems that the lower the ferritin level, the greater the health benefits.</span></p>
<p>Because of the absence of systematic iron elimination mechanisms, most organisms, including humans, tend to accumulate excess iron with age.</p>
<p>It is unclear whether the lack of disposal methods for excess iron was due to a scarcity of iron in the evolutionary environment or the rarity of iron&#8217;s detrimental effects in an environment where few organisms died of natural causes. As a result, the body cannot rid itself of excess iron, leaving us with an age-related accumulation.</p>
<p>In the natural world, iron reacts with oxygen to form rust. Within the body, it has a similar effect, causing elevated levels of oxidative stress.</p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Iron&#8217;s capacity to undergo cyclic oxidation and reduction is crucial to its function. However, this redox activity can lead to the production of free radicals and other highly oxidizing substances that have the potential to cause various biological injuries.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>Iron&#8217;s capacity to undergo cyclic oxidation and reduction is crucial to its function. However, this redox activity can lead to the production of free radicals and other highly oxidizing substances that have the potential to cause various biological injuries.</p>

</div><p>More specifically, iron&#8217;s ability to accept or donate electrons is what makes it useful but also capable of biological damage. When iron reacts with hydrogen peroxide via the Fenton reaction, it can create a highly reactive and toxic free radical called hydroxyl.</p>
<p>This can lead to severe mitochondrial dysfunction, which may be the root cause of most chronic degenerative diseases.</p>
<p>Numerous health issues, including cancer, heart disease, diabetes, stroke, neurodegenerative diseases, gouty arthritis, hepatitis C, Alzheimer&#8217;s disease, and liver disease, have been linked to elevated iron levels.</p>
<p>High ferritin levels have been associated with dysfunctional glucose metabolism, which can increase the risk of diabetes in both men and women. In fact, men may experience a fivefold increase in diabetes risk, while women may experience a fourfold increase, similar to the risk associated with obesity.</p>
<p>Additionally, high ferritin levels may double the risk of metabolic syndrome, a condition that is linked to an increased risk of high blood pressure, liver disease, and heart disease. Those practicing proactive health must manage ferritin levels to reduce the future risk of these health issues.</p>
<!-- <div class="block-quotes px-lg-40px ps-lg-60px ps-8px mb-32px">
    <div class="d-flex align-items-start">
        <img class="pe-20px" src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg' alt=""/>
        <div>
         
        <div class="bq-main"> <p>Although many people routinely check their cholesterol levels, which have a limited impact on heart health, few think to check their ferritin (stored iron) levels. Iron is the new cholesterol.</p>

        </div> 
            
        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->


<div class="block-quotes">
    <img decoding="async" class="first" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">
    <img decoding="async" class="second" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">

    

    <div class="bq-main mb-28px">
        <p>Although many people routinely check their cholesterol levels, which have a limited impact on heart health, few think to check their ferritin (stored iron) levels. Iron is the new cholesterol.</p>

    </div>

    
   

</div><h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">How to Lower Ferritin Levels</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Donating blood is generally the recommended solution to iron overload. However, a three-pronged approach is even better: phlebotomy, detoxification, and reducing dietary iron.</span></p>
<h3>Blood donation</h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Donating blood twice or thrice yearly is the simplest method to reduce iron load significantly. However, you may need to perform phlebotomies more frequently if you have a severe overload. Blood loss is the primary way to lower excess iron.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Because hemoglobin is the primary iron store in the body, its replacement demands the use of iron stores and depletes them. Several studies have found that blood donors have a lower mortality rate, even when the healthy donor effect of donors being healthier than others prior to donation is accounted for.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">When examining blood donors only as a distinct group, a negative correlation has been observed between the frequency of blood donation and mortality. In fact, each additional yearly donation is linked to a 7.5% decrease in the mortality rate. Blood donation is also linked to a significant reduction in body iron levels in adult men. Depleted ferritin levels (&lt;15 μg/L) in male donors are approximately eight times more prevalent than in non-donors.</span></p>
<h3><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Use the Right Kitchenware</span></h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Cooking acidic foods (e.g., tomatoes) in iron pots or pans can lead to higher levels of iron absorption. This is because the acid in the food reacts with the iron in the cookware, causing small amounts of iron to leach into the food. Instead, cook acidic foods with other cookware, such as stainless steel.</span></p>
<h3><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Read Supplement Labels</span></h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Vitamins and mineral supplements frequently include iron. Read the labels and check &#8211; particularly the multi-vitamin and mineral products. For example, &#8220;meal replacements and nutritional supplements&#8221; must have iron added in Canada.</span></p>
<h3><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Sauna</span></h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">According to research, sauna use increases sweating, which can help remove iron through the skin. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">In addition, saunas have been shown to increase the production of erythropoietin, a hormone that stimulates red blood cell production and increases the body&#8217;s iron demand. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">This increased iron demand can help reduce the amount of excess iron in the body.</span></p>
<h3><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Limit Alcohol Consumption</span></h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Avoid regular alcohol consumption because it enhances dietary iron absorption. For example, consuming wine with your steak may result in absorbing more iron than you need.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Alcohol inhibits the production of hepcidin, the hormone that controls iron metabolism. Hepcidin regulates the quantity of dietary iron that is absorbed and released from storage in the body. It has been demonstrated that alcohol reduces hepcidin production, which can increase iron absorption and accumulation.</span></p>
<h3><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Avoid Fortified Foods</span></h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The United States and Canada mandate that many food and drink items are fortified with iron, including flour, pre-cooked rice, and fruit-flavoured drinks. Avoid regularly eating processed foods such as cereals and white bread. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Two servings of fortified breakfast cereal alone can provide as much as 44 milligrams (mg) of iron, perilously close to the recommended maximum daily iron intake.</span></p>
<h3><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Food and Drink that Inhibits Iron Absorption</span></h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">You can alter your diet and beverages to reduce the amount of iron you absorb. The following may inhibit iron absorption:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Dairy products</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Eggs</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Chocolate</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Tea and coffee</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Vegetables</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Phytate-rich foods including hazelnuts, almonds, and legumes (beans, peas, lentils)</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The consumption of eggs and dairy products along with meals may hinder iron absorption by as much as 50%. Calcium found in dairy products competes with iron for absorption, which can inhibit it. Similarly, eggs contain a substance that tightly binds iron and prevents its absorption. This substance also helps to protect eggs from bacterial invasion by denying iron to potential invaders.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Tea and coffee greatly lower the amount of iron that&#8217;s absorbed from a meal. To inhibit iron, coffee or tea must be drunk with or shortly after a meal and not before.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Coffee can reduce iron absorption by as much as 80% when consumed with a meal. Black or green tea appears to be the most effective iron inhibitor. As much as 94% of iron absorption is inhibited when black tea is drunk with a meal.</span></p>
<h3>Dietary Tea</h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">By inhibiting iron absorption, Camellia sinensis extracts increase the lifespan of Drosophila (&#8220;small fruit flies&#8221;) by up to 21.4%.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Camellia sinensis is more commonly known as </span><em><span data-preserver-spaces="true">tea plant</span></em><span data-preserver-spaces="true">. White tea, yellow tea, green tea, oolong, dark tea, and black tea are all harvested from one of two major varieties grown today. Different processing methods yield the various types of tea.</span></p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Studies have also shown that catechins can act as antioxidants, reducing oxidative damage and inflammation in cells.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>Studies have also shown that catechins can act as antioxidants, reducing oxidative damage and inflammation in cells.</p>

</div><p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The active compounds that are responsible are the catechins, which are a type of flavonoid. Flavonoids are a group of polyphenols. Catechins can bind to dietary iron, preventing it from being absorbed by the body. </span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Consider Supplements</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">A number of geroprotectors increase lifespan in model organisms, and many of these either block dietary iron absorption or chelate iron and remove it.</span></p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>A geroprotector is an agent that helps protect against aging. It works by targeting the underlying mechanisms involved in aging and helping to maintain youthful cellular and tissue functions. Geroprotectors can come in many forms, such as supplements, medications, and lifestyle modifications.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>A geroprotector is an agent that helps protect against aging. It works by targeting the underlying mechanisms involved in aging and helping to maintain youthful cellular and tissue functions. Geroprotectors can come in many forms, such as supplements, medications, and lifestyle modifications.</p>

</div><!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Chelating agents are compounds with multiple sites capable of binding to metal ions, such as iron. When a chelating agent binds to iron, it forms a complex in which the iron is no longer free to participate in chemical reactions. These compounds help to remove metal ions from the body.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <p>Chelating agents are compounds with multiple sites capable of binding to metal ions, such as iron. When a chelating agent binds to iron, it forms a complex in which the iron is no longer free to participate in chemical reactions. These compounds help to remove metal ions from the body.</p>

</div><h3>Curcumin</h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Mice-fed diets supplemented 0.2% with curcumin became iron deficient; levels of zinc and copper were not affected, suggesting that curcumin is a potent iron chelator. Curcumin (and its metabolite tetrahydrocurcumin) extended the average lifespan of three model organisms: C. elegans, Drosophila, and mice.</span></p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Curcumin is known to have a wide range of benefits, including antioxidant, antiviral, anti-inflammatory, improving digestion and cognitive function, relieving joint pain, aiding in weight loss, antiangiogenic and antitumorigenic (preventing cancer), and more.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>Curcumin is known to have a wide range of benefits, including antioxidant, antiviral, anti-inflammatory, improving digestion and cognitive function, relieving joint pain, aiding in weight loss, antiangiogenic and antitumorigenic (preventing cancer), and more.</p>

</div><p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Curcumin is the key active ingredient in turmeric. Turmeric is a yellow powder made from the rhizome of the Curcuma longa plant. It has been used as a traditional medicine in Ayurvedic practices and as a food ingredient for thousands of years.</span></p>
<h3>EGCG</h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG) is a type of catechin, found in green tea, that is a strong iron chelator. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">EGCG has been shown to extend the lifespan of both C. elegans and Drosophila. Studies on mice have revealed that EGCG safeguards against alcoholic liver disease by decreasing iron levels in the liver.</span></p>
<h3>Berberine</h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Berberine has been shown to extend the lifespan of mice. Berberine has been found to exhibit iron-chelating properties. In a study on rats, berberine reduced iron overload in the liver. Additionally, the study found that berberine could inhibit the expression of hepcidin, a protein involved in iron metabolism and storage. </span></p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Studies have shown berberine to be an antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-bacterial, and anti-fungal, as well as potential benefits for a range of other health conditions, including blood sugar control, cardiovascular health, weight management, and digestion.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>Studies have shown berberine to be an antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-bacterial, and anti-fungal, as well as potential benefits for a range of other health conditions, including blood sugar control, cardiovascular health, weight management, and digestion.</p>

</div><p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Berberine is an active compound known as an alkaloid (an organic compound containing at least one nitrogen atom) found in certain plants, including barberry, goldenseal, Oregon grape, and tree turmeric.</span></p>
<h3>Quercetin</h3>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Quercetin has been shown to extend the lifespan of </span><em><span data-preserver-spaces="true">C. elegans.</span></em><span data-preserver-spaces="true"> Quercetin has demonstrated iron-chelating properties.</span></p>
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px warning'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/warning.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <p>Studies have shown quercetin to reduce the risk of heart disease, lower blood pressure, improve blood sugar control, and support the immune system. Quercetin has also been studied for its potential benefits in treating allergies, asthma, and other respiratory illnesses.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card warning">
    <p>Studies have shown quercetin to reduce the risk of heart disease, lower blood pressure, improve blood sugar control, and support the immune system. Quercetin has also been studied for its potential benefits in treating allergies, asthma, and other respiratory illnesses.</p>

</div><p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Quercetin is a flavonoid that occurs naturally in a variety of plants, including red onions, pears, berries, and certain leafy green vegetables. It is available in supplement form.</span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Optimal Ferritin Levels</span></h2>
<!-- <div class="block-quotes px-lg-40px ps-lg-60px ps-8px mb-32px">
    <div class="d-flex align-items-start">
        <img class="pe-20px" src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg' alt=""/>
        <div>
         
        <div class="bq-main"> <p>Often patients express worry that their ferritin levels are too low, when, in fact, I am concerned about the opposite.</p>

        </div> 
             <div class='d-block bq-attributes bq-below'>
<p class='m-0'>- Lesley James MD
</p>
</div>
        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->


<div class="block-quotes">
    <img decoding="async" class="first" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">
    <img decoding="async" class="second" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/quote-icon.svg" alt="">

    

    <div class="bq-main mb-28px">
        <p>Often patients express worry that their ferritin levels are too low, when, in fact, I am concerned about the opposite.</p>

    </div>

     <div class='d-block bq-attributes bq-below'>
<p class='m-0'>- Lesley James MD
</p>
</div>
   

</div><p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Those interested in proactive healthcare, reducing future-disease risk, and extending lifespan, must consider much tighter upper bounds than &#8220;normal ranges&#8221; would suggest. Laboratories give upper ranges that may be far too high for optimal health.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Gerry Koenig, former chairman of the Iron Disorders Institute and the Hemochromatosis Foundation, related the following ferritin values:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">The most commonly used threshold for iron deficiency in clinical studies is 12-15 ng/mL (30-37 nmol/L).</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">You do not want to be below 20 ng/mL (50 nmol/L) or above 80 ng/mL (200 nmol/L). </span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Adult men and non-menstruating women should aim for 30-40 ng/mL (75-100 nmol/L).</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Regularly screen for iron overload with a ferritin test. Your iron status is likely far more critical than your cholesterol. </span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Virtually all adult men and postmenopausal women are at risk for iron overload due to inefficient iron excretion since they do not lose blood on a regular basis.</span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">What is ferritin</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Ferritin is a protein that stores iron and releases it as needed. It helps to regulate the amount of iron in the blood and tissues, ensuring that our cells have enough to function properly. It is present in almost all living organisms, including plants, animals, and humans.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Additionally, ferritin plays an important role in maintaining healthy levels of red blood cells and preventing anemia. Anemia is a blood disorder in which the blood has a reduced ability to carry oxygen due to a lower-than-normal number of red blood cells or a reduction in hemoglobin.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Ferritin is found in many different tissues in the body, but it is most abundant in the liver, spleen, and bone marrow. The liver is the primary site of ferritin synthesis and storage.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">When the body has an excess of iron, the iron is stored in the form of ferritin to prevent it from causing damage to other tissues. When the body needs more iron, ferritin releases the stored iron into the bloodstream, where it can be transported to other tissues to be used for various functions (such as the production of red blood cells).</span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Why measure ferritin levels</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Ferritin is an important indicator of overall health that is measured to provide insight into the amount of iron stored in the body and detect any abnormalities in iron metabolism.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Low ferritin levels typically indicate low iron stores in the body, which can lead to anemia and other health problems. Iron deficiency anemia is a common type of anemia that occurs when the body does not have enough iron to produce hemoglobin, a protein in red blood cells that carries oxygen.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">On the other hand, high ferritin levels can indicate an excess of stored iron, which can also have negative health effects and accelerate aging.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Measuring ferritin levels may also help detect diseases like cancer, diabetes and thyroid problems earlier on. Therefore, measuring ferritin levels is essential for maintaining good health and well-being.</span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">What are the symptoms of low ferritin?</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Low ferritin levels, also known as hyporferritinemia, may be the cause of one or more of the symptoms:</span></p>
<ol>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Fatigue and weakness: Low iron levels can cause fatigue and weakness, as iron is needed to produce hemoglobin, which carries oxygen throughout the body.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Shortness of breath: Low iron levels can also cause shortness of breath, particularly with physical activity.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Headaches: Low iron levels can cause headaches, particularly when the body is low on oxygen.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Dizziness or lightheadedness: Low iron levels can cause dizziness or lightheadedness, particularly when standing up quickly.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Pale skin: Iron deficiency anemia can cause the skin to become pale or even yellowish.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Cold hands and feet: Low iron levels can cause a decrease in body temperature, leading to cold hands and feet.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Restless leg syndrome: Iron deficiency can cause restless leg syndrome, characterized by uncomfortable sensations in the legs and an urge to move them.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Brittle nails: Low iron levels can cause the nails to become brittle and fragile.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Slow healing:</span>
<ul>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Low iron levels can impair the body&#8217;s ability to heal wounds, as oxygen is necessary for the formation of new blood vessels and the production of collagen, a protein that helps the skin heal.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Additionally, iron is involved in the immune system&#8217;s response to infection, and low levels of iron can impair the immune system&#8217;s ability to fight off infections which can cause wounds to heal more slowly.</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Infertility: Low iron levels can lead to the ovaries producing fewer and lower-quality eggs, which can contribute to infertility. Additionally, iron deficiency anemia can cause menstrual irregularities, such as heavy or prolonged menstrual bleeding, which can also contribute to infertility.</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">It&#8217;s important to note that not all people with low ferritin levels will experience symptoms and that other conditions can also cause the symptoms of low ferritin.</span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">What are the symptoms of high ferritin?</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">High ferritin levels, also known as hyperferritinemia, can manifest as several symptoms associated with several conditions, including iron overload disorders and certain types of inflammatory or infectious diseases:</span></p>
<ol>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Abdominal pain: High ferritin levels can be associated with conditions such as hemochromatosis, which can cause abdominal pain and discomfort.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Joint pain and swelling: Certain inflammatory conditions associated with high ferritin levels, such as rheumatoid arthritis, can cause joint pain and swelling.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Skin discoloration: In some cases, high ferritin levels can cause skin discoloration, such as a bronzed appearance.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Loss of libido and impotence: Iron overload disorders, such as hemochromatosis, can cause hormonal imbalances that can lead to a loss of libido and impotence.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Weight gain: High ferritin levels can be a sign of liver damage or inflammation, which can be detected through elevated liver enzyme levels. High ferritin levels can be seen in certain types of liver disease, such as non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, which can cause weight gain.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Metabolic syndrome: High ferritin levels are associated with an increased risk of developing metabolic syndrome, but they are not a direct cause of the condition. Metabolic syndrome is a group of conditions that occur together, including high blood pressure, high blood sugar, excess body fat around the waist, and abnormal cholesterol or triglyceride levels.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Cancer: High ferritin levels can be seen in certain types of cancer, particularly those that involve inflammation or liver damage. High ferritin levels may also be associated with an increased risk of developing certain types of cancer. For example, some studies have found that high ferritin levels are associated with an increased risk of liver cancer and colorectal cancer.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Celiac disease: High ferritin levels can be associated with certain underlying medical conditions that may contribute to the development of celiac disease. For example, iron overload disorders such as hemochromatosis can cause damage to the liver and pancreas, leading to impaired pancreatic function and an increased risk of developing celiac disease. Additionally, chronic inflammation, which is associated with high ferritin levels, can also contribute to the development of celiac disease.</span></li>
</ol>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Some people with high ferritin levels may not experience any symptoms, while others may experience symptoms related to the underlying condition causing the high ferritin levels.</span></p>
<h2><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Interpretation of ferritin test results and optimal ranges</span></h2>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Ferritin test results are reported in nanograms of ferritin per milliliter of blood (ng/mL) or micrograms per liter (μg/L). SiPhox Health reports are expressed in ng/mL.</span></p>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Here&#8217;s how to interpret your ferritin results:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Cleveland Clinic lists a normal range of 30.3 to 565.7 ng/ML for men, and a normal range of 14.7 to 205.1 ng/ML for women.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">According to Oregon Health &amp; Science University (OHSU), a ferritin value of less than 20 ng/mL is indicative of iron deficiency, while a ferritin count of 21 to 50 is indicative of a possible iron deficiency. When the ferritin level exceeds 200 ng/mL, iron overload is a possibility.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Generally, ferritin levels below 30 ng/mL during pregnancy are considered to be indicative of iron deficiency anemia, which is a common concern during pregnancy. The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG) lists a ferritin level of 30 to 150 ng/ML as normal in pregnancy.</span></li>
<li><span data-preserver-spaces="true">SiPhox Health lists a normal range of 23.9 to 336.2 ng/ML for men, and a normal range of 11 to 306.8 ng/ML for women.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Optimal ferritin levels can vary depending on factors such as age, sex, and underlying health conditions. </span></p>
<div class="next-chapter">
    <div class="text-uppercase">
        <h4 class="m-0">
            start your siphox health journey
        </h4>
    </div>
    <div class="title">
        <h3 class="mt-0">
            Home health testing has never been this good
        </h3>
    </div>
    <p>Subscribe to SiPhox and start tracking your Ferritin + 16 other critical biomarkers as well as sleep, activity and heart data all in one comprehensive dashboard.</p>

    <a href='https://l.siphox.health/ferritin'class='btn-cta'>Get started<span class='ms-8px'><img src='/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/right-arrow-light.svg' /></span></a>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2636" role="img" src="/hub/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Pricing-comparison-5.svg" alt="" width="1182" height="1001" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="font-size: 14px;">Disclaimer: If you have any medical questions or concerns, please talk to your healthcare provider. The articles on the SiPhox Health Hub are underpinned by peer-reviewed research and information drawn from medical societies and governmental agencies. However, they are not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
