<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>SiPhox Health</title>
	<atom:link href="/hub/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/hub/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 22:52:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Urine Albumin</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-albumin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3936</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[
What is Urine Albumin? Urine albumin is the presence of albumin—a major blood protein—in your urine. Under normal conditions, healthy kidneys filter waste products while keeping essential proteins like albumin in your bloodstream. When albumin appears in urine, it may indicate that the kidney’s filtering units (glomeruli) are damaged or stressed, allowing protein to leak&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-albumin/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Urine Albumin</span></a>]]></description>
			
							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!-- <div class='highlight-card mb-32px highlight-card-info'>
    <div class='d-flex'>
        <div class='icon-container'>
            <img decoding="async" src="/hub/wp-content/themes/theblog-child/assets/images/tip.svg" alt=''/>
        </div>
        <div class='d-flex ms-16px'>
            <h2>What is Urine Albumin?</h2>
<p>Urine albumin is the presence of albumin—a major blood protein—in your urine. Under normal conditions, healthy kidneys filter waste products while keeping essential proteins like albumin in your bloodstream. When albumin appears in urine, it may indicate that the kidney’s filtering units (glomeruli) are damaged or stressed, allowing protein to leak through.</p>
<h2>Why Testing Urine Albumin Matters</h2>
<p>Detecting albumin in urine (<strong>albuminuria</strong>) is an early marker for kidney disease. Because kidney damage often progresses without symptoms, regular urine albumin testing can identify problems before they cause significant, irreversible damage. The test is especially important for people with <strong>diabetes</strong> or <strong>high blood pressure</strong>, which are leading causes of chronic kidney disease (CKD). It’s also used to monitor individuals with other conditions that can affect kidney function.</p>
<h2>Types of Urine Albumin Tests</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Random urine albumin test:</strong> Measures albumin concentration from a single sample.</li>
<li><strong>24-hour urine collection:</strong> Measures total albumin excretion over a full day.</li>
<li><strong>Albumin-to-creatinine ratio (ACR):</strong> Preferred method that adjusts for urine concentration differences.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal Ranges</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<p><strong>Albumin-to-creatinine ratio (ACR):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Normal: &lt; 30 mg/g</li>
<li>Moderately increased (microalbuminuria): 30–300 mg/g</li>
<li>Severely increased (macroalbuminuria): &gt; 300 mg/g</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>24-hour urine albumin:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Normal: &lt; 30 mg/day</li>
<li>Microalbuminuria: 30–300 mg/day</li>
<li>Macroalbuminuria: &gt; 300 mg/day</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Temporary elevations can occur with fever, intense exercise, urinary tract infections, dehydration, or menstruation. Repeat testing is often recommended to confirm persistent albuminuria.</p>
<h2>Conditions Linked to Elevated Urine Albumin</h2>
<ul>
<li>Diabetes (diabetic nephropathy)</li>
<li>Hypertension (high blood pressure)</li>
<li>Glomerulonephritis (inflammation of kidney filters)</li>
<li>Polycystic kidney disease</li>
<li>Lupus and other autoimmune disorders</li>
<li>Heart failure</li>
<li>Preeclampsia during pregnancy</li>
<li>Multiple myeloma or amyloidosis</li>
</ul>
<h2>Strategies to Reduce Urine Albumin &#038; Protect Kidneys</h2>
<h3>Blood Pressure and Blood Sugar Control</h3>
<ul>
<li>Maintain blood pressure &lt;130/80 mmHg for CKD patients</li>
<li>Use ACE inhibitors or ARBs for kidney protection</li>
<li>Keep HbA1c below ~7% in diabetes to lower risk</li>
</ul>
<h3>Dietary Modifications</h3>
<ul>
<li>Limit sodium to &lt;2,300 mg/day</li>
<li>Moderate protein intake (0.8–1.0 g/kg/day for kidney disease)</li>
<li>Follow DASH or Mediterranean diet</li>
<li>Reduce processed foods and added sugars</li>
<li>Increase fruits, vegetables, and whole grains</li>
</ul>
<h3>Lifestyle Changes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Exercise regularly (150 minutes/week of moderate activity)</li>
<li>Maintain healthy weight</li>
<li>Quit smoking</li>
<li>Stay well-hydrated</li>
</ul>
<h2>Monitoring Kidney Health Over Time</h2>
<p>People with diabetes should start annual albumin testing at diagnosis (type 2) or after 5 years (type 1). Those with hypertension or other risk factors should test regularly. Kidney health monitoring should also include serum creatinine, eGFR, blood pressure, and electrolytes for a complete picture.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> This information is for educational purposes only and is not a substitute for professional medical advice. Always consult your healthcare provider for interpretation of your urine albumin results and for personalized kidney health recommendations.</p>

        </div>
    </div>
</div> -->
<div class="highlight-card highlight-card-info">
    <h2>What is Urine Albumin?</h2>
<p>Urine albumin is the presence of albumin—a major blood protein—in your urine. Under normal conditions, healthy kidneys filter waste products while keeping essential proteins like albumin in your bloodstream. When albumin appears in urine, it may indicate that the kidney’s filtering units (glomeruli) are damaged or stressed, allowing protein to leak through.</p>
<h2>Why Testing Urine Albumin Matters</h2>
<p>Detecting albumin in urine (<strong>albuminuria</strong>) is an early marker for kidney disease. Because kidney damage often progresses without symptoms, regular urine albumin testing can identify problems before they cause significant, irreversible damage. The test is especially important for people with <strong>diabetes</strong> or <strong>high blood pressure</strong>, which are leading causes of chronic kidney disease (CKD). It’s also used to monitor individuals with other conditions that can affect kidney function.</p>
<h2>Types of Urine Albumin Tests</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Random urine albumin test:</strong> Measures albumin concentration from a single sample.</li>
<li><strong>24-hour urine collection:</strong> Measures total albumin excretion over a full day.</li>
<li><strong>Albumin-to-creatinine ratio (ACR):</strong> Preferred method that adjusts for urine concentration differences.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal Ranges</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<p><strong>Albumin-to-creatinine ratio (ACR):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Normal: &lt; 30 mg/g</li>
<li>Moderately increased (microalbuminuria): 30–300 mg/g</li>
<li>Severely increased (macroalbuminuria): &gt; 300 mg/g</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>24-hour urine albumin:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Normal: &lt; 30 mg/day</li>
<li>Microalbuminuria: 30–300 mg/day</li>
<li>Macroalbuminuria: &gt; 300 mg/day</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Temporary elevations can occur with fever, intense exercise, urinary tract infections, dehydration, or menstruation. Repeat testing is often recommended to confirm persistent albuminuria.</p>
<h2>Conditions Linked to Elevated Urine Albumin</h2>
<ul>
<li>Diabetes (diabetic nephropathy)</li>
<li>Hypertension (high blood pressure)</li>
<li>Glomerulonephritis (inflammation of kidney filters)</li>
<li>Polycystic kidney disease</li>
<li>Lupus and other autoimmune disorders</li>
<li>Heart failure</li>
<li>Preeclampsia during pregnancy</li>
<li>Multiple myeloma or amyloidosis</li>
</ul>
<h2>Strategies to Reduce Urine Albumin &#038; Protect Kidneys</h2>
<h3>Blood Pressure and Blood Sugar Control</h3>
<ul>
<li>Maintain blood pressure &lt;130/80 mmHg for CKD patients</li>
<li>Use ACE inhibitors or ARBs for kidney protection</li>
<li>Keep HbA1c below ~7% in diabetes to lower risk</li>
</ul>
<h3>Dietary Modifications</h3>
<ul>
<li>Limit sodium to &lt;2,300 mg/day</li>
<li>Moderate protein intake (0.8–1.0 g/kg/day for kidney disease)</li>
<li>Follow DASH or Mediterranean diet</li>
<li>Reduce processed foods and added sugars</li>
<li>Increase fruits, vegetables, and whole grains</li>
</ul>
<h3>Lifestyle Changes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Exercise regularly (150 minutes/week of moderate activity)</li>
<li>Maintain healthy weight</li>
<li>Quit smoking</li>
<li>Stay well-hydrated</li>
</ul>
<h2>Monitoring Kidney Health Over Time</h2>
<p>People with diabetes should start annual albumin testing at diagnosis (type 2) or after 5 years (type 1). Those with hypertension or other risk factors should test regularly. Kidney health monitoring should also include serum creatinine, eGFR, blood pressure, and electrolytes for a complete picture.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> This information is for educational purposes only and is not a substitute for professional medical advice. Always consult your healthcare provider for interpretation of your urine albumin results and for personalized kidney health recommendations.</p>

</div>]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Urine Creatinine</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-creatinine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:28:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3934</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is Urine Creatinine? Urine creatinine is a waste product produced from the normal breakdown of muscle tissue. During muscle metabolism, creatine phosphate breaks down into creatinine, which travels through the bloodstream to the kidneys, where it is filtered out and eliminated in urine. Because creatinine production is relatively constant and proportional to muscle mass,&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-creatinine/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Urine Creatinine</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is Urine Creatinine?</h2>
<p>Urine creatinine is a waste product produced from the normal breakdown of muscle tissue. During muscle metabolism, creatine phosphate breaks down into creatinine, which travels through the bloodstream to the kidneys, where it is filtered out and eliminated in urine. Because creatinine production is relatively constant and proportional to muscle mass, it serves as a reliable marker for assessing kidney function, muscle mass, and the accuracy of other urine test results.</p>
<h2>Why Urine Creatinine Testing Matters</h2>
<p>Urine creatinine testing provides insights that blood creatinine levels alone cannot. While blood creatinine reflects how well your kidneys filter waste, urine creatinine measures how much creatinine is actually excreted. This is important for:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Evaluating kidney function:</strong> Especially when used alongside blood tests and other urine markers.</li>
<li><strong>Normalizing other urine results:</strong> For example, in the albumin-to-creatinine ratio (ACR) to detect early kidney damage.</li>
<li><strong>Assessing muscle mass changes:</strong> Helpful in conditions that cause muscle wasting or growth.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring kidney disease progression:</strong> Regular measurements can track changes over time.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal Ranges</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<p><strong>24-hour urine collection:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Males: 955–2936 mg/24 hours (8.4–25.9 mmol/24 hours)</li>
<li>Females: 601–1689 mg/24 hours (5.3–14.9 mmol/24 hours)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Random urine sample:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Males: 20–370 mg/dL</li>
<li>Females: 20–320 mg/dL</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Values above or below these ranges aren’t automatically abnormal—athletes often have higher values due to greater muscle mass, while elderly individuals or those with muscle-wasting conditions may have lower levels.</p>
<h2>Factors Influencing Urine Creatinine</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Muscle mass:</strong> Higher mass increases creatinine production.</li>
<li><strong>Age:</strong> Levels tend to decrease as muscle mass declines.</li>
<li><strong>Diet:</strong> High protein intake or creatine supplements can temporarily raise levels.</li>
<li><strong>Exercise:</strong> Intense activity can increase production.</li>
<li><strong>Hydration status:</strong> Dehydration concentrates urine, elevating levels.</li>
<li><strong>Pregnancy:</strong> Often lowers urine creatinine due to increased filtration.</li>
<li><strong>Medications:</strong> ACE inhibitors, NSAIDs, certain antibiotics can affect results.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Optimizing Kidney Health</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stay well-hydrated—aim for at least 8 glasses of water daily, adjusting for activity and climate.</li>
<li>Control blood pressure and blood sugar—hypertension and diabetes are leading causes of kidney disease.</li>
<li>Maintain healthy muscle mass through regular, balanced exercise.</li>
<li>Eat a nutrient-rich diet—fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and limited sodium and processed foods.</li>
<li>Limit alcohol and avoid smoking to protect kidney function.</li>
<li>Discuss long-term medication use with your healthcare provider, especially NSAIDs and other drugs that can affect the kidneys.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Key Takeaway</h2>
<p>Urine creatinine is a steady, reliable indicator that helps assess kidney health, muscle mass, and the accuracy of other urine tests. Tracking it alongside other markers such as albumin can identify early kidney changes and guide preventive or therapeutic strategies.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> This information is for educational purposes only and should not replace professional medical advice. Always consult your healthcare provider for personalized interpretation of your urine creatinine results and recommendations for kidney health monitoring.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Urine Albumin:Creatinine Ratio</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-albumincreatinine-ratio/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:27:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3932</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is the Urine Albumin:Creatinine Ratio? The urine albumin:creatinine ratio (ACR) is a simple but important urine test that measures the amount of albumin (a protein) in your urine relative to creatinine (a waste product from muscle metabolism). This ratio helps standardize results for urine concentration and is one of the most reliable ways to&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-albumincreatinine-ratio/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Urine Albumin:Creatinine Ratio</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is the Urine Albumin:Creatinine Ratio?</h2>
<p>The urine albumin:creatinine ratio (ACR) is a simple but important urine test that measures the amount of albumin (a protein) in your urine relative to creatinine (a waste product from muscle metabolism). This ratio helps standardize results for urine concentration and is one of the most reliable ways to detect early kidney damage, especially in people with diabetes or high blood pressure.</p>
<h2>Understanding the Albumin:Creatinine Ratio</h2>
<p>Healthy kidneys act as selective filters, retaining essential proteins like albumin in the blood while excreting waste products into urine. When kidney filtering units (glomeruli) become damaged, they can leak albumin into the urine—a condition known as <strong>albuminuria</strong> or <strong>proteinuria</strong>. By comparing albumin to creatinine, the ACR accounts for changes in urine concentration, making it more accurate than measuring albumin alone.</p>
<h2>Why This Test Matters</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Early kidney disease detection:</strong> ACR can detect kidney damage before symptoms or standard kidney function tests show abnormalities.</li>
<li><strong>Guiding treatment:</strong> Elevated ACR levels help healthcare providers decide when to start interventions like blood pressure or blood sugar optimization, or kidney-protective medications.</li>
<li><strong>Cardiovascular risk assessment:</strong> Elevated albumin in urine is linked to higher risk of heart attack, stroke, and other vascular diseases.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal Ranges and Interpretation</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<ul>
<li><strong>Normal:</strong> &lt; 30 mg/g</li>
<li><strong>Microalbuminuria (early kidney damage):</strong> 30–300 mg/g</li>
<li><strong>Macroalbuminuria (advanced kidney damage):</strong> &gt; 300 mg/g</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Temporary factors that can elevate ACR without indicating chronic kidney damage include urinary tract infection, vigorous exercise in the past 24 hours, fever, dehydration, and menstruation. Repeat testing is often recommended to confirm abnormal results.</p>
<h2>Who Should Be Tested and How Often</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diabetes:</strong> All type 2 diabetics at diagnosis and all type 1 diabetics starting five years after diagnosis—then annually.</li>
<li><strong>Hypertension:</strong> All patients should have regular ACR screening.</li>
<li>Other groups: People over age 60, those with family history of kidney disease, cardiovascular disease, obesity, or metabolic syndrome.</li>
</ul>
<p>Testing frequency is typically once a year if results are normal, and every 3–6 months if elevated or if kidney disease is present.</p>
<h2>Protecting Kidney Health if ACR is Elevated</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Control blood pressure:</strong> Aim for &lt;130/80 mmHg; ACE inhibitors or ARBs are preferred in albuminuria.</li>
<li><strong>Manage blood sugar:</strong> Keep HbA1c below ~7% (individual targets may vary).</li>
<li><strong>Adjust diet:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Limit sodium to &lt; 2,300 mg/day</li>
<li>Moderate protein intake (0.8–1.0 g/kg/day for kidney disease)</li>
<li>Choose fresh foods over processed items high in phosphorus and potassium</li>
<li>Follow DASH or Mediterranean diet patterns</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Stay hydrated:</strong> About 6–8 glasses of water daily unless otherwise advised.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Key Takeaway</h2>
<p>The urine albumin:creatinine ratio is a critical, non-invasive tool for identifying early kidney damage and assessing cardiovascular risk. Regular testing—especially for those at higher risk—combined with proactive lifestyle changes and medical management can slow or prevent progression to chronic kidney disease and improve long-term health outcomes.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> This information is for educational purposes only and is not a substitute for professional medical advice. Always consult your healthcare provider for personalized recommendations and interpretation of your urine ACR results.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Urine Specific Gravity</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-specific-gravity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:25:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3930</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is Urine Specific Gravity? Urine specific gravity (USG) measures how concentrated your urine is by comparing the density of dissolved particles in your urine to that of pure water (which has a specific gravity of 1.000). It reflects your kidneys’ ability to concentrate or dilute urine, providing important insights into hydration status, kidney function,&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-specific-gravity/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Urine Specific Gravity</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is Urine Specific Gravity?</h2>
<p>Urine specific gravity (USG) measures how concentrated your urine is by comparing the density of dissolved particles in your urine to that of pure water (which has a specific gravity of 1.000). It reflects your kidneys’ ability to concentrate or dilute urine, providing important insights into hydration status, kidney function, and metabolic health.</p>
<h2>Why Urine Specific Gravity Matters</h2>
<p>USG helps healthcare providers evaluate:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hydration status:</strong> Detecting dehydration or overhydration.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney function:</strong> Assessing the kidneys’ ability to conserve or excrete water and solutes.</li>
<li><strong>Metabolic and systemic conditions:</strong> Identifying patterns linked to diabetes insipidus, SIADH, acute kidney injury, or chronic kidney disease.</li>
<li><strong>Fluid management:</strong> Monitoring patients receiving IV fluids or diuretics.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal Ranges and What They Mean</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<ul>
<li><strong>Normal range:</strong> 1.003 – 1.030</li>
<li><strong>Well-hydrated:</strong> 1.003 – 1.010</li>
<li><strong>Typical random sample:</strong> 1.010 – 1.025</li>
<li><strong>Concentrated (dehydrated):</strong> 1.025 – 1.030</li>
<li><strong>First morning sample:</strong> 1.015 – 1.025</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p><strong>Low USG (&lt;1.003):</strong> Possible overhydration, diabetes insipidus, kidney concentrating defects, or excessive fluid intake.<br />
<strong>High USG (&gt;1.030):</strong> Possible dehydration, glycosuria (glucose in urine), proteinuria, or recent contrast dye administration.</p>
<h2>Factors Affecting Urine Specific Gravity</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hydration status:</strong> Fluid intake is the main determinant.</li>
<li><strong>Time of collection:</strong> Morning urine tends to be more concentrated.</li>
<li><strong>Diet:</strong> High protein or sodium can increase USG.</li>
<li><strong>Medications:</strong> Diuretics, lithium, certain antibiotics may alter results.</li>
<li><strong>Medical conditions:</strong> Diabetes, heart failure, liver disease.</li>
<li><strong>Exercise:</strong> Intense activity can temporarily raise USG.</li>
<li><strong>Age:</strong> Concentrating ability decreases with age.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Optimizing Your Urine Specific Gravity</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stay well-hydrated—aim for pale yellow urine, not completely clear.</li>
<li>Adjust fluid intake based on activity, climate, and health status.</li>
<li>Eat a balanced, low-processed diet to support kidney health.</li>
<li>Manage blood pressure and blood sugar to prevent kidney damage.</li>
<li>Exercise regularly to improve circulation and kidney function.</li>
</ul>
<h2>When to Seek Medical Attention</h2>
<p>See a healthcare provider if you have:</p>
<ul>
<li>Persistent excessive thirst or urination</li>
<li>Dark urine despite good hydration</li>
<li>Foamy urine or swelling (possible protein loss)</li>
<li>Fatigue, weakness, confusion, or nausea</li>
</ul>
<h2>Testing Methods</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Refractometry:</strong> Gold standard, measures light refraction through urine.</li>
<li><strong>Dipstick test:</strong> Quick, less precise, common in clinics.</li>
<li><strong>Urinometer:</strong> Laboratory instrument for density measurement.</li>
</ul>
<p>USG is often measured alongside urinalysis parameters like pH, protein, glucose, and ketones to give a full picture of kidney and metabolic function.</p>
<p><strong>Bottom line:</strong> Urine specific gravity is a simple, non-invasive indicator of hydration and kidney health. Tracking USG over time, especially if you have kidney disease risk factors, can help identify issues early and guide lifestyle or treatment changes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Urine pH</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-ph/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:23:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3928</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is Urine pH? Urine pH measures how acidic or alkaline your urine is, using a scale from 0 to 14. A pH of 7 is neutral, values below 7 are acidic, and values above 7 are alkaline. Normal urine pH typically falls between 4.5 and 8.0, with most healthy adults having slightly acidic urine&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-ph/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Urine pH</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is Urine pH?</h2>
<p>Urine pH measures how acidic or alkaline your urine is, using a scale from 0 to 14. A pH of 7 is neutral, values below 7 are acidic, and values above 7 are alkaline. Normal urine pH typically falls between 4.5 and 8.0, with most healthy adults having slightly acidic urine in the range of 5.5–6.5. This simple biomarker offers insights into your metabolic processes, kidney function, and can flag potential conditions like urinary tract infections (UTIs) or kidney stones.</p>
<h2>Why Urine pH Matters</h2>
<p>Your kidneys help maintain your body’s acid–base balance by excreting acids or bases into urine. Shifts in urine pH can reflect dietary patterns, hydration status, medication use, or underlying health issues. Tracking urine pH over time can help identify imbalances before they cause more serious problems.</p>
<h2>Normal Ranges</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<ul>
<li><strong>Typical healthy range:</strong> 4.5–8.0</li>
<li><strong>Slightly acidic (most common):</strong> 5.5–6.5</li>
<li><strong>First morning urine:</strong> 5.0–6.0</li>
<li><strong>After meals:</strong> 7.0–8.0</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Morning urine is often more acidic due to overnight metabolism, while post-meal urine may become more alkaline due to the “alkaline tide” effect from digestion.</p>
<h2>Factors Influencing Urine pH</h2>
<h3>Diet</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Acid-forming foods:</strong> Meat, fish, eggs, dairy, grains, processed foods, alcohol</li>
<li><strong>Alkaline-forming foods:</strong> Fruits (including citrus), vegetables, nuts, legumes</li>
<li><strong>Neutral:</strong> Most fats, oils, sugars</li>
</ul>
<h3>Medical Conditions</h3>
<ul>
<li>UTIs from urease-producing bacteria (more alkaline urine)</li>
<li>Metabolic acidosis or diabetic ketoacidosis (acidic urine)</li>
<li>Kidney disease</li>
<li>Respiratory disorders affecting CO₂ balance</li>
</ul>
<h3>Medications &#038; Supplements</h3>
<ul>
<li>Alkalinizing: Antacids, potassium citrate, some diuretics</li>
<li>Acidifying: Vitamin C, methionine, certain antibiotics</li>
</ul>
<h2>Health Implications of Abnormal pH</h2>
<h3>Acidic Urine (pH &lt; 5.0)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Increased risk of uric acid or cystine kidney stones</li>
<li>Possible metabolic acidosis or diabetic ketoacidosis</li>
<li>High-protein diet, dehydration, chronic diarrhea</li>
</ul>
<h3>Alkaline Urine (pH &gt; 8.0)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Possible UTI from urease-positive bacteria</li>
<li>Increased risk of calcium phosphate or struvite stones</li>
<li>Renal tubular acidosis, prolonged vomiting</li>
</ul>
<h2>Optimizing Urine pH</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stay hydrated (8–10 glasses water/day)</li>
<li>Eat a balanced diet with plenty of fruits and vegetables</li>
<li>Limit excessive animal protein if urine is consistently acidic</li>
<li>Adjust diet for kidney stone prevention: uric acid stones (target pH 6.0–6.5), calcium phosphate stones (target pH &lt; 6.5)</li>
<li>Work with your provider if you have recurrent UTIs or kidney stones</li>
</ul>
<h2>Testing and Monitoring</h2>
<p>You can measure urine pH at home with pH test strips or through a lab urinalysis. For most accurate results, test first morning urine before eating or drinking. Lab tests also evaluate protein, glucose, ketones, and other markers for a fuller health picture.</p>
<p><strong>Bottom line:</strong> Urine pH is an easy-to-measure indicator that, when interpreted alongside other findings and symptoms, can provide valuable information about kidney function, diet, and overall metabolic health.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Leukocytes in Urine</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/leukocytes-in-urine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:21:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3926</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What are Leukocytes in Urine? Leukocytes, or white blood cells (WBCs), are immune cells that help fight infection. When they appear in urine—a condition called leukocyturia or pyuria—it usually indicates inflammation or infection somewhere in the urinary tract. In healthy individuals, urine contains very few or no white blood cells. Elevated levels detected during a&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/leukocytes-in-urine/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Leukocytes in Urine</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What are Leukocytes in Urine?</h2>
<p>Leukocytes, or white blood cells (WBCs), are immune cells that help fight infection. When they appear in urine—a condition called <strong>leukocyturia</strong> or <strong>pyuria</strong>—it usually indicates inflammation or infection somewhere in the urinary tract. In healthy individuals, urine contains very few or no white blood cells. Elevated levels detected during a urinalysis often point to conditions like urinary tract infections (UTIs), kidney infections, or other urinary system disorders that may require medical evaluation.</p>
<h2>Normal Ranges</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Normal:</strong> 0–5 WBCs per high-power field (hpf) on microscopic exam</li>
<li><strong>Borderline elevated:</strong> 6–10 WBCs/hpf</li>
<li><strong>Significant elevation:</strong> &gt;10 WBCs/hpf</li>
<li><strong>Dipstick:</strong> Negative to trace amounts considered normal</li>
</ul>
<p>Counts above 5 WBCs/hpf typically warrant further investigation, especially if accompanied by urinary symptoms.</p>
<h2>Common Causes of Leukocytes in Urine</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Urinary tract infections (UTIs):</strong> Bacterial infection of bladder (cystitis) or urethra.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney infections (pyelonephritis):</strong> More serious infections with potential fever, flank pain.</li>
<li><strong>Interstitial cystitis:</strong> Chronic bladder inflammation without bacterial cause.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney stones:</strong> Can irritate urinary tract and trigger inflammation.</li>
<li><strong>Sexually transmitted infections (STIs):</strong> Chlamydia, gonorrhea, and others.</li>
<li><strong>Prostatitis:</strong> Inflammation of the prostate gland in men.</li>
<li><strong>Pregnancy-related changes:</strong> Possible temporary elevation.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney disease:</strong> Nephritis, glomerulonephritis.</li>
<li><strong>Bladder or kidney cancer:</strong> Less common but possible cause of persistent leukocyturia.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Associated Symptoms</h2>
<p>Leukocytes in urine may be present without symptoms, but often occur with:</p>
<ul>
<li>Burning or pain during urination</li>
<li>Frequent urge to urinate</li>
<li>Cloudy or foul-smelling urine</li>
<li>Lower abdominal or back pain</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Seek immediate care</strong> if you have fever, chills, nausea, severe flank pain, blood in urine, or persistent symptoms despite initial treatment—these may indicate kidney infection or a more serious condition.</p>
<h2>Testing and Diagnosis</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dipstick urinalysis:</strong> Detects leukocyte esterase, an enzyme from WBCs.</li>
<li><strong>Microscopic exam:</strong> Directly counts WBCs in urine sediment.</li>
<li><strong>Urine culture:</strong> Identifies bacteria and guides antibiotic choice.</li>
<li><strong>Additional testing:</strong> May include imaging or specialized labs if structural or systemic disease is suspected.</li>
</ul>
<p>Proper sample collection (clean-catch, midstream) is important to avoid contamination that could produce false-positive results.</p>
<h2>Treatment</h2>
<p>Management depends on the underlying cause:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bacterial UTIs:</strong> Treated with antibiotics tailored to culture results.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney infections:</strong> Often require longer courses or intravenous antibiotics.</li>
<li><strong>Non-infectious inflammation:</strong> Addressed with targeted therapies (e.g., for stones, interstitial cystitis).</li>
<li><strong>Chronic/recurrent issues:</strong> May need prophylactic strategies or treatment of underlying risk factors.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Prevention Strategies</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stay well-hydrated.</li>
<li>Practice proper genital hygiene; wipe front to back.</li>
<li>Urinate promptly when you feel the urge; empty bladder fully.</li>
<li>Urinate before and after sexual activity.</li>
<li>Avoid irritating hygiene products in the genital area.</li>
<li>Maintain a healthy immune system with balanced diet, exercise, and adequate sleep.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Bottom line:</strong> Leukocytes in urine signal an immune response to infection or inflammation in the urinary tract. Even without symptoms, persistent leukocyturia should be evaluated to identify and treat the underlying cause, preventing complications.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nitrites in Urine</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/nitrites-in-urine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:19:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3924</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What are Nitrites in Urine? Nitrites in urine are chemical compounds that can indicate the presence of certain bacteria in the urinary tract, most commonly pointing to a urinary tract infection (UTI). A positive nitrite test means that bacteria capable of converting nitrates to nitrites are present in your urinary system, and it is often&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/nitrites-in-urine/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Nitrites in Urine</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What are Nitrites in Urine?</h2>
<p>Nitrites in urine are chemical compounds that can indicate the presence of certain bacteria in the urinary tract, most commonly pointing to a urinary tract infection (UTI). A positive nitrite test means that bacteria capable of converting nitrates to nitrites are present in your urinary system, and it is often used alongside other urinalysis markers to diagnose infection.</p>
<h2>Understanding Nitrites in Urine</h2>
<p>Normally, urine contains <strong>nitrates</strong>—harmless byproducts from dietary sources like leafy greens and beets. Some bacteria, particularly gram-negative species, produce the enzyme <em>nitrate reductase</em>, which converts nitrates to <strong>nitrites</strong>. This conversion usually takes several hours of urine being retained in the bladder, which is why first-morning urine often yields the most accurate nitrite results.</p>
<h3>Common nitrite-producing bacteria include:</h3>
<ul>
<li><em>Escherichia coli</em> (E. coli) – causes 80–90% of UTIs</li>
<li><em>Klebsiella</em> species</li>
<li><em>Proteus</em> species</li>
<li><em>Enterobacter</em> species</li>
<li><em>Citrobacter</em> species</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal Ranges and Test Interpretation</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Normal:</strong> Negative (no nitrites detected)</li>
<li><strong>Abnormal:</strong> Positive (nitrites present)</li>
</ul>
<p>A positive nitrite test has high specificity (90–100%) for certain UTIs, but a negative result doesn’t completely rule out infection. Reasons for a false negative include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Infection by non–nitrite-producing bacteria (e.g., <em>Enterococcus</em>, <em>Staphylococcus</em>)</li>
<li>Urine in bladder for less than 4 hours</li>
<li>Low dietary nitrate intake</li>
<li>Very dilute urine from high fluid intake</li>
<li>Interference from high vitamin C intake</li>
</ul>
<h2>Clinical Significance and Symptoms</h2>
<p>Positive nitrites in urine usually indicate bacteriuria and often a UTI, especially if symptoms are present:</p>
<ul>
<li>Burning or pain during urination</li>
<li>Frequent or urgent need to urinate</li>
<li>Cloudy or foul-smelling urine</li>
<li>Pelvic discomfort (women)</li>
<li>Visible blood in urine</li>
<li>Fever or chills (possible kidney involvement)</li>
</ul>
<p>In certain groups—like pregnant women, immunocompromised patients, or those scheduled for urologic procedures—positive nitrites may warrant treatment even without symptoms.</p>
<h2>Special Considerations</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pregnancy:</strong> UTIs can lead to complications like preterm labor and low birth weight—prompt treatment is essential.</li>
<li><strong>Elderly:</strong> May not show classic UTI symptoms despite positive nitrites; screening is often recommended if other signs of illness are present.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Prevention and Management</h2>
<p>If nitrites are present, your provider will typically confirm with a urine culture and prescribe antibiotics targeted to the bacteria found. To reduce recurrence risk:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stay well-hydrated and urinate regularly</li>
<li>Empty your bladder fully when urinating</li>
<li>Wipe front to back to prevent bacterial spread</li>
<li>Urinate after sexual activity</li>
<li>Avoid irritating hygiene products in the genital area</li>
<li>Discuss cranberry products or D-mannose with your provider if prone to UTIs</li>
</ul>
<p>Always finish the full course of prescribed antibiotics and follow up as advised, especially for complicated or recurrent infections.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER:</strong> A positive nitrite test should be interpreted in the context of other urinalysis results and your symptoms. Consult a healthcare provider for diagnosis and treatment recommendations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>White Blood Cells in Urine</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/white-blood-cells-in-urine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:18:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3922</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What are White Blood Cells in Urine? White blood cells (WBCs) in urine, known as pyuria, indicate inflammation or infection somewhere in the urinary tract. In healthy urine, WBCs are minimal—typically 0–5 cells per high-power field (hpf) under a microscope. Elevated counts often signal urinary tract infections (UTIs), kidney infections, stones, or other urinary conditions&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/white-blood-cells-in-urine/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">White Blood Cells in Urine</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What are White Blood Cells in Urine?</h2>
<p>White blood cells (WBCs) in urine, known as <strong>pyuria</strong>, indicate inflammation or infection somewhere in the urinary tract. In healthy urine, WBCs are minimal—typically 0–5 cells per high-power field (hpf) under a microscope. Elevated counts often signal urinary tract infections (UTIs), kidney infections, stones, or other urinary conditions that require medical evaluation.</p>
<h2>Understanding White Blood Cells in Urine</h2>
<p>WBCs are part of your immune system’s defense against harmful microorganisms. When bacteria, viruses, or other irritants are detected in the urinary tract, the body dispatches WBCs to fight the threat. Their presence in urine reflects this immune activity and can help pinpoint underlying urinary or kidney problems.</p>
<h2>Normal Ranges</h2>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<ul>
<li><strong>Normal:</strong> 0–5 WBCs/hpf</li>
<li><strong>Borderline elevated:</strong> 6–10 WBCs/hpf</li>
<li><strong>Significantly elevated:</strong> &gt;10 WBCs/hpf</li>
<li><strong>Severe pyuria:</strong> &gt;50 WBCs/hpf</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>Results above 5 WBCs/hpf generally warrant further investigation, especially if accompanied by urinary symptoms.</p>
<h2>Common Causes of Elevated WBCs in Urine</h2>
<h3>Infections</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Urinary tract infections (UTIs):</strong> Most common cause; symptoms include burning urination, urgency, cloudy urine.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney infections (pyelonephritis):</strong> Can cause fever, back pain, nausea.</li>
<li><strong>Sexually transmitted infections (STIs):</strong> Such as chlamydia, gonorrhea, trichomoniasis.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Non-infectious Causes</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Kidney stones:</strong> Irritate urinary tract lining, sometimes with secondary infection.</li>
<li><strong>Interstitial cystitis:</strong> Chronic bladder inflammation without infection.</li>
<li><strong>Prostatitis:</strong> Prostate gland inflammation in men.</li>
<li><strong>Autoimmune diseases:</strong> Lupus and others affecting the kidneys.</li>
<li><strong>Urinary tract cancers:</strong> Rare but important to rule out.</li>
<li><strong>Medication reactions:</strong> Certain antibiotics, NSAIDs.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Symptoms That May Accompany Pyuria</h2>
<ul>
<li>Painful or burning urination</li>
<li>Frequent or urgent urination</li>
<li>Cloudy or foul-smelling urine</li>
<li>Lower abdominal or back pain</li>
<li>Fever and chills</li>
<li>General fatigue</li>
</ul>
<p>Some people, especially older adults or immunocompromised individuals, may have significant pyuria without noticeable symptoms.</p>
<h2>Testing and Diagnosis</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Urinalysis:</strong> Chemical dipstick detects leukocyte esterase (WBC enzyme); microscopic exam counts cells.</li>
<li><strong>Urine culture:</strong> Identifies bacteria and antibiotic sensitivity.</li>
<li><strong>Clean-catch midstream collection:</strong> Reduces contamination from skin/genital flora.</li>
<li><strong>Additional tests:</strong> Blood work for kidney function, imaging (ultrasound, CT) for structural issues.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Treatment Approaches</h2>
<p>Depends on the cause:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bacterial infections:</strong> Antibiotics tailored to culture results.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney stones:</strong> Hydration, pain control, possible procedures to remove or break stones.</li>
<li><strong>Non-infectious inflammation:</strong> Symptom management, addressing underlying condition.</li>
<li><strong>Prostatitis:</strong> Combination of antibiotics, anti-inflammatory medications.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Prevention Strategies</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stay hydrated (8+ glasses water/day)</li>
<li>Practice good bathroom hygiene (front-to-back wiping)</li>
<li>Urinate after sexual activity</li>
<li>Avoid irritating hygiene products in genital area</li>
<li>Wear breathable cotton underwear</li>
<li>Consider cranberry products, probiotics, vitamin C, or D-mannose if prone to UTIs (consult provider first)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>When to Seek Care:</strong> See a healthcare provider promptly if WBCs in urine are accompanied by fever, severe pain, blood in urine, persistent vomiting, or symptoms lasting more than 48 hours. Early diagnosis and treatment help prevent complications.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: THIS INFORMATION IS FOR EDUCATIONAL PURPOSES AND SHOULD NOT REPLACE MEDICAL ADVICE. ALWAYS CONSULT YOUR HEALTHCARE PROVIDER FOR PERSONALIZED CARE.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Red Blood Cells in Urine</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/red-blood-cells-in-urine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3920</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What are Red Blood Cells in Urine? Red blood cells (RBCs) in urine, known as hematuria, indicate the presence of blood that normally should not be there. This can result from issues anywhere along the urinary tract—from the kidneys to the urethra. Hematuria may be visible (gross hematuria), turning urine pink, red, or cola-colored, or&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/red-blood-cells-in-urine/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Red Blood Cells in Urine</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What are Red Blood Cells in Urine?</h2>
<p>Red blood cells (RBCs) in urine, known as <strong>hematuria</strong>, indicate the presence of blood that normally should not be there. This can result from issues anywhere along the urinary tract—from the kidneys to the urethra. Hematuria may be visible (<strong>gross hematuria</strong>), turning urine pink, red, or cola-colored, or microscopic, detectable only through laboratory testing. While some causes are benign, persistent hematuria requires medical evaluation to rule out serious conditions.</p>
<h2>Understanding Red Blood Cells in Urine</h2>
<p>Under normal circumstances, the kidneys filter waste from the blood while retaining blood cells. RBCs in urine signal that the urinary tract lining has been irritated or damaged, or that the kidney&#8217;s filtering units (glomeruli) are compromised.</p>
<h2>Common Causes and Risk Factors</h2>
<h3>Urinary Tract Infections (UTIs)</h3>
<ul>
<li>Bacterial irritation of the bladder or urethra allows RBCs to leak into urine.</li>
<li>Often accompanied by burning during urination, urgency, and cloudy or odorous urine.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Kidney and Bladder Stones</h3>
<ul>
<li>Mineral deposits scrape urinary tract walls, causing bleeding.</li>
<li>May present with severe flank or abdominal pain.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Kidney Disease and Glomerulonephritis</h3>
<ul>
<li>Inflammation or damage to glomeruli allows RBCs into urine.</li>
<li>Can be related to autoimmune conditions, infections, or chronic disease.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Other Causes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Enlarged prostate (BPH) in older men</li>
<li>Strenuous exercise (“runner’s hematuria”)</li>
<li>Recent urologic procedures or catheter use</li>
<li>Certain medications (blood thinners, aspirin)</li>
<li>Inherited disorders (e.g., sickle cell disease, Alport syndrome)</li>
<li>Urinary tract cancers (bladder, kidney, prostate)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Diagnosis and Testing</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Urinalysis:</strong> Detects and counts RBCs; normal urine has &lt; 3 RBCs/high-power field.</li>
<li><strong>Urine culture:</strong> Identifies infection-causing bacteria.</li>
<li><strong>Urine cytology:</strong> Checks for abnormal or cancerous cells.</li>
<li><strong>Blood tests:</strong> Evaluate kidney function (creatinine, BUN).</li>
<li><strong>Imaging:</strong> Ultrasound, CT, or MRI to visualize kidneys, ureters, and bladder.</li>
<li><strong>Cystoscopy:</strong> Endoscopic exam of the bladder and urethra.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney biopsy:</strong> If glomerular disease is suspected.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Treatment Approaches</h2>
<p>Treatment depends on the underlying cause:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>UTIs:</strong> Antibiotics clear infection and resolve hematuria.</li>
<li><strong>Kidney stones:</strong> Increased fluids, pain control, or procedures like lithotripsy.</li>
<li><strong>BPH:</strong> Medications (alpha-blockers) or procedures to reduce prostate size.</li>
<li><strong>Glomerulonephritis:</strong> May require corticosteroids, immunosuppressants, or blood pressure control.</li>
<li><strong>Medication-related:</strong> Adjusting dose or switching drugs.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Lifestyle Support</h2>
<ul>
<li>Drink adequate fluids to dilute urine and flush the urinary tract.</li>
<li>Reduce high-oxalate foods if prone to stones.</li>
<li>Maintain healthy blood pressure.</li>
<li>Quit smoking to lower bladder cancer risk.</li>
<li>Use good hygiene to prevent UTIs.</li>
<li>Moderate intense exercise if it triggers hematuria.</li>
</ul>
<h2>When to Seek Medical Attention</h2>
<p>See a healthcare provider promptly if you notice:</p>
<ul>
<li>Visible blood in urine, even once</li>
<li>Blood with severe pain, fever, or inability to urinate</li>
<li>Blood clots in urine</li>
<li>Persistent microscopic hematuria, especially over age 40 or with cancer risk factors</li>
</ul>
<p>Early evaluation can detect treatable conditions before they progress and improve long-term outcomes.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: ANY INSTANCE OF GROSS HEMATURIA OR PERSISTENT MICROSCOPIC HEMATURIA SHOULD BE EVALUATED BY A HEALTHCARE PROFESSIONAL.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Urine Ketones</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-ketones/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 20:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3918</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What are Urine Ketones? Urine ketones are byproducts of fat metabolism that appear when your body burns fat for energy instead of glucose. They are a normal finding during fasting or on a ketogenic diet, but high levels—especially in people with diabetes—can signal diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA), a medical emergency. Understanding Ketones and Their Role in&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/urine-ketones/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Urine Ketones</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What are Urine Ketones?</h2>
<p>Urine ketones are byproducts of fat metabolism that appear when your body burns fat for energy instead of glucose. They are a normal finding during fasting or on a ketogenic diet, but high levels—especially in people with diabetes—can signal diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA), a medical emergency.</p>
<h2>Understanding Ketones and Their Role in Your Body</h2>
<p>Ketones are organic compounds produced by the liver during fat breakdown, a process called <strong>ketosis</strong>. This happens when glucose, your body&#8217;s primary fuel, is limited. There are three main types:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Acetoacetate</strong></li>
<li><strong>Beta-hydroxybutyrate</strong></li>
<li><strong>Acetone</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Under typical conditions, glucose from dietary carbohydrates fuels most cells. During fasting, prolonged exercise, low-carb eating, or certain illnesses, the body switches to fat as the primary fuel source, producing ketones that can be detected in urine, blood, or breath.</p>
<h2>Why Ketones Appear in Urine</h2>
<p>If ketone production exceeds the body’s usage, the excess is excreted in urine (<strong>ketonuria</strong>). Common causes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ketogenic or very low-carb diets</li>
<li>Extended fasting or severe calorie restriction</li>
<li>Intense or prolonged exercise</li>
<li>Pregnancy (especially with morning sickness)</li>
<li>Uncontrolled type 1 or advanced type 2 diabetes</li>
<li>Excessive alcohol intake</li>
<li>Vomiting, diarrhea, or other illnesses</li>
</ul>
<h2>Normal vs. Concerning Ketone Levels</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Normal:</strong> Negative to trace (&lt; 5 mg/dL)</li>
<li><strong>Nutritional ketosis:</strong> Small to moderate (5–40 mg/dL)</li>
<li><strong>Concerning (seek immediate care, especially if diabetic):</strong> Large (&gt; 80 mg/dL)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Testing Methods and When to Test</h2>
<p>Urine ketone testing can be done at home with test strips that change color based on ketone concentration. Steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>Collect a urine sample.</li>
<li>Dip the strip briefly into the sample.</li>
<li>Wait the instructed time.</li>
<li>Compare the strip color to the chart provided.</li>
</ol>
<p>Testing is recommended for people with diabetes when:</p>
<ul>
<li>Blood glucose is &gt; 240 mg/dL</li>
<li>Experiencing DKA symptoms: nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, fruity-smelling breath</li>
<li>During illness or infection</li>
<li>Pregnant with gestational diabetes</li>
</ul>
<p>For nutritional ketosis, many test in the morning or 3–4 hours after meals. Note: Urine testing becomes less accurate as the body adapts to ketone use.</p>
<h2>Health Implications and Management</h2>
<p>For healthy individuals, mild to moderate ketonuria during fasting or ketogenic diets is usually benign and may be linked to benefits such as fat loss and mental clarity. In diabetes, however, high ketones can mean DKA, which requires emergency care.</p>
<h3>DKA Warning Signs</h3>
<ul>
<li>High blood glucose</li>
<li>Large ketone levels</li>
<li>Rapid breathing</li>
<li>Confusion or lethargy</li>
<li>Dehydration</li>
</ul>
<h3>Managing Ketone Levels</h3>
<ul>
<li>Stay well-hydrated</li>
<li>Monitor blood glucose closely if diabetic</li>
<li>Adjust insulin per medical advice</li>
<li>Avoid strenuous exercise when ketones are high</li>
<li>Seek prompt medical care for high ketones with symptoms</li>
</ul>
<p>Regular biomarker testing—especially in people with diabetes—can help track metabolic changes and detect issues early, guiding dietary and medical decisions.</p>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: IF YOU HAVE DIABETES AND DETECT MODERATE TO HIGH KETONES, SEEK MEDICAL CARE IMMEDIATELY.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
