<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>testosterone &#8211; SiPhox Health</title>
	<atom:link href="/hub/tag/testosterone/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/hub/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 23:06:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Male Testosterone</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-male-testosterone/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 21:20:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[male testosterone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3818</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is testosterone in males? Testosterone is the primary male sex hormone, responsible for the development of male sexual characteristics and maintaining functions such as sexual health, muscle mass, bone density, and mood. It’s produced mainly in the testes and regulated by the pituitary gland. As men age, their testosterone levels naturally decline, and maintaining&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-male-testosterone/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Male Testosterone</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is testosterone in males?</h2>
<p>Testosterone is the primary male sex hormone, responsible for the development of male sexual characteristics and maintaining functions such as sexual health, muscle mass, bone density, and mood. It’s produced mainly in the testes and regulated by the pituitary gland. As men age, their testosterone levels naturally decline, and maintaining balanced testosterone is essential for overall health.</p>
<h2>Why is testosterone important?</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK526128/#:~:text=Testosterone%20is%20the%20primary%20male,characteristics%2C%20spermatogenesis%2C%20and%20fertility.)">In men</a>, testosterone regulates sex drive (libido), bone mass, fat distribution, muscle mass and strength, and the production of red blood cells and sperm.</p>
<p><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/15603-low-testosterone-male-hypogonadism">Low testosterone</a> can lead to fatigue, muscle loss, and decreased libido, while high testosterone (especially due to steroids or tumors) can have negative effects on health. Testosterone also helps maintain mood and energy levels. Men with low testosterone often report symptoms like irritability, depression, or difficulty concentrating, which can affect their quality of life.</p>
<h2>How can I better understand my testosterone levels?</h2>
<p>Total testosterone quantifies, as the name suggests, the overall quantity of testosterone including molecules that are both free (unbound) and bound to proteins (mainly <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/shbg">SHBG</a> and <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/albumin">albumin</a>).</p>
<p>Total testosterone ranges vary based on many factors, including age.</p>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<p>Normal total testosterone in males:</p>
<ul>
<li>21-49 years: 240.68 &#8211; 870.68 ng/dL</li>
<li>&gt;50 years: 220.91 &#8211; 715.81 ng/dL</li>
</ul>
<h3>SiPhox Ranges:</h3>
<table style="height: 327px;" width="594">
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>Age</strong></th>
<th><strong>Optimal Range</strong></th>
<th><strong>Good Range</strong></th>
<th><strong>Fair Range</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>20-39 yrs</strong></td>
<td>500-1150 ng/dL</td>
<td>351-1200 ng/dL</td>
<td>&lt;351 ng/dL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>40-49 yrs</strong></td>
<td>481-1000 ng/dL</td>
<td>341-1000 ng/mL</td>
<td>&lt;341 ng/dL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>50-59 yrs</strong></td>
<td>461-900 ng/dL</td>
<td>321-900 ng/dL</td>
<td>&lt;321 ng/dL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>60-69 yrs</strong></td>
<td>441-800 ng/dL</td>
<td>301-800 ng/dL</td>
<td>&lt;301 ng/dL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>&gt;70 yrs</strong></td>
<td>421-750 ng/dL</td>
<td>281-750 ng/dL</td>
<td>&lt;281 ng/dL</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
<p>Testosterone, like many hormones, follows a <a href="https://www.endocrinology.org/endocrinologist/134-winter19/features/24-hours-in-the-life-of-a-hormone-what-time-is-the-right-time-for-a-pituitary-function-test/#:~:text=TESTOSTERONE,to%20rise%20again%20at%20night.)">diurnal rhythm</a>, peaking in the morning and dipping in the early evening. Peak secretion occurs between 7 and 10 a.m., which is why testing testosterone levels in the morning helps to limit variations, particularly in younger men.</p>
<p><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/15603-low-testosterone-male-hypogonadism">Low testosterone</a> is more likely to affect those who are older, obese, have type 2 diabetes or HIV/AIDS, have sleep apnea, or have chronic conditions such as kidney or liver dysfunction. Since abnormally high or low testosterone levels may indicate problems with the testicles, pituitary gland, or hypothalamus, it is important to consult with your physician if you are concerned about your levels.</p>
<h2>How can I maintain optimal testosterone levels?</h2>
<p>If you need to maintain or adjust your testosterone levels, consider the following strategies:</p>
<p><strong>Dietary Changes:</strong>  A diet rich in lean proteins, healthy fats, antioxidant-rich foods, and hormone-supporting herbs like ginger and turmeric can support testosterone regulation. Including <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6612531/">honey</a> can help to increase lower testosterone levels. Research suggests that <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8538516/">macronutrient, vitamin, and mineral</a> intake can impact testosterone synthesis. Zinc-containing foods like oysters and pumpkin seeds can also regulate testosterone.</p>
<p><strong>Lifestyle Changes:</strong> Avoiding <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8743653/">chronic stressors</a>, getting <a href="https://www.uchicagomedicine.org/forefront/news/sleep-loss-lowers-testosterone-in-healthy-young-men#:~:text=The%20effects%20of%20sleep%20loss,2%20pm%20and%2010%20pm">more</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qJXKhu5UZwk&amp;t=2864s">higher-quality</a> sleep, and lowering <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5924956/">abdominal fat percentage</a> through a healthy regimen can help in improving testosterone levels. Additionally, engaging in regular <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11915780/">physical activity</a>, including strength training and aerobic exercise, can help support hormone balance, muscle strength, and overall well-being. Practicing stress-reducing techniques such as mindfulness, meditation, deep breathing exercises, and adequate sleep can also help support <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10253890.2021.1891220">hormone balance</a> and overall health.</p>
<p><strong>Supplementation:</strong> Supplements like <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8166567/">fenugreek seed extract, ashwagandha roots and leaves</a>, and  <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8538516/">saw palmetto or boron</a> can help to increase lower testosterone levels. <a href="https://pcosweightloss.org/does-zinc-boost-testosterone/#:~:text=Zinc%20actually%20helps%20regulate%20your,a%20good%20thing%20to%20consider!)">Adequate zinc intake</a> has also been shown to regulate both elevated and decreased hormone levels, including testosterone.</p>
<h2>Where can I learn more?</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://hubermanlab.com/the-science-of-how-to-optimize-testosterone-and-estrogen/">Andrew Huberman has a masterclass on testosterone for males.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/staying-healthy/testosterone--what-it-does-and-doesnt-do">Harvard Medical School – Testosterone: What It Is and How It Affects Your Health</a></li>
<li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/24101-testosterone">Cleveland Clinic – Testosterone</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: IF YOU ARE CONCERNED WITH ANY OF YOUR RESULTS, PLEASE CONSULT WITH YOUR PHYSICIAN.</strong></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: cce275af-244a-4937-b7be-cb6e107782c7 --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Female Testosterone</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-female-testosterone/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 21:14:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[female testosterone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3811</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is testosterone in females? While testosterone is a hormone primarily associated with male development and reproductive function, it is also present in females. Testosterone in females is an androgenic hormone produced in small amounts by the ovaries and adrenal glands. It plays a vital role in maintaining bone density, muscle mass, sexual function, and&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-female-testosterone/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Female Testosterone</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is testosterone in females?</h2>
<p>While testosterone is a hormone primarily associated with male development and reproductive function, it is also present in females. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26358173/">Testosterone in females</a> is an androgenic hormone produced in small amounts by the ovaries and adrenal glands. It plays a vital role in maintaining bone density, muscle mass, sexual function, and overall energy levels. While women have much lower testosterone levels than men, this hormone is still essential for health and vitality.</p>
<p>Testosterone also serves as a precursor to estrogen, which plays a significant role in the menstrual cycle and reproductive health.</p>
<h2>Why is testosterone important?</h2>
<p>Testosterone supports sexual desire, bone health, muscle strength, and mood in women. Low testosterone levels can contribute to fatigue, low libido, and muscle weakness, while high testosterone levels are associated with conditions like <a href="https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/polycystic-ovary-syndrome-pcos/causes/">PCOS</a>, leading to symptoms such as excessive hair growth, acne, and menstrual irregularities.</p>
<p>Proper testosterone levels are essential for maintaining optimal health, especially as women age.</p>
<h2>How can I better understand my testosterone levels?</h2>
<p>Total testosterone in females can vary depending on age, health status, and testing methods. Higher than normal testosterone levels in females, known as <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8548673/">hyperandrogenism</a>, may indicate conditions such as polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), adrenal disorders, ovarian tumors, or certain medications. Further evaluation, including additional tests and medical history assessment, may be necessary to determine the underlying cause. Lower than normal testosterone levels in females may result from conditions such as primary ovarian insufficiency (early menopause), adrenal insufficiency, pituitary disorders, or certain medications. Additional testing and medical evaluation are essential to identify the underlying cause and determine appropriate management.</p>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<h3>Lab Range:</h3>
<ul>
<li>In range: 0-0.75 ng/mL</li>
<li>Out of range (high): &gt;0.75 ng/mL</li>
</ul>
<h3>SiPhox Range:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Optimal Range: 0.1-0.3 ng/mL</li>
<li>Good Range: 0.3-0.4 ng/mL</li>
<li>Fair Range: 0.05-0.1 ng/mL or 0.4-0.9 ng/mL</li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2>How can I maintain optimal testosterone levels?</h2>
<p>Maintaining balanced testosterone levels in women involves the following steps:</p>
<p><strong>Dietary Changes:</strong> A diet rich in lean proteins, healthy fats, antioxidant-rich foods, and hormone-supporting herbs like ginger and turmeric can support testosterone regulation. Including <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6612531/">honey</a> can help to increase lower testosterone levels. Spearmint tea may reduce excess testosterone, especially in women with conditions like PCOS. Zinc-containing foods like oysters and pumpkin seeds can also regulate testosterone.</p>
<p><strong>Lifestyle Changes:</strong>  Avoiding <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8743653/">chronic stressors</a>, getting <a href="https://www.uchicagomedicine.org/forefront/news/sleep-loss-lowers-testosterone-in-healthy-young-men#:~:text=The%20effects%20of%20sleep%20loss,2%20pm%20and%2010%20pm">more</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qJXKhu5UZwk&amp;t=2864s">higher-quality</a> sleep, and lowering <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5924956/">abdominal fat percentage</a> through a healthy regimen can help improve testosterone levels. Additionally, engaging in regular <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11915780/">physical activity</a>, including strength training and aerobic exercise, can help support hormone balance, muscle strength, and overall well-being. Practicing stress-reducing techniques such as mindfulness, meditation, deep breathing exercises, and adequate sleep can also help support <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10253890.2021.1891220">hormone balance</a> and overall health.</p>
<p><strong>Supplementation:</strong> Consuming <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8538516/">saw palmetto or boron</a> supplements can aid in increasing low testosterone in women. <strong>These supplements are not recommended in pregnancy or for individuals with kidney disease.</strong></p>
<h2>Where can I learn more?</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26358173/">PubMed &#8211; Testosterone in Women</a></li>
<li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/24897-low-testosterone-in-women">Cleveland Clinic &#8211; Low Testosterone in Women</a></li>
<li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/24639-hyperandrogenism">Cleveland Clinic &#8211; Hyperandrogenism in Women</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: IF YOU ARE CONCERNED WITH ANY OF YOUR RESULTS, PLEASE CONSULT WITH YOUR PHYSICIAN.</strong></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: 337663ee-5a29-4fce-9ab8-632161b5939a --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Free Testosterone</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-free-testosterone/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 20:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free testosterone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/hub/?p=3808</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[

What is free testosterone? Free testosterone is the fraction of testosterone in the blood that is not bound to proteins such as SHBG and albumin. This bioactive form of testosterone plays a crucial role in many physiological processes, including sexual health, muscle mass, bone density, and mood regulation. Unlike total testosterone, free testosterone is the&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-free-testosterone/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Free Testosterone</span></a>]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2>What is free testosterone?</h2>
<p>Free testosterone is the fraction of testosterone in the blood that is not bound to proteins such as <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-sex-hormone-binding-globulin-shbg">SHBG</a> and <a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/pages/albumin">albumin</a>. This bioactive form of testosterone plays a crucial role in many physiological processes, including sexual health, muscle mass, bone density, and mood regulation. Unlike total testosterone, free testosterone is the portion that is readily available to the body’s tissues to exert its effects.</p>
<p>In <strong>males</strong>, testosterone is primarily produced by the testes, under the regulation of the pituitary gland. Although only 1–2% of the testosterone in a man’s body is free, it is essential for driving bodily functions. Free testosterone levels naturally decline as men age, but maintaining balanced testosterone is crucial for overall health and vitality. In <strong>females,</strong> testosterone is primarily produced by the ovaries and adrenal glands. Even small fluctuations in free testosterone can have a significant impact on health, including symptoms such as low libido, fatigue, and muscle weakness.</p>
<h2>Why is free testosterone important?</h2>
<p>Free testosterone is essential for:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Males</strong>: sexual health, sperm production, muscle growth, bone density, mood, and vitality.</li>
<li><strong>Females</strong>: libido, lean muscle maintenance, energy, emotional stability, and bone strength.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Low free testosterone</strong> in either sex can lead to fatigue, reduced muscle mass, low libido, and mood imbalances even if total testosterone appears normal.</p>
<p><strong>High free testosterone</strong> can also signal problems:</p>
<ul>
<li>In men: is often seen in exogenous steroid users and can cause acne, aggression, or hair loss.</li>
<li>In women: may indicate conditions like <a href="https://www.nhs.uk/conditions/polycystic-ovary-syndrome-pcos/causes/">PCOS</a>, and cause hirsutism, acne, or irregular periods.</li>
</ul>
<h2>How can I better understand my free testosterone levels?</h2>
<p>Free testosterone is typically tested alongside total testosterone to assess hormonal activity. Levels vary by:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Age</strong> (typically decreasing over time)</li>
<li><strong>Time of day</strong> (highest in the early morning due to <a href="https://www.endocrinology.org/endocrinologist/134-winter19/features/24-hours-in-the-life-of-a-hormone-what-time-is-the-right-time-for-a-pituitary-function-test/#:~:text=TESTOSTERONE">diurnal rhythm</a>)</li>
<li><strong>Sex</strong>, menstrual cycle (in females), and menopausal status</li>
</ul>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<h3>Lab Ranges:</h3>
<p><strong>Male:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Out of range (low): &lt;0.03 ng/mL</li>
<li>In range: 0.03-0.2 ng/mL</li>
<li>Out of range (high): &gt;0.2 ng/mL</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Female:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Out of range (low): &lt;1.1 pg/mL</li>
<li>In range: 1.1-12.9 pg/mL</li>
<li>Out of range (high): &gt;12.9 pg/mL</li>
</ul>
<h3>SiPhox Ranges:</h3>
<p><strong>Male:</strong></p>
<table style="height: 348px;" width="710">
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>Age</strong></th>
<th><strong>Optimal Range</strong></th>
<th><strong>Good Range</strong></th>
<th><strong>Fair Range</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>20-39 yrs</td>
<td>0.13-0.30 ng/mL</td>
<td>0.08-0.30 ng/mL</td>
<td>&gt;0.05 ng/mL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40-49 yrs</td>
<td>0.1-0.29 ng/mL</td>
<td>0.06-0.29 ng/mL</td>
<td>&gt;0.04 ng/mL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50-59 yrs</td>
<td>0.1-0.28 ng/mL</td>
<td>0.06-0.28 ng/mL</td>
<td>&gt;0.04 ng/mL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>60-69 yrs</td>
<td>0.09-0.27 ng/mL</td>
<td>0.05-0.27 ng/mL</td>
<td>&gt;0.03 ng/mL</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>&gt;70 yrs</td>
<td>0.08-0.26 ng/mL</td>
<td>0.04-0.26 ng/mL</td>
<td>&gt;0.03 ng/mL</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Female:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Good Range: 1.1-12.9 pg/mL</li>
</ul>
</div>
<h2>How can I maintain optimal free testosterone levels?</h2>
<p><strong>Dietary Changes:</strong>  A diet rich in lean proteins, healthy fats, antioxidant-rich foods, and hormone-supporting herbs like ginger and turmeric can support testosterone regulation. Including <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6612531/">honey</a> can help to increase lower testosterone levels. Research suggests that <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8538516/">macronutrient, vitamin, and mineral</a> intake can impact testosterone synthesis. Spearmint tea may reduce excess testosterone, especially in women with conditions like PCOS. Zinc-containing foods like oysters and pumpkin seeds can also regulate testosterone.</p>
<p><strong>Lifestyle Changes:</strong> Avoiding <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8743653/">chronic stressors</a>, getting <a href="https://www.uchicagomedicine.org/forefront/news/sleep-loss-lowers-testosterone-in-healthy-young-men#:~:text=The%20effects%20of%20sleep%20loss,2%20pm%20and%2010%20pm">more</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qJXKhu5UZwk&amp;t=2864s">higher-quality</a> sleep, and lowering <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5924956/">abdominal fat percentage</a> through a healthy regimen can help in improving testosterone levels. Additionally, engaging in regular <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/11915780/">physical activity</a>, including strength training and aerobic exercise, can help support hormone balance, muscle strength, and overall well-being. Practicing stress-reducing techniques such as mindfulness, meditation, deep breathing exercises, and adequate sleep can also help support <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/10253890.2021.1891220">hormone balance</a> and overall health.</p>
<p><strong>Supplementation:</strong> Supplements like <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8166567/">fenugreek seed extract, ashwagandha roots and leaves</a>, and  <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8538516/">saw palmetto or boron</a> can help to increase lower free testosterone levels. <a href="https://pcosweightloss.org/does-zinc-boost-testosterone/#:~:text=Zinc%20actually%20helps%20regulate%20your,a%20good%20thing%20to%20consider!">Adequate zinc intake</a> has also been shown to regulate both elevated and decreased hormone levels, including testosterone. <strong>These supplements are not recommended in pregnancy or for individuals with kidney disease.</strong></p>
<h2>Where can I learn more?</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://hubermanlab.com/the-science-of-how-to-optimize-testosterone-and-estrogen/">Andrew Huberman has a masterclass on testosterone for males.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/staying-healthy/testosterone--what-it-does-and-doesnt-do">Harvard Medical School – Testosterone: What It Is and How It Affects Your Health</a></li>
<li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/articles/24101-testosterone">Cleveland Clinic – Testosterone</a></li>
<li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26358173/">PubMed &#8211; Testosterone in Women</a></li>
<li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/24897-low-testosterone-in-women">Cleveland Clinic &#8211; Low Testosterone in Women</a></li>
<li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/24639-hyperandrogenism">Cleveland Clinic &#8211; Hyperandrogenism in Women</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>DISCLAIMER: IF YOU ARE CONCERNED WITH ANY OF YOUR RESULTS, PLEASE CONSULT WITH YOUR PHYSICIAN.</strong></p>
<p><!-- notionvc: b8a1f3ef-ee54-45ca-92ec-b8f12c58455f --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DHEA-S</title>
		<link>/hub/biomarkers-2/biomarker-dhea-s-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[SiPhox Health Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 20:25:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biomarkers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blood test]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DHEA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DHEA-S]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[estrogen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[testosterone]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hub.siphoxhealth.com/?p=2936</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[DHEA-S is a hormone that serves as a precursor for testosterone and estrogen, the primary sex hormones for males and females. As a result, DHEA-S levels can provide a glimpse into an individual's sexual and reproductive health.]]></description>
			

							<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">What is DHEA-S?</span></h3>
<p><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.urmc.rochester.edu/encyclopedia/content.aspx?contenttypeid=167&amp;contentid=dhea" data-sanitized-target="_blank">DHEA</a></span> (dehydroepiandrosterone) is a hormone produced primarily by the adrenal glands of the kidneys, but also by the ovaries and testes in smaller amounts, and converted into DHEA-S (<span data-sanitized-data-mce-fragment="1">dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate) by the adrenal glands and liver</span>. DHEA-S serves as a precursor for testosterone and estrogen, the primary sex hormones for males and females.</span></p>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Why is DHEA-S important?</span></h3>
<p><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">DHEA-S levels provide a glimpse into sexual and reproductive health given its connection with testosterone and estrogen. DHEA-S is currently included in the <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://siphoxhealth.com/" data-sanitized-target="_blank">SiPhox Health</a></span> male base panel as well as the female Hormone+ panel. It serves as a good <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.labcorp.com/tests/004020/dehydroepiandrosterone-dhea-sulfate" data-sanitized-target="_blank" data-sanitized-data-mce-href="https://www.labcorp.com/tests/004020/dehydroepiandrosterone-dhea-sulfate">indicator</a></span> of overall adrenal function and can potentially point toward adrenal tumors or hyperplasia (enlargement).</span></p>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">How can I better understand my results?</span></h3>
<p><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><span data-sanitized-data-mce-fragment="1">Generally, it is advisable to fall within the higher end of the normal range. To assist in interpreting results, <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.mountsinai.org/health-library/tests/dhea-sulfate-test#:~:text=Normal%20Results&amp;text=Ages%2018%20to%2019%3A%20145,0.86%20to%206.48%20%C2%B5mol%2FL" data-sanitized-target="_blank">Mount</a></span></span><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.mountsinai.org/health-library/tests/dhea-sulfate-test#:~:text=Normal%20Results&amp;text=Ages%2018%20to%2019%3A%20145,0.86%20to%206.48%20%C2%B5mol%2FL" data-sanitized-target="_blank"> Sinai</a></span> established normal ranges of DHEA-S broken down by age and sex:</span></p>
<div data-dynamic-ranges="true" data-test="1"></div>
<div data-ranges="true">
<span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><strong>Male</strong>:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Age 18-19: 108-441 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Age 20-29: 280-640 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Age 30-39: 120-520 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Age 40-49: 95-530 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Age 50-59: 70-310 ug/dL</span></li>
<li>Age 60-69: 42-290 ug/dL</li>
<li>Age 69+: 28-175 ug/dL</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Female</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0">Age 18-19: 145-395 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0">Age 20-29: 65-380 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0">Age 30-39: 45-270 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0">Age 40-49: 32-240 ug/dL</span></li>
<li><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0">Age 50-59: 26-200 ug/dL</span></li>
<li>Age 60-69: 13-130 ug/dL</li>
<li>Age 69+: 17-90 ug/dL</li>
</ul>
</div>
<p>According to <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://medlineplus.gov/lab-tests/dhea-sulfate-test/" data-sanitized-target="_blank">MedlinePlus</a></span>, abnormally high DHEA-S may be caused by adrenal hyperplasia, adrenal tumors, or PCOS in females, while low levels may indicate Addison&#8217;s disease or hypopituitarism. It is important to consult with your physician if you are concerned with your results.</p>
<h3>How can I maintain optimal DHEA-S levels?</h3>
<p>If you have low DHEA-S, here are some lifestyle modifications you can try:</p>
<p><strong>Lifestyle Changes: </strong>If you want to increase your DHEA-S levels, studies have shown that practicing <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8604255/">MSBR</a></span> (mindfulness-based stress reduction) such as through yoga or meditation may help. DHEA-S levels can also be raised through regular exercise, especially with <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://physoc.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1113/EP085361">high-intensity interval training</a></span> (HIIT).</p>
<p><strong>Supplementation:</strong> If you have low DHEA-S levels, supplementing with <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6438434/">ashwagandha</a></span> may help.</p>
<p>If you have elevated DHEA-S levels, you can try:</p>
<p><strong>Lifestyle Changes: </strong>If you wish to lower your DHEA-S levels, practicing <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/14/11/2343">intermittent fasting</a></span> may help.</p>
<p><strong>Supplementation: </strong>Consuming fish oil and vitamin E supplements may help in decreasing elevated DHEA-S levels.</p>
<h3><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot="">Where can I learn more?</span></h3>
<ul>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><a class="notion-link-token notion-enable-hover" href="https://hubermanlab.com/the-science-of-how-to-optimize-testosterone-and-estrogen/" data-sanitized-target="_blank" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id--1590225648">Andrew Huberman touches on DHEA in this episode on testosterone</span></a></span></span></li>
<li><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span class="notion-enable-hover" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><a class="notion-link-token notion-enable-hover" href="https://www.mountsinai.org/health-library/supplement/dehydroepiandrosterone" data-sanitized-target="_blank" data-sanitized-data-token-index="0" data-token-index="0" data-sanitized-data-reactroot="" data-reactroot=""><span class="link-annotation-unknown-block-id-854033424">Mount Sinai has great educational material on DHEA</span></a></span></span></li>
</ul>
<p data-sanitized-data-mce-fragment="1"><strong data-sanitized-data-mce-fragment="1">DISCLAIMER: IF YOU ARE CONCERNED WITH ANY OF YOUR RESULTS, PLEASE CONSULT WITH YOUR PHYSICIAN.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
